<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">Our evaluation focuses on the community of Arviat, Nunavut. Nunavut is the newest territory in Canada, established in 1999 by the Nunavut Land Claims Agreement (Government of Nunavut 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2014</xref>) (population: 37,315, 84% Inuit). The territory is spread across 1.9 million km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and contains 26 small communities, all of which are accessible only by plane or by boat in summer months (Government of Nunavut 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2016</xref>; Nunavut Bureau of Statistics 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2015</xref>). Nunavut has warmed by between 1.6 and 2.6 °C since the 1960s (Environment Canada, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2015</xref>), permafrost temperature across the territory has seen a warming of between 0.04 and 0.25 °C per year since 2008 (Ednie and Smith 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2015</xref>). The community of Arviat (population: 2514, 94% Inuit), is located on the west coast of Hudson Bay (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Arviat is situated on continuous permafrost, and existing infrastructure is exhibiting signs of impact as a result of permafrost thaw, including frost jacking, thaw settlement and possible instability related to saline permafrost (Forbes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2014</xref>). Importantly, the community is growing rapidly, with a projected increase in population of &gt; 60% in the next 20 years (Nunavut Bureau of Statistics 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2015</xref>) and there is a high demand for new housing (Forbes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2014</xref>). Arviat completed hazard mapping to help identify suitable areas for future development and was selected for this evaluation because the community was a major hub for the ICCiLD project and received additional community outreach work.
</p>
