<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic variables</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Precipitation, temperature, relative humidity, and wind velocity are part of the essential climate variables (ECV) identified by the Global Climate Observing System (GCOS) as relevant for understanding the climatic system (Mason et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2010</a>). Climatic data in Ecuador are spatially heterogeneous as a result of geophysical factors; however, their availability is limited. The coarse resolution of global circulation models (GCM) does not allow reliable geographic interpolations or aggregations. Thus, to incorporate the spatial and temporal pattern of the climatic indicators we use reanalysis datasets that are the outcome of numerical models and observational data assimilation with a finer resolution than the GCM.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatic variables come from the climate forecast system reanalysis (CFSR) developed by the National Center for Environmental Prediction (NCEP). This reanalysis model is the first that includes both oceanic and atmospheric features, and has demonstrated that it adequately reproduces precipitation and surface temperature, and calibrates for the natural and inter-seasonal variability (Saha et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2010</a>; Tett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1997</a>). The ECVs are on a monthly basis for a range of 40 years (1971–2011) and are extracted in a rectangular grid (83 W–74 W, 2 N–6 S). The NCEP reanalysis dataset coincides with the climate observation satellite area, which implies that reliable observations are added in the assimilation process (Kanamitsu et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2002</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four climatic indices were constructed to describe the trends of the climatic variables. The dataset was divided into two regions: western Ecuador (coastal zone) and eastern Ecuador (the Inter-Andean and Amazon regions). Thus, we implemented the EOF for the monthly variation of each climatic variable at canton level, except for precipitation, where we used the yearly averages because there were only 4 or 5 months with positive values of precipitation, whereas for the rest of the year the monthly values were equal to zero. This variation does not significantly affect the results. For computational purposes we use the EOF as the dimensions of reanalysis datasets are large since they combine time series with spatial maps. The EOF characterizes the temporal and spatial patterns of the climatic variables in the areas of interest, and have been used extensively in meteorological and climatological studies (Dai et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">1997</a>; Kutzbach 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1967</a>; Messié and Chavez 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2011</a>; Tatli and Türkeş 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2011</a>; von Storch and Navarra 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">1999</a>). The EOF is equivalent to the principal components used in multivariate statistics and is close relative to the bases used in factor analysis. Furthermore, the EOF basis set defined directly from data can be used to represent a climatological field very economically (Kutzbach 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1967</a>), both as a basis for a set of predictors (Barnett and Hasselmann 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1979</a>) or as a means of physically interpreting the data (Wallace and Gutzler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">1981</a>). That is, if one thinks of the snapshots of geophysical data maps as realizations of random fields generated by a stochastic process, it is possible to construct second moment statistics linking one point and another in the map. The resulting covariance matrix is real and symmetric and therefore possesses a set of orthogonal eigenvectors with positive eigenvalues. The map associated with each eigenvector represents a pattern that is statistically independent of the others and spatially orthogonal to them. The eigenvalue indicates the amount of variance accounted for by the pattern. The eigenvector patterns contain information about the multidimensional probability distribution that constitutes the climate and are, therefore, of theoretical interest (North 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">1984</a>). Thus, the EOF is designed to derive the dominant variability patterns from sets of fields of any type of synthetic indicators or indexes, and summarize the variability observed in a group of variables (Bultó et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2006</a>; Thomson and Emery 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
