<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier work has documented the extensive range of tools to assess climate change vulnerability at local levels. The use of any tool depends on the research questions to be answered. Vulnerability assessments, through the indicators approach, provide an overview of the socioeconomic, climatic, and geophysical determinants for a canton, or any other geographic unit, that are vulnerable to climate change. In this paper we use an approach that enables the relative ordering of the cantons in the continental territory of Ecuador. Our aim is to make full use of the climatic and non-climatic features, and construct additional indicators related to exposure, sensitivity, and adaptive capacity to climate change (Pachauri et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2014</a>). Our approach allows us to capture the multi-dimensionality of vulnerability in a comprehensive framework (Leichenko and O’Brien 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2002</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To construct the composite vulnerability indicator we use a large number of variables. Thus, in order to attain a meaningful and theoretically consistent vulnerability indicator, we normalize the variables and calculate the weights based on their relative variability. The weights represent their contribution to the formation of the composite indicator.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As it was not possible to apply standard modelling procedures to climatic data, because of the data’s unavailability or coarse resolution, we use a reanalysis strategy where the EOF incorporates spatial and temporal patterns. The composite indicator is bounded between 0 and 1 and takes the form of ratios, thus we assume it follows a beta distribution. It may be argued that this assumption does not apply to every dataset and context, but if a priori we assumed a normal distribution we would lose generality and incur potential specification errors if asymmetries arose. By assuming a beta distribution we leave open the possibility of approximating the beta to a normal distribution in case the parameters 
  <div id="IEq32" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M75" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$a$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M76" class="math">
     <span class="mi">a</span>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="40064_2015_1536_Article_IEq32.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> and 
  <div id="IEq33" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M77" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$b$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M78" class="math">
     <span class="mi">b</span>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="40064_2015_1536_Article_IEq33.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> are approximately equal (Iyengar and Sudarshan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">1982</a>). The errors from this approximation are negligible (Pratt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">1968</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The institutional capacity of the cantons has the largest contribution to the formation of the composite indicator. Though we did not observe significant differences across the vulnerability categories, we argue that the availability of environmental- and climate-change-related policies improve the adaptive capacity. These policies serve to anticipate the impacts of climate change and form potential responses. However, this indicator does not capture the nature and extent of those policies. For this we use as a proxy the funds per capita allocated to environmental protection. Results showed that there is a wide variation in the less vulnerable category, thus we cannot reach a conclusion that funds are significantly larger for the cantons in this category. However, getting allocation of funds in general from the central government is often the outcome of an intense lobbying process that depends on the relative economic and political importance of each canton. As the less vulnerable category includes some of Ecuador’s largest cantons (e.g. Guayaquil and Quito) along with others that are much smaller (e.g. Mejía and Marcelino Maridueña), we argue that correcting by economy and population size, both institutional capabilities and greater funds for environmental development can determine whether a canton is less vulnerable to climate change.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier work has shown that variables such as the proportion of households with sewage treatment service, with garbage collection service, and with access to water through piped system indicate both poverty levels and development (Baker 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2004</a>; Feitelson and Chenoweth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2002</a>). Thus, we found that those cantons in the least vulnerable category are also those with higher coverage of these public services. In addition, the proportion of population working in agriculture, hunting or fisheries and the proportion of households on owning agricultural land are associated with local economic capabilities and opportunities. Results show that these indicators are among the ten largest contributions to the composite indicator. That is, vulnerability in Ecuador is also influenced by the concentration of economic activities related to agriculture, which limits other economic activities and the ability of people to shift in response to reduced agricultural income that may result from adverse climatic conditions. Some implications of these results arise: first, land tenure promotes economic development and reduces vulnerability as economic deprivation, in an adverse climatic event, is partially resolved by selling land assets. In addition, as agricultural work does not necessarily demand academic qualifications or schooling, this affects human capital accumulation and implies reduced adaptive capacity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For cantons in the highly and very highly vulnerable categories, at least 50 % of the population works in agriculture, hunting or fisheries. With a weaker contribution to the composite indicator, the proportion of agricultural land that is irrigated has the fourteenth largest contribution. To this we add that 64 % of Ecuador’s population (9.3 million individuals) lives in cantons that are considered highly and very highly exposed. Thus, small holder and subsistence farmers will suffer impacts of climate change that will be locally specific and hard to predict. Hence, the variety of crop and livestock species produced by any one household, and their interactions in production and marketing, will increase the complexity both of the impacts and of subsequent adaptations (Morton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2007</a>). In addition, approximately 20 % of the population (2.9 million individuals) live in cantons with high and very high vulnerability mainly because of the limitations of adaptive capacity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the largest cantons in Ecuador (Quito, Guayaquil, and Machala) show a very high adaptive capacity, given their development infrastructure, which may spill into surrounding cantons. However, it is not possible to conclude that there is a strong correlation between population size and adaptive capacity because mid-size cantons such as El Empalme and Santa Elena are categorized as highly vulnerable. Furthermore, we cannot generalize that proximity to the largest cantons will guarantee coverage of public services, for example, Salitre and Nobol, which, despite their close proximity to Guayaquil (on average 20 miles), appear as highly vulnerable.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For policy purposes, particular attention should be directed to the low coverage of health services, private health insurance, and social security. Though coverage may have increased since data collection, it may not be at a high enough level to guarantee adequate adaptive capacity in most of the cantons analysed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some limitations are worth mentioning. First, we do not include the Galapagos Islands, as their climatic features are different from Ecuadorian continental territory. Second, though we do not intend to compete with other vulnerability approaches and have not developed a formal comparison test with PCA, a research path would be to assess how different weighting of indicators influence interpretation and to identify the potential links to planning, prioritization, decision-making, and monitoring over time, given the dynamic nature of vulnerability (Bele et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>). Third, we did not take a particular focus on agriculture or rural areas. Future economic or demographic impact analysis would certainly complement the extent of the implications of this study.
 </p>
</sec>
