<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vulnerability indicators</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the mid-1990s the approach to vulnerability changed from an exclusive focus on meteorological and biophysical factors to a comprehensive approach that included social, economic, and political dimensions (Blaikie et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2004</a>; Bohle et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">1994</a>; Cutter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1996</a>; Kelly and Adger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2000</a>). We separated the variables into the exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity indicators of each canton. For appropriate selection of the variables we held extensive discussions and a workshop with experts both in Ecuador and at the headquarters of the Inter-American Development Bank, Washington DC. Thus, we selected 42 variables and did not attempt to reduce dimensions (e.g. via principal components analysis) as our interest is to identify the effects of each variable on the formation of the composite indicator.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic variables</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Precipitation, temperature, relative humidity, and wind velocity are part of the essential climate variables (ECV) identified by the Global Climate Observing System (GCOS) as relevant for understanding the climatic system (Mason et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2010</a>). Climatic data in Ecuador are spatially heterogeneous as a result of geophysical factors; however, their availability is limited. The coarse resolution of global circulation models (GCM) does not allow reliable geographic interpolations or aggregations. Thus, to incorporate the spatial and temporal pattern of the climatic indicators we use reanalysis datasets that are the outcome of numerical models and observational data assimilation with a finer resolution than the GCM.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatic variables come from the climate forecast system reanalysis (CFSR) developed by the National Center for Environmental Prediction (NCEP). This reanalysis model is the first that includes both oceanic and atmospheric features, and has demonstrated that it adequately reproduces precipitation and surface temperature, and calibrates for the natural and inter-seasonal variability (Saha et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2010</a>; Tett et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1997</a>). The ECVs are on a monthly basis for a range of 40 years (1971–2011) and are extracted in a rectangular grid (83 W–74 W, 2 N–6 S). The NCEP reanalysis dataset coincides with the climate observation satellite area, which implies that reliable observations are added in the assimilation process (Kanamitsu et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2002</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four climatic indices were constructed to describe the trends of the climatic variables. The dataset was divided into two regions: western Ecuador (coastal zone) and eastern Ecuador (the Inter-Andean and Amazon regions). Thus, we implemented the EOF for the monthly variation of each climatic variable at canton level, except for precipitation, where we used the yearly averages because there were only 4 or 5 months with positive values of precipitation, whereas for the rest of the year the monthly values were equal to zero. This variation does not significantly affect the results. For computational purposes we use the EOF as the dimensions of reanalysis datasets are large since they combine time series with spatial maps. The EOF characterizes the temporal and spatial patterns of the climatic variables in the areas of interest, and have been used extensively in meteorological and climatological studies (Dai et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">1997</a>; Kutzbach 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1967</a>; Messié and Chavez 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2011</a>; Tatli and Türkeş 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2011</a>; von Storch and Navarra 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">1999</a>). The EOF is equivalent to the principal components used in multivariate statistics and is close relative to the bases used in factor analysis. Furthermore, the EOF basis set defined directly from data can be used to represent a climatological field very economically (Kutzbach 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1967</a>), both as a basis for a set of predictors (Barnett and Hasselmann 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1979</a>) or as a means of physically interpreting the data (Wallace and Gutzler 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">1981</a>). That is, if one thinks of the snapshots of geophysical data maps as realizations of random fields generated by a stochastic process, it is possible to construct second moment statistics linking one point and another in the map. The resulting covariance matrix is real and symmetric and therefore possesses a set of orthogonal eigenvectors with positive eigenvalues. The map associated with each eigenvector represents a pattern that is statistically independent of the others and spatially orthogonal to them. The eigenvalue indicates the amount of variance accounted for by the pattern. The eigenvector patterns contain information about the multidimensional probability distribution that constitutes the climate and are, therefore, of theoretical interest (North 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">1984</a>). Thus, the EOF is designed to derive the dominant variability patterns from sets of fields of any type of synthetic indicators or indexes, and summarize the variability observed in a group of variables (Bultó et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2006</a>; Thomson and Emery 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2014</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity and adaptive capacity indicators</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> shows the socioeconomic indicators related to sensitivity and adaptive capacity. The indicators related to human capital, family structure, physical infrastructure, economic capability, socially vulnerable groups, demographics, and employment come from the National System of Indicators (SNI in Spanish) (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sni.gob.ec" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.sni.gob.ec</span>). The SNI contains data from several national-level census and surveys administered in Ecuador. Housing tenure and housing characteristics information comes from the 2010 National Population and Household Census. Institutional capacity indicators are constructed based on the 2010 Census for the Management, Expenditures and Investment on Environmental Protection at Municipalities and Provincial Councils. Agricultural information such as the proportion of agricultural land with respect to total area, the proportion of agricultural land with irrigation, as well as tenure of agricultural land comes from the 2010 National Agricultural Census. Information about medical doctors and staff comes from the 2009 Health Resources and Activities Census.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Vulnerability indicators</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">Focus</th>
       <th align="left">Indicators</th>
       <th align="left">Source</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" colspan="3">Sensitivity</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="3"> Demographics</td>
       <td align="left">Illiteracy rate (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Population density (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Unemployment rate (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="5"> Socially vulnerable groups</td>
       <td align="left">Average number of children per household (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of crowded households (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population 0–5 years (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population 65 years or older (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population with permanent disability (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="2"> Land</td>
       <td align="left">Proportion agricultural land/total land extension (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NAC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion irrigated land/total agricultural land (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" colspan="3">Adaptive capacity</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="12"> Physical infrastructure</td>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households receiving water through piped system (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with access to computer (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with electricity service (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with garbage collection service (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with land phone service (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with proper sanitary facilities (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households with sewage treatment service (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of houses with exclusive room for kitchen (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of houses with exclusive sanitary facilities (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population with internet access (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population with mobile phone access (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Minimum distance to large town (−)
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="7"> Economic capability</td>
       <td align="left">Average business revenues (−)</td>
       <td align="left">EC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Average energy consumption (Kwh/annum) (−)</td>
       <td align="left">EC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Average time in business (−)</td>
       <td align="left">EC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population working in own business (−) (amb)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households on agriculture owning land (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population working agriculture, hunting or fisheries (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Tax revenues per capita (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="8"> Human capital</td>
       <td align="left">Hospital beds per capita (−)</td>
       <td align="left">HRAC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Population per medical doctor (+)</td>
       <td align="left">HRAC</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Average number of years of scholarity for head of household (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households living on owned house (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of households where head is female (+)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population under social security coverage (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population with private health insurance (−)</td>
       <td align="left">NSI</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Proportion of population affected by disasters (+)</td>
       <td align="left">DIMS</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="2"> Institutional capacity</td>
       <td align="left">Funds for environmental protection per capita (−)</td>
       <td align="left">EMS</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Institutional capacity index (−)</td>
       <td align="left">EMS</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>From a conceptual standpoint (+) represents a positive relationship between the indicator and vulnerability, and (−) represents a negative relationship</p>
     <p>
      <span class="italic">NSI</span> National System of Information 2010, 
      <span class="italic">NAC</span> National Agricultural Census 2010, 
      <span class="italic">EMS</span> Environmental Management Survey 2010, 
      <span class="italic">HRAC</span> Health Resources and Activities Census 2009, 
      <span class="italic">DIMS</span> Disaster Information Management System (Desinventar)
     </p>
     <p>
      <span class="sup">a</span>Computed by the authors
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To construct the institutional capacity indicator we apply polychoric principal component analysis to a set of variables related to whether the canton has developed information, programs, strategies or policies on: (1) environmental sensitivity assessments; (2) environmental development; (3) pollution management; and (4) climate change. Though these programs and policies are not uniform across cantons, their availability and extent are an input for the management of climate-related hazards and other environmental risks. Thus, the institutional indicator and its weight signal that in Ecuador the capacities and the relative institutional development of the cantons play a significant role in terms of resource management to cope with changing climatic conditions. We also include the per capita funds municipalities allocate or receive for investments on environmental protection.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a proxy for the economic size of each canton we use indicators related to the average business revenues, average annual energy consumption of households, proportion of businesses with a national or foreign client, tax revenue per capita, and proportion of the population who work in their own business.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
