<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate model simulations</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulations were performed using the GFDL CM2.1 model adapted to late Eocene (38 Ma) boundary conditions. The control simulation, using atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> of 800 ppm, is described in detail in Hutchinson et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. The model uses the palaeogeography reconstruction of Baatsen et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, with an ocean resolution of 1° × 1.5° × 50 levels and an atmosphere resolution of 3° × 3.75° × 24 levels. This allows better representation of ocean gateways than most existing Eocene–Oligocene climate models, which typically use lower ocean resolution, or employ geographic boundary conditions not designed for this time interval. The Arctic closed experiment uses the same configuration except that the Arctic–Atlantic gateway is closed by a land bridge, in line with geological evidence in the lead up to the EOT. Furthermore, we have closed the narrow passageway in our control simulation between Greenland and Svalbard to ensure Arctic isolation. We note that this passageway between Greenland and Svalbard was an artefact of re-gridding the Baatsen et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> dataset onto our model grid, and was closed in the original dataset (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). Sensitivity tests indicate that this artefact has minimal impact on the North Atlantic salinity compared with the wider and deeper open Barents Sea connection, and our control salinity climatology is similar to that found in Baatsen et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. The Arctic Ocean retains a shallow outflow through the Turgai Strait into the Tethys Ocean, which ensures that Arctic freshwater accumulation does not cause numerical instabilities. This outflow has negligible impact on Atlantic water mass properties.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The control simulation has a similar horizontal ocean circulation to the model configuration of Baatsen et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>, who explore the ocean circulation in an ocean-only and a fully coupled climate model forced using the same late Eocene palaeogeography as this study. Surface air temperature and precipitation patterns are also similar to Baatsen et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. A key difference between our model and theirs is that we find bipolar Pacific sinking, whereas they find unipolar Pacific sinking. Their ocean-only model simulations exhibit either North Pacific sinking or South Pacific sinking, depending on the boundary and initial conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, while their coupled model exhibits South Pacific sinking under the same palaeogeography
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. These differences may be due to differences in model resolution and re-gridding effects, or differences in internal dynamics of each model. Their model uses a resolution of ~1° in the ocean (with a different discretization) and ~2° in the atmosphere, giving rise to differences in the resulting topography, runoff and freshwater forcing in the sinking regions. Nevertheless, our simulations broadly support their findings that both on and off states of North Pacific sinking can be found under this palaeogeography, and the North Atlantic is too fresh to sustain sinking with an open Arctic gateway. Given that our model exhibits distinct states of North Pacific and North Atlantic sinking, governed by salt-advection feedbacks, we cannot exclude the possibility of bistability. However, this would require significant further testing and re-equilibration of the model and is beyond the scope of this study.
 </p>
</sec>
