<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we have argued that the onset of modern-like deep water formation in the North Atlantic was triggered by the gradual closing of the Arctic from the Atlantic prior to the EOT. The question remains whether this geographically induced AMOC start-up is causally related to the Antarctic glaciation at the EOT. We found that Arctic closure could not have induced an Antarctic ice sheet through heat transport changes alone because the Antarctic continent actually warms by an average of 1.4 °C after closure. Southern Ocean temperature proxy records do in fact detect warming on the order of 1–2 °C in the latest Eocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>, consistent with recent suggestions that the AMOC strengthened ~1 to 0.5 Myr prior to Antarctic glaciation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. If Arctic closure played a role in Antarctic ice sheet formation, it must have occurred through indirect effects, such as circulation changes lowering atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>, or altering precipitation over Antarctica. We found that a halving of CO
  <sub>2</sub> from 800 to 400 ppm induces a cooling of Antarctica of around 8 °C (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). This is likely an overestimate of the CO
  <sub>2</sub> drop across the EOT; however, it illustrates that the climate impacts of CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing on Antarctica are likely to dominate over ocean heat transport effects induced by the change in circulation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> can decrease due to many factors, such as a reduction in CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, or changes to geological sinks or carbon reservoirs. We consider here two potential mechanisms of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> reduction, which could be related to the modelled circulation changes, namely, increased ocean carbon uptake and enhanced weathering. We found that the global mean ventilation age of the ocean increases from 479 to 570 years. This longer ventilation time may imply a greater capacity to store carbon in the deep ocean. Tentative estimates of circulation-induced changes to deep ocean carbon storage capacity suggest that such changes imply a relatively small change in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> (~10–30 ppm)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> compared with the overall decline in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> over the Eocene–Oligocene of several hundred ppm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The other proposed mechanism to reduce atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> is enhanced silicate weathering. Elsworth et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> argued that a Southern Ocean gateway-triggered AMOC start-up led to an increase in precipitation and temperature in the Northern Hemisphere, which caused a drawdown of CO
  <sub>2</sub> through enhanced silicate weathering. We do not find evidence for this mechanism, because the increased precipitation in the Atlantic is balanced by a decrease in precipitation in the Pacific (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). We also do not find evidence for a northward shift in the ITCZ, as suggested by a change in dust provenance in the eastern equatorial Pacific from Asian sources to South/Central American sources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). This may be because we do not have an ice sheet in our model and these changes are interpreted to be a response to Antarctic glaciation and asymmetric polar cooling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. However, we found a narrowing of the northern branch of the Pacific ITCZ, associated with a strengthening of the subtropical anticyclone in the North Pacific. The latter is likely related to SST cooling in the North Pacific and resulting increase in land–ocean temperature contrast
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to properly understand the links between overturning changes and changes in CO
  <sub>2</sub>, further research is needed using climate models that include a carbon cycle and weathering processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. Nevertheless, our results provide a strong motivation to better understand the physical climate and ocean circulation changes at the EOT in the context of a well-resolved palaeogeography. The close timing between this overturning shift and the EOT glaciation suggests that the two events could be causally related.
 </p>
</sec>
