<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 2005 World Summit on Social Development identified three main sustainable development goals, related to economic development, social development and environmental protection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, these are often referred to as the Three Pillars of Sustainability. Where sustainability is the ability of biological systems to remain diverse and productive indefinitely. Ensuring sustainability across ecological, social and economic dimensions is a cornerstone of international Sustainable Development policy (United Nations Sustainable Development Goals) and Blue Growth initiatives
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish and seafood are the largest single animal-based food production sector (FISHSTAT, 2017) and provide 4.3 billion people worldwide with 15–20% of their intake of animal protein and in some countries over 50%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. The demand for fish continues to increase (4% per year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>), driven by a growing population (1.18% per year)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, technological innovations and the availability of more disposable income. At least 30% of large commercial fish stocks are currently classified as overexploited
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Although this is an improvement over previous decades, for many regions of the world — particularly poorer countries with small-scale fisheries — the sustainability status of fisheries and even the amount of fishing happening is uncertain
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Further, changes to already heavily exploited systems — mediated by climate, or changes in demand from population growth and wealth — risk fisheries collapses or significant increases in the price of fish products. Given the food security, livelihoods and nutritional importance of fish for so many people, effectively managed fisheries is central to many sustainable development goals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tuna represent a significant part of the global fish and seafood economy with an annual value of USD$42.2 billion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Tuna also play an important role in the health and functioning of the ecosystem
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> and across all sectors of a wider fishing community necessitating improved management to maintain fish stocks in a healthy state
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Because of the high value of tuna stocks they are subject to high fishing pressure and there is growing concern about (i) the risks of failing to achieve fisheries and conservation objectives, (ii) the ability to implement recovery plans for depleted stocks and (iii) effective protection for those that are vulnerable to overfishing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While some progress has been made in developing a precautionary approach to fisheries management for tuna by developing limit reference points to indicate overfishing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, this has, however, been mainly confined to biological elements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Although more integrated approaches for addressing the combined ecological, social and economic risks of overfishing have been called for over the past decade
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. This normally requires targets and limits related to economic and social factors in order to effectively manage a fishery.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tuna Regional Fisheries Management Organisations (tRFMOs) represent international organisations with fishing interests in a specific area (see Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) and most have adopted Maximum Sustainable Yield (MSY) as a management target defined as the largest average catch of a species that can be taken over time that guarantees that the resource is not depleted. MSY is, however, notoriously difficult to estimate and generally relies on equilibrium model assumptions and/or data from stocks that have already exceeded the level (B
  <sub>MSY</sub>) that supports MSY
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. The management performance of each tuna fishery is monitored by a set of indicators to report on the progress in achieving F
  <sub>MSY</sub> (the fishing mortality level consistent with achieving maximum sustainable yield) and B
  <sub>MSY</sub> (Spawning stock biomass or Total biomass that results from fishing at F
  <sub>MSY</sub> for a sustained period of time)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. A major challenge, however, is understanding how the sustainability of fisheries is affected by exernal forces such as climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> and shocks such as market fluctuations or environmental variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the last two decades there have been significant changes in fuel costs, fish prices, global warming, technological change (i.e. introduction of gears such as Fish Aggregation Devices, FADs), and changes in adult tuna stock biomass
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. All of these factors have a cumulative effect on the operating costs of fleets and thus their spatial behaviour
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. For tuna stocks, past exploitation levels and management measures have shown to be as important as the links between life history, market price and vulnerability to overexploitation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Although a composite index of fisheries management at the country-level has shown to be positively related to factors such as countries’ gross domestic product
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> an integrated understanding of how these drivers connect to environmental with economic and biological variables for tuna stocks is currently missing.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we examine whether tends in tuna stock status, as measured by F/F
  <sub>MSY</sub>, are related to the economic and social development of countries (Human Development Index, HDI) to identify whether some countries are more risk of overexploitation. We then develop statistical models to explore how stock status could be affected by different types of short-term shocks based on the relationships between F/F
  <sub>MSY</sub> with economic fluctuations (e.g. fish prices and fuel price), social (fleet diversity/fishing activity – knowledge transfer) and climatic variability (e.g. North Atlantic Oscillation Index (NAO) and Southern Oscillation index (SOI)). Time series of economic, climatic and spatial indices were available for more than 23 years. As these indicators are potentially correlated, we constructed ridge regression models (see Methods and Materials) and used these to assess the sensitivity of F/F
  <sub>MSY</sub> for tuna stock to each driver of change.
 </p>
</sec>
