<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although our ABC analyses identified distributional shift as the best‐fit scenario, it did not receive unambiguously superior support relative to the next‐best scenario, and the estimated error in scenario choice was large (Supporting Information Table 
 <xref rid="ece35065-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S7.8</xref>). Accordingly, we must consider our ABC‐based inference to be a preliminary working hypothesis, to be re‐evaluated and re‐tested with new data. Notwithstanding some limitations of our ABC inferences, it is notable that a common feature of the best‐fit and second‐best hypotheses is the expansion of the Central cluster. Specifically, both scenarios include the Northern cluster giving rise to the Central cluster. Additionally, both scenarios include a direct long‐distance dispersal event. Buckley (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) advocated for an iterative approach to phylogeography, highlighting the value of working hypotheses for focusing subsequent analytical efforts on scenarios that have some empirical support. This study contributes to a growing body of literature that highlights an important role for multiple refugia—including those located further north than previously expected—in phylogeographic structuring of plants (McLachlan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>), vertebrates (Fontanella, Feldman, Siddall, &amp; Burbrink, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), and invertebrates (Merz et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Having characterized contemporary fine‐scale spatial structure and historical climate‐based distributions for 
 <italic class="italic">R. flavipes</italic>, the present study has also revealed specific geographic locations that warrant dedicated sampling (e.g., the Southern genetic cluster has a relatively small range that requires better representation, and based on SDMs, sampling in the Gulf Coast and Coastal Plain areas would be particularly valuable).
</p>
