<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both approaches offer insight but have serious limitations [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The phenomenological approach generally employs spatially or temporally broad and ecologically relevant datasets, but risks basing models on spurious rather than causal relationships when it does not first establish the mechanisms governing the effects of environmental variables on tick demography. In addition, the absence or rarity of ticks in certain regions is often assumed to be caused by unsuitable (current) conditions in that region, but such unsuitability is rarely if ever established [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Lastly, the different spatial and temporal scales of these phenomenological studies, not to mention the different climatic variables they include, have made it difficult to identify and evaluate consistent patterns in associations [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The mechanistic approach, on the other hand, typically uses controlled experiments to determine the effects of specific environmental conditions on a handful of specific developmental or demographic responses. Because the environmental conditions are usually imposed in laboratory settings, which necessarily exclude many dimensions of ecological realism (e.g. variability in conditions, interacting species), one must take care in extrapolating relationships observed in the laboratory to the field. Field experiments can provide more ecologically relevant data but are usually of limited scope focusing, for instance, on only a subset of relevant demographic processes, often in few locations, or physically restraining ticks in a way that complicates interpretation of survival patterns [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. The advantage of this approach is that projections are based on mechanistic relationships rather than statistical associations. But while the models used to integrate these empirical studies have become increasingly sophisticated [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], they are still based on few empirical data and best guesses about key parameters.
</p>
