<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used six established frequentist methods (see full model descriptions in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Methods</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 1</xref> and ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>) to infer the timing of extinction for 28 identified megafauna species (plus 8 indeterminate species identified only to genus) grouped into 16 genera (other genera do not present enough high-quality-rated fossil ages to compute the extinction window; 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>) and first human occurrence. We applied these models to 659 megafauna fossil records and 438 archaeological records extracted from the new FosSahul database (see author information) by first aggregating species into genera and then computing the extinction window for each genus. Each method returns an extinction window (temporal confidence interval) for each taxon; thus, we calculated a window of cross-model agreement through time (that is, for every year from 120 to 0 kyr, we calculated how many models predicted extinction for a given taxon) under the assumption that higher cross-model agreement decreases uncertainties in extinction-window estimates
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref>. From the 2,138 records of extinct fauna species in the database, each fossil was quality rated following an A* to C scale (from ‘high quality' to ‘unreliable') based on objective criteria
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>, including reliability in sample pretreatment and measurement (see details below). We used only A* and A quality-rated data and further excluded all data for which ages were obtained from materials in depositional context below or above the fossil(s) of interest. We used the same methodology to extract data from the 6,349 archaeological records. There are few human skeletal remains in the database; thus, human presence is largely restricted to artefacts related to human activities (for example, hearth charcoal, shell middens, stone tools and rock art). We excluded an age estimate of 62±6 kyr from Lake Mungo, because it is highly contested
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref>. Including this age would push back our first human appearance estimate to about 62 kyr (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>), but does not affect our conclusion that megafauna extinctions are not correlated with climate variation. Its inclusion would result in a longer period of human–megafauna coexistence (18.5 kyr), thus extending the timeframe by about 5 kyr for humans to extirpate megafauna species continent wide. Similarly, the youngest 
 <italic class="italic">Genyornis</italic> ages should be treated with caution, because 
 <sup class="sup">14</sup>C ages on carbonate materials are sensitive to exchange with younger carbon; such ages are potentially ‘minimum' ages and the true ages could be older than the estimated peak of extinction, but this complication does not affect our conclusions. We calibrated all 
 <sup class="sup">14</sup>C dates to calendar years before present using the Southern Hemisphere Calibration curve (ShCal13) and Marine Calibration curve (Marine13 for marine shells) from the OxCal radiocarbon calibration tool Version 4.2 (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://c14.arch.ox.ac.uk" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://c14.arch.ox.ac.uk</ext-link>).
</p>
