<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maximum Entropy (MaxEnt) version 3.3.3k [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>] was used to run the models, choosing the options that created the best models (i.e. feature classes QPT, 10000 background points, 1000 iterations, cross-validation [k = 10] with 10 replicates [for estimating prediction errors], 10% training presence threshold, and logistic output format), and to create the binarized (via thresholding) maps. MaxEnt performance is good with presence-only data and relatively few records [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. The option set was chosen after extensive tests to maximise the AUC and TSS, the standard measures of goodness-of-fit for SDMs [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. The one species with a mean AUC score less than 0.7 was removed from the analysis, as recommended [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Following [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], we chose the “10% training presence” threshold rule to give a binary map for each of the 10 replicates for each species. With the 10% training presence rule, the threshold selects pixels where 90% of the training presences are correctly classified, thus giving some allowance for the possibilities of ephemeral populations or recording errors. A minimal training presence threshold that correctly predicts every training presence may lead to over-prediction. The resulting maps were analysed under the two extreme dispersal assumptions (unlimited and no-dispersal) usually applied in such studies (for example, [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]). Both assumptions have been criticized for not involving the impact of biotic interactions on species distributions [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], but there is no practical way of incorporating any putative interactions for Egyptian species. Species gains occur when species occupy new areas, while losses can occur when the habitat suitability is reduced for that area in the future. Species turnover is the differences between the current and future species composition of the same location, used as an indicator at large or regional scales [
 <xref rid="pone.0187714.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>].
</p>
