<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dietary switch</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the marine realm, some seabirds are known for their dietary plasticity [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref024">24</a>], with recurrent dietary switches following fishery-induced perturbations [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref025">25</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref028">28</a>]. This is precisely what we found in Cape gannets. During our study period, birds breeding on Malgas Island fed within their usual home-range off the west coast of South Africa (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210328.g003" href="#pone.0210328.g003">Fig 3</a>; [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref023">23</a>]), and their foraging parameters were comparable to those observed across the last decade [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref016">16</a>]. Yet, surprisingly, they exclusively caught saury. Cape gannets normally favour sardines whenever available and switch to fishery waste (mainly hake) in the absence of their preferred prey [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref016">16</a>]. Saury occurs irregularly in Cape gannet diet [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref029">29</a>]. It favours warmer waters (18–22°C) than anchovy and sardine, which typically frequent upwelled waters (SST &lt;16°C; [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref030">30</a>]). The presence of saury close to the west coast of South Africa might therefore be a sign of reduced upwelling activity. However, the SST within the core home-range of foraging Cape gannets has been consistently &gt;16°C during early chick-rearing (Oct-Nov) across the last decade (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210328.g008" href="#pone.0210328.g008">Fig 8</a>), providing no support for abnormal conditions in 2017.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because saury occur irregularly and in small schools [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref031">31</a>], they are not exploited commercially in South Africa. Hence, Cape gannets targeting them are unlikely to forage in the vicinity of fishing vessels. The calorific value of saury (6.2 kJ.g
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) is intermediate between that of sardines (8.6 kJ.g
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and hake (4.1 kJ.g
  <span class="sup">−1</span>; [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref032">32</a>]), and diet calorific value strongly constrains gannet reproductive performance [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref017">17</a>]. This potentially explains why gannets breeding on Malgas, facing a scarcity of sardines, switched to feeding on locally abundant saury, rather than fishery waste made available by hake trawlers. Dietary plasticity thus allows the gannets to maintain adult body condition and adequate chick growth rates (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210328.g002" href="#pone.0210328.g002">Fig 2</a>; see [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref033">33</a>] for further information on inter-annual trends). Saury has also been found in Cape gannet diet in Namibia [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref034">34</a>], and is profitable prey for other Benguela seabirds, as indicated by a recent study [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref035">35</a>] in greater crested terns (
  <span class="italic">Thalasseus bergii bergii</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
