<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seabirds coexist with fisheries across the world’s oceans, and interact with them in a number of ways [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref001">1</a>]. Seabirds have been guiding fishermen towards profitable harvesting grounds from ancient times. This practice persists to this day, even in industrial fisheries using radar technology to locate seabird aggregations over tuna shoals in tropical waters [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref002">2</a>]. Further, fishing gear may catch or injure seabirds. This contributed to significant seabird population declines, especially in petrels and albatrosses exposed to long-line fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref003">3</a>]. Mitigations measures have been relatively efficient with respect to hook-and-line fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref004">4</a>], yet issues persist with other gear types and because mitigation measures on long-lines are rarely applied in international waters [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref005">5</a>]. Also, 10% of fisheries catches are wasted at sea [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref006">6</a>], and some of this biomass becomes additional food available to seabirds. Yet, fisheries also extract potential seabird food from the oceans, leading to competition for resources which are becoming limited because of global overfishing [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref008">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seabirds have developed a range of responses to the presence of fishing vessels. Some species consistently show no reaction to the presence of any vessel (except to avoid them when resting at the water surface), especially those which feed on zooplankton (small petrels, prions and several alcids) and have nothing to gain from potential waste. In contrast, piscivorous seabirds are usually attracted by fishing vessels [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref010">10</a>]. They are capable of discriminating gear types, and of showing contrasting responses to the presence of fishing vessels [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref011">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the case in Cape gannets (
  <span class="italic">Morus capensis</span>), which are endemic to the Benguela upwelling region off the west coast of southern Africa. In this marine ecosystem, previous work indicated that gannets avoided purse-seiners, with whom they compete for small pelagic fish, and actively sought trawlers, which generate fishery wastes upon which they can feed [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref012">12</a>]. More specifically, Cape gannets are known to feed naturally by plunge-diving in coastal areas, primarily on sardines (
  <span class="italic">Sardinops sagax</span>). Following the fishery-induced collapse of this resource in the 1960s off South Africa, and in the 1970s off Namibia, gannets also fed on anchovies (
  <span class="italic">Engraulis encrasicolus</span>) and other prey [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref013">13</a>]. In South Africa, small pelagic fish stocks (sardines and anchovies) partly recovered in the 1990s, but are still well below pre-exploitation levels [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref014">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cape gannets presently compete with local purse-seine fisheries for greatly diminished sardine stocks [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref015">15</a>]. In years with particularly low abundance of their natural prey, birds switch to feed on fishery wastes from demersal trawling vessels, primarily targeting hake (
  <span class="italic">Merlucius spp</span>.) [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref016">16</a>]. This second fleet operates year-round within the foraging range of Cape gannets, performing 45–90 trawls per day, on average [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref017">17</a>]. Fishing waste is easily available to gannets when dumped by vessels, yet its calorific value is only half that of sardines [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref018">18</a>]. Adults feeding on this low-quality diet have poorer body condition, their chicks grow slower [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref016">16</a>] and their reproductive output declines strongly [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cape gannets therefore seem trapped in a system where they face a scarcity of their natural prey, and an abundance of ‘junk-food’. Their total population declined by 50–79% over 3 generations (approx. 50 years) and their conservation status has recently been downgraded to 
  <span class="italic">Endangered</span>, considering this trend and the fact that they only occur at six breeding sites worldwide [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref019">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to better understand the foraging behaviour of Cape gannets in the context of limited food supplies, and to contribute to conservation schemes, we equipped them with recently-developed, miniaturized electronic tags. Those record the GPS position of birds travelling at-sea, but also regularly scan their surroundings to detect the presence of ship radar, as an indication of fishing vessel presence [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref020">20</a>]. On the basis of previous work [
  <a rid="pone.0210328.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210328.ref012">12</a>], we hypothesized that, faced with the scarcity of their natural prey, adult birds would approach vessels generating fishery waste.
 </p>
</sec>
