<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Endotherms often need to invest energy in heat production to maintain body temperature within a range compatible with life (Alexander 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1999</a>). Over-wintering at high latitudes is especially challenging for small passerines as they cannot store large internal energy reserves and, therefore, need to cover their daily energy requirements at a time when environmental conditions deteriorate, time available for feeding diminishes and non-renewable food resources become scarcer (Blem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2000</a>). Birds track environmental conditions to prevent starvation during harsh ambient episodes (Carey and Dawson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">1999</a>), and as part of an acclimatization process raise their metabolic capacity (Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2004</a>) and the level of energy reserves (Blem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1990</a>) to meet increasing thermogenic needs. During nighttime, which is a forced fasting period, heat production is fueled by internal body stores largely composed of fat, although other internal tissues are catabolized when fat reserves are depleted (Hulbert and Else 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2000</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy management during winter is believed to rely basically on the adaptive acquisition and storage of reserves (McNamara and Houston 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">1990</a>; McNamara et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">1994</a>; Houston et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1997</a>; Pravosudov and Grubb 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">1997</a>; Brodin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2007</a>). This scenario has been extensively studied from both a theoretical and empirical perspective, giving rise to what is known as the “optimal body mass” (OBM) theory (Lima 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">1986</a>; Rogers 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">1987</a>; Rogers and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1993</a>; Witter and Cuthill 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">1993</a>; Houston et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1997</a>). The central tenet underlying this theory is that birds should carry as large energy reserves as needed to prevent starvation risk (Krams et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2013</a>) or to be able to sustain disease-induced periods of anorexia (Speakman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2018</a>). Furthermore, since their internal reserves are rarely at its maximum, it follows that there should be some associated costs of carrying and/or gathering reserves, probably in terms of predation. Consequently, birds should optimize their energy reserves according to a predation-starvation trade-off (Lima 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">1986</a>; Witter and Cuthill 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">1993</a>; Gosler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1996</a>; Bonter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2013</a>). Such predation-starvation trade-offs may vary between individuals for example according to dominance (Krams et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2013</a>). Small wintering birds exhibit a pronounced daily body mass (BM) increase (Cuthill et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2000</a>; MacLeod et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2005</a>; Moiron et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2018</a>), superimposed on a seasonal cycle known as winter fattening (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">1987</a>; Rogers 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">1987</a>; Haftorn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">1989</a>; Rogers and Rogers 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">1990</a>; Bednekoff and Houston 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">1994</a>; Koivula et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">1995</a>; Rintamäki et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2003</a>). However, although the OBM theory has received considerable empirical support for daily patterns of BM variation (e.g., Polo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2007</a>), evidence is equivocal for energy management strategies over larger time scales and in hoarding species (e.g., Pravosudov and Grubb 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1998</a>; Brodin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2000</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2003</a>; Cooper 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, in addition to BM regulation winter-acclimatized small birds increase the capacity for metabolic output that concomitantly leads to an overall increase in the cost of maintenance, i.e., basal metabolic rate (BMR) (Kendeigh and Blem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">1974</a>; Liknes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2002</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2004</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2007</a>; Swanson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2010</a>), which is paralleled with changes in body composition (Scott et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">1996</a>; Liknes and Swanson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2011</a>; Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2014</a>; Zheng et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2014</a>). BMR is a highly plastic trait that can change in a matter of days (Piersma and Lindström 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1997</a>; Swanson and Olmstead 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">1999</a>; Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2013</a>; Petit and Vézina 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2014</a>; Dubois et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2016</a>). Still, individual birds follow consistent BMR strategies (Speakman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2004</a>) as it is a long-term repeatable trait (Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2009</a>) that is heritable (Nilsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2009</a>) and, thus, susceptible to selection (Sadowska et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">2015</a>). If energy is not constraining, increases in BMR have been related to increased working capacity (Nilsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2002</a>; Sadowska et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2013</a>) and fitness (Boratynski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2013</a>; Sadowska et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">2015</a>), see (Biro and Stamps 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2010</a>). However, BMR it is often assumed to be shaped by indirect selection on other correlated traits, e.g., maximal metabolic rate, and thus unlikely to be adaptively modulated (Swanson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2017</a>), although evidence accumulates suggesting that BMR responds differently to environmental conditions than such correlated traits (Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2013</a>; Dubois et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2016</a>). The ecological significance of individual variation in BMR remains poorly understood (see Burton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2011</a>), as it may change among different populations and circumstances (Rønning et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2015</a>; Nilsson and Nilsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since both BM and BMR are phenotypically integrated traits that are highly and positively related, understanding how environmental factors affect one independently of the other requires a reciprocal standardization for a proper interpretation of each trait separately. On the one hand, BM is an emerging property of the organism, which necessarily changes with the proportion of different tissues. However, the prevalent theoretical framework assumes that winter changes in BM mostly result from variation in fat reserves (Blem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1990</a>; Broggi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2006</a> and references therein). Furthermore, changes in BMR may result from variation in size of different organs or the proportion of tissues that will likely influence BM (Piersma and Lindström 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1997</a>; Ksiazek et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2004</a>; Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2014</a>), in addition to changes in cellular aerobic metabolic intensity (Rønning et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2008</a>). Absolute BM (BM
  <sub>abs</sub>) represents the whole-animal BM that includes all variation due to structural size and changes in body composition, while standardized BM by BMR (BM
  <sub>std</sub>) represents the individual BM that is independent of the variation in BMR. Variation in BMR necessarily involves variation in sizes and proportions of organs and tissues with different metabolic activity. Therefore, variation in BM
  <sub>std</sub> would reflect variation in tissues with lower metabolic activity such as fat that largely compose the internal body reserves in birds (Klaassen and Biebach 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">1994</a>). On the other hand, studies on energy metabolism have traditionally corrected BMR for BM to standardize BMR measurements across individuals and species as an estimate of metabolic intensity (Hulbert and Else 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2000</a>). However, whole-animal (BMR
  <sub>abs</sub>) and mass-specific metabolism (BMR
  <sub>std</sub>) have been recognized as different traits with different biological meaning (Hayes 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2001</a>; Nespolo and Franco 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2007</a>; Rønning et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2008</a>). While BMR
  <sub>abs</sub> represents the overall basal energy consumption of the whole animal and scales with individual size, BMR
  <sub>std</sub> is the mass-specific BMR that reflects variation in metabolic intensity of the different organs/tissues of the individual (Rønning et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2008</a>; Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2014</a>; Zheng et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2014</a>). While mass-specific BMR has been widely used as a measure of metabolic intensity and for comparative purposes, standardizing BM for BMR is a novel approach (but see Senar et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2000</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological research on energy management in wintering birds has traditionally focused on BM fluctuations as a proxy of reserve acquisition and storage within the starvation-predation trade-off framework (OBM), whereas changes in BMR have been considered as a byproduct of the regulation on other traits rather than a strategically modulated mechanism (e.g., Speakman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2004</a>; Burton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2011</a>). We hypothesize that BMR can be adaptively adjusted to changing environmental and ecological circumstances in addition to BM. If both traits were to be modulated in concert, albeit on different time scales (days vs. hours), the OBM would no longer be sufficient to interpret energy management in wintering small passerines. Here, we explore to what extent these two traits covary and respond independently to the environmental conditions in three species of forest dwelling passerines with distinct life-history strategies and originating from two different climatic regions to reveal potential strategies in the simultaneous regulation of BM and BMR during winter.
 </p>
</sec>
