<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="evo12635-sec-0200" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As opposed to numerous studies that have assessed the consequences of a fixed maternal effect on other characters (Kirkpatrick and Lande, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0036">1989</a>; Wolf et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0093">1999</a>; Räsänen and Kruuk, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0068">2007</a>; Hoyle and Ezard, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0026">2012</a>; Ezard et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0013">2014</a>), this study is one of the first to assess the evolutionary dynamics of maternal effects themselves. Interestingly, our model shows that maternal effects are indeed anything but a static parameter: rather, the evolved magnitude and sign of maternal effects are sensitive to specific ecological and organismal features, such as the nature of environmental change, the strength of selection and the presence of other mechanisms that facilitate adaptation (such as phenotypic plasticity).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Focusing on the evolution of maternal effects, we find that rapid environmental shifts lead to the transient evolution of positive maternal effects of a large magnitude, during which maternal effects remain positive for several thousand generations (see Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0002">2</a>). As highlighted in the results, the reason for the presence of such positive maternal effects is that an individual that manages to survive and reproduce is likely to have a phenotype that lies closer to the novel environmental optimum. Consequently, offspring that aim to adjust themselves to the novel environment benefit by attaining a similar phenotype to their parents, which is achieved through positive parental effects. Hence, the evolution of maternal effects in response to environmental shifts confirms well‐established verbal theories (Uller, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0080">2008</a>, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0081">2012</a>), which state that maternal effects evolve when the parental phenotype provides information about the offspring's future environment. We find that such transiently positive parental effects occur even when phenotypic plasticity is also present (although the effects are less pronounced). That maternal effects still exhibit a marked evolutionary response in the presence of phenotypic plasticity is due to the sudden nature of the shift: after the environmental perturbation has occurred, drastically larger values of the elevation 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and the reaction norm 
  <span class="italic">b</span> become selectively favored. However, as the evolution of larger values of 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and 
  <span class="italic">b</span> does not occur instantaneously, the evolution of maternal effects provides a powerful additional means of rapid adaptation to sudden changes in environmental conditions, as it allows the maternal phenotype closer to the optimum to influence the offspring's phenotype.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results are strikingly different, however, in the context of periodically changing environments, where an environment never reaches a new equilibrium, but changes continuously. When selection is weak, we find the scope for maternal effects of a substantial magnitude to be only modest in fluctuating environments (e.g., Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>B). The limited prevalence of maternal effects when selection is weak and plasticity is absent is in line with the notion that maternal effects will only evolve when the parental phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-249" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">*</span>
   </div>
  </div> is informative about future environmental conditions (see also Uller, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0080">2008</a>; Fischer et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0016">2011</a>; Kuijper and Johnstone, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0040">2013</a>; Kuijper et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0041">2014</a>). When selection acting on the maternal phenotype is weak (and phenotypic plasticity is absent), the maternal phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-250" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">*</span>
   </div>
  </div> will not correlate strongly with the prevailing environmental conditions, as individuals with phenotypes 
  <div id="nlm-math-251" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> that lie very far away from the parental selective optimum 
  <div id="nlm-math-252" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> are still able to survive and produce offspring. As the parental phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-253" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">*</span>
   </div>
  </div> is thus largely uninformative about the selective environment to offspring, maternal effects are hardly relevant when selection is weak and plasticity is absent. By contrast, when plasticity is present, individuals adjust their phenotype to the prevailing environmental conditions, so that their phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-254" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> becomes more closely aligned to the selective optimum 
  <div id="nlm-math-255" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>. As the parental phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-256" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">*</span>
   </div>
  </div> is now more informative to offspring (at least when 
  <div id="nlm-math-257" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> and 
  <div id="nlm-math-258" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <span class="mi">t</span>
   </div>
  </div> are correlated), maternal effects of a larger magnitude evolve (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>B). Moreover, 
  <div id="nlm-math-259" class="math">
   <div accent="true" class="mover">
    <span class="mi">m</span>
    <span class="mo">¯</span>
   </div>
  </div> generally evolves in line with the environmental autocorrelation (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>E, see also Kuijper et al. 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0041">2014</a>), although this pattern becomes more complicated for species with long development times (see Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0006">6</a>). The notion that plasticity can enhance the evolution of maternal effects corroborates similar findings by previous studies, which showed that certain combinations of plasticity and fixed maternal effects improve mean fitness (Hoyle and Ezard, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0026">2012</a>; Ezard et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0013">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When selection on the overall phenotype is stronger, we find that maternal effects achieve the largest values when plasticity is absent or severely constrained (e.g., Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>D). This is unsurprising, as strong selection causes only those mothers to survive whose phenotype 
  <div id="nlm-math-260" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">*</span>
   </div>
  </div> is very closely aligned to the selective optimum 
  <div id="nlm-math-261" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <span class="mi">t</span>
   </div>
  </div>. Consequently, strong selection makes the maternal phenotype predictive about the offspring environment (at least when 
  <div id="nlm-math-262" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <span class="mi">t</span>
   </div>
  </div> and 
  <div id="nlm-math-263" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> are correlated). Moreover, in the absence of plasticity, individuals are forced to rely on maternal effects as it is the only means of adaptation to a fluctuating environment. When plasticity is present, however, lower values of maternal effects evolve, as relying on plasticity (which constitutes a more direct source of environmental information, as opposed to indirect information through the maternal phenotype) is the preferred means of adaptation. As the relevance of strong selection in long‐term adaptation is generally considered to be limited (Kingsolver et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0034">2001</a>), the relevance of scenarios where maternal effects evolve to very large values remains to be empirically demonstrated. Nonetheless, in certain cases selection has been demonstrated to be strong (e.g., King et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0032">2011</a>), particularly in the realm of antagonistic coevolution. Based on our study, we would expect that maternal effects would be most easily detected in these contexts (see also Mostowy et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0058">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A general result emerging from this study is that phenotypic plasticity has a much stronger influence on adaptation than maternal effects (e.g., Figs. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0002">2</a>A and 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0003">3</a>A). In relation to that, we also find a much larger impact of evolving phenotypic plasticity on the magnitude of maternal effects, whereas the reverse impact of maternal effects on plasticity is much more limited (e.g., see Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>). That phenotypic plasticity is a more efficient means of adaptation is unsurprising, as plasticity relies on direct environmental information, whereas maternal effects necessarily rely on the maternal phenotype as an indirect source of environmental information. As a result, maternal effects only evolve when the maternal phenotype is sufficiently correlated with the environment that will be encountered by offspring, which in turn occurs only when selection is strong and an environmental autocorrelation is present between subsequent generations. As such conditions do not apply to direct environmental cues, it is not surprising that the role of maternal effects is thus more restrictive than phenotypic plasticity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our prediction that maternal effects have a rather limited role when selection is weak may well correspond with a recent meta‐analysis (Uller et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0083">2013</a>), which shows that there is only limited evidence of maternal effects facilitating adaptation to environmental change. In addition, another meta‐analysis finds that selection coefficients are, in fact, remarkably consistent over time, demonstrating that currently little evidence exists for either large selective shifts of a substantial magnitude or continuously fluctuating selection (Siepielski et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0072">2013</a>). Consequently, these lines of evidence would suggest that maternal effect coefficients 
  <span class="italic">m</span> should evolve to be small and negative in the majority of cases. Indeed, empirical studies show that negative maternal effect coefficients appear to be the norm: (reviewed in Räsänen and Kruuk, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0068">2007</a>), only two cases of positive maternal effects have been found: maternal effects of adult body size on hatchling body size in Darwin's finches and great tits have coefficients 
  <div id="nlm-math-264" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">m</span>
    <span class="mo">≈</span>
    <span class="mn">0.6</span>
   </div>
  </div> and 
  <div id="nlm-math-265" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">m</span>
    <span class="mo">≈</span>
    <span class="mn">0.3</span>
    <span class="mo">,</span>
   </div>
  </div> respectively (Lande and Price, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0047">1989</a>). By contrast, all other studies that measured maternal effects have found to be negative and relatively small (e.g., Falconer, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0014">1965</a>; Janssen et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0027">1988</a>; Schluter and Gustafsson, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0071">1993</a>; McAdam and Boutin, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0053">2004</a>). In addition, a number of studies have measured a negative correlation between direct genetic effects and maternal genetic effects (e.g., Cheverud, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0008">1984</a>; Wilson et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0089">2005</a>; Wilson and Réale, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0088">2006</a>; Räsänen and Kruuk, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0068">2007</a>; Kent et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0029">2009</a>), which often indicates that the actual maternal effects coefficient 
  <span class="italic">m</span> is also negative (Falconer, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0014">1965</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although weak selection (Kingsolver and Diamond, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0033">2011</a>; Kingsolver et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0035">2012</a>; Siepielski et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0072">2013</a>) may be a fruitful explanation for the prevalence of negative maternal effects for the purpose of variance minimization (Hoyle and Ezard, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0026">2012</a>), this is of course not the whole story. Existing data on fluctuating selection is confounded by sampling biases (e.g., exclusion of unsuccessful years or small populations from analyses of selection) and typically only provides a brief snapshot in time (Siepielski et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0072">2013</a>). Also, the notion that major climatic variables (e.g., rainfall, temperature) are characterized by substantial temporal variation (Vasseur and Yodzis, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0084">2004</a>) shows that the ecological context of fluctuating selection is far from understood. In addition, although maternal effects have, on average, only slight consequences for offspring phenotypes (Uller et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0083">2013</a>), a number of undeniable examples exist where maternal phenotypes have clear transgenerational influences on offspring phenotypes (Gustafsson et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0021">2005</a>; Galloway and Etterson, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0017">2007</a>). It is imperative to tie these studies (and future ones) to information about (1) the strength of selection on the overall phenotype, (2) the strength of selection on phenotypic plasticity, and (3) the nature of environmental variation (e.g., positive vs. negatively correlated environments). In terms of measurable parameters, our study shows that the strength of selection on phenotypes needs to be substantial to give rise to maternal effects of a significant magnituede (i.e., phenotypic selection gradients 
  <div id="nlm-math-266" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">|</span>
    </div>
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">β</span>
     <span class="mi">z</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">|</span>
     <span class="mo">∝</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span class="mi">ω</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">z</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <span class="mn">2</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, see Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0005">5</a>) and phenotypic plasticity needs to be costly (e.g., 
  <div id="nlm-math-267" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">|</span>
    </div>
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">β</span>
     <span class="mi">b</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mo">|</span>
     <span class="mo">∝</span>
    </div>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <div class="msubsup">
      <span class="mi">ω</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">b</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">&gt;</span>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <span class="mn">10</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>), or constrained in other ways (see Auld et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0002">2010</a>). Lastly, the sign and magnitude of maternal effects is highly contingent on the nature of environmental variation, with positively correlated, or slowly and predictably changing, environments selecting for positive maternal effects, while negatively correlated, or rapidly changing, environments selectively favor negative maternal effects (see also Ezard et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0013">2014</a>; Kuijper et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0041">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess thoroughly whether variation in maternal effects can be tied to different ecological contexts, studies that measure intraspecific variation in maternal effect coefficients would be desirable. Although a number of studies have considered intraspecific variation in maternal effects (e.g., Mousseau, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0060">1991</a>; Williams, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0087">1994</a>), these studies only investigated phenotypic variation in offspring characters, but did not assess the strength and sign of maternal effects. Particularly suitable target species to measure intraspecific variation in maternal effects are those for which substantial detail about the genetic architecture is available through multigenerational pedigrees in different populations, as is the case for great tits 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (Vedder et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0085">2013</a>; Korsten et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0038">2013</a>). Next to that, measurements of parent–offspring correlations in multiple contexts (Lande and Price, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0047">1989</a>) would provide insight into the extent of maternal effects, which may be particularly interesting to assess variation in maternal effects in human populations (Kent et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0029">2009</a>; Stearns et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0075">2010</a>). In addition, experimental evolution (Kawecki et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0028">2012</a>), for example on offspring size, would provide a more rigorous approach to assessing the evolutionary properties of maternal effects, particularly when the rate of environmental fluctuations varies across experimental subpopulations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies within the same framework suggest that our conclusions generalize to other contexts, such as stochastically fluctuating environments (Kuijper et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0041">2014</a>; Ezard et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0013">2014</a>). Indeed, Figure S5 shows that maternal effects also evolve in stochastically fluctuating environments. Similarly to our results in a periodic environment in which developmental delays are small (see Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>), maternal effects evolve to positive (or negative) values in positively (or negatively) autocorrelated environments. In addition, stochastic models also allow to assess how maternal effects evolve in response to increasingly unpredictable environments (in which the autocorrelation ρ decreases toward 0), congruent with recent climate change (Hansen et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0023">2012</a>). Figure S5 shows that maternal effects rapidly decay to slight negative values that merely reduce phenotypic variance, with little transgenerational importance. Consequently, increasing climatic unpredictability is likely to reduce the scope for maternal effects in the long term.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible extensions to our model include the incorporation of spatial environmental variation. Given our previous results in temporally fluctuating environments (e.g., Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>), we would expect that correlations between parental and offspring environments are also key to the evolution of maternal effects in spatial environments. In a simple spatial model (consisting of two different environments and a probability 
  <span class="italic">d</span> with which individuals migrate to a different environment), we indeed find that correlations are again important (see Fig. S6): when dispersal 
  <div id="nlm-math-268" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">d</span>
    <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
    <span class="mn">0.5</span>
   </div>
  </div>, maternal effects evolve to slight negative values as the majority of offspring remain in the natal environment and thus experience no change. By contrast, when the dispersal probability is higher (
  <div id="nlm-math-269" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">d</span>
    <span class="mo">≥</span>
    <span class="mn">0.5</span>
   </div>
  </div>), maternal effects now evolve to negative values 
  <div id="nlm-math-270" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div accent="true" class="mover">
     <span class="mi">m</span>
     <span class="mo">¯</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
    <span class="mn">0</span>
   </div>
  </div> of a substantial magnitude. This occurs because the majority of offspring will end up in an environment opposite to that of their parents. Although this simple example thus suggests that our findings extend to spatial contexts, more work is needed to assess how maternal effects evolve in more complicated, spatio‐temporal environments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another assumption is that maternal effects 
  <span class="italic">m</span> are expressed by offspring, rather than by the mother. However, additional simulations show that outcomes do not depend on maternal versus offspring expression of 
  <span class="italic">m</span> (results not shown). This is unsurprising, as offspring fitness is independent of that of its siblings, so that parent–offspring conflict is absent. It would be interesting to relax this assumption in future studies, for example by modeling maternal effects in viscous populations where relatives interact (Uller and Pen, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0082">2011</a>; Kuijper and Johnstone, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0039">2012</a>). Alternatively, one could model the evolution of maternal effects 
  <span class="italic">m</span> when the phenotype 
  <span class="italic">z</span> reflects offspring size, which trades‐off with maternal fecundity as in classical life‐history theory (Smith and Fretwell, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0074">1974</a>; Parker and Macnair, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0065">1978</a>; Parker and Begon, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0064">1986</a>). Preliminary results of the latter scenario show that offspring size 
  <div id="nlm-math-271" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">z</span>
    <span class="mi">t</span>
   </div>
  </div> indeed diverges between mother and offspring, as expected. However, the difference in offspring size is entirely caused by differences in the evolved values of the elevation 
  <span class="italic">a</span>, while values of 
  <span class="italic">m</span> only attain small values, mirroring our findings for weak selection (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>B). Values of 
  <span class="italic">m</span> are small, as survival in classical size‐fecundity models increases monotonically with size (Smith and Fretwell, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0074">1974</a>; Parker and Macnair, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0065">1978</a>), resulting in an open‐ended distribution of surviving maternal phenotypes. As a result, a mother's size is always less informative about the environment relative to a scenario of stabilizing selection in which the distribution of phenotypes is narrowly concentrated around an optimum. An exception to this rule occurs when 
  <span class="italic">m</span> is expressed by the mother (denoted by 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>m</sub>), while the elevation 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and plasticity 
  <span class="italic">b</span> are expressed by offspring. Here we find that 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>m</sub> evolves to very large magnitudes. This is a result of an arms race, in which offspring evolve ever larger values of their elevation and plasticity as they favor an increased size, whereas 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>m</sub> evolves to ever smaller (negative) values, as mothers favor a reduced offspring size. Ultimately, extinction follows, as the phenotypic variance explodes when the mean maternal effect becomes smaller than 
  <div id="nlm-math-272" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="msub">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <span class="mi">m</span>
      <span class="mo">¯</span>
     </div>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">m</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
    <span class="mo">−</span>
    <span class="mn">1</span>
   </div>
  </div> (Kirkpatrick and Lande, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0036">1989</a>), so that more and more offspring are either too small (
  <div id="nlm-math-273" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">z</span>
     <span class="mi">t</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">z</span>
     <span class="mi"> min </span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>) or no offspring are produced at all (when 
  <div id="nlm-math-274" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">z</span>
     <span class="mi">t</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mi">∞</span>
   </div>
  </div>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the latter outcome seems to be interesting, it remains doubtful whether exclusive maternal expression of 
  <span class="italic">m</span> is biologically relevant. If 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>m</sub> reflects, for example, a manipulative maternal hormone that reduces offspring resource demand, the previously studied scenario implies that offspring can only respond (over evolutionary time) by increasing their expression levels of other substances (through the elevation 
  <span class="italic">a</span> and plasticity 
  <span class="italic">b</span>) to compensate for their decrease in demand. Yet, a scenario that is widely considered to be more likely is that offspring are selected to reduce their level of sensitivity to the maternal hormone 
  <span class="italic">m</span>
  <sub>m</sub> in the first place (Müller et al., 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0062">2007</a>; Tobler and Smith, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0078">2010</a>) (e.g., by reducing the number of hormone receptor binding sites, Groothuis and Schwabl, 
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0019">2008</a>). In that case, the evolved value of the maternal effect 
  <span class="italic">m</span> will be the result of a combined interaction between gene loci expressed in mother and offspring, rather than a result of maternal loci alone. In the context of dispersal, a previous model by Uller and Pen (
  <a rid="evo12635-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#evo12635-bib-0082">2011</a>) has demonstrated that the evolution of offspring insensitivity to maternal manipulation generally results in offspring “winning” the conflict, so that the value of maternal effects reflects the offspring's optimum, rather than that of the mother. Hence, assuming that offspring express 
  <span class="italic">m</span> (rather than their mothers) is likely to be a more reasonable choice when making predictions regarding the strength and magnitude of maternal effects in the long term.
 </p>
</sec>
