<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="evo12635-sec-0170" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strong selection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>C shows that values of phenotypic plasticity 
  <div id="nlm-math-198" class="math">
   <div accent="true" class="mover">
    <span class="mi">b</span>
    <span class="mo">¯</span>
   </div>
  </div> are much larger when selection is strong (here 
  <div id="nlm-math-199" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <div class="msubsup">
     <span class="mi">ω</span>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">z</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mn">2</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mn">0.7</span>
   </div>
  </div>), as individuals are under stronger selection to use environmental information to match the fluctuating environment. Regarding maternal effects, we find that when 
  <span class="italic">m</span> evolves together with plasticity, a qualitatively similar pattern occurs as for the case of weak selection (compare Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>B and D): maternal effects evolve to slight positive values in environments characterized by strong, positive autocorrelations between subsequent generations (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>E), whereas they evolve to negative values otherwise. Moreover, negative values of 
  <div id="nlm-math-200" class="math">
   <div accent="true" class="mover">
    <span class="mi">m</span>
    <span class="mo">¯</span>
   </div>
  </div> can be substantial in case the environment is sufficiently negatively correlated close to 
  <div id="nlm-math-201" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">f</span>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mi">π</span>
   </div>
  </div>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When maternal effects evolve in the absence of phenotypic plasticity, we find that strong selection favors maternal effects of a substantial magnitude (gray line in Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>D). Interestingly, maternal effects evolve to be large and positive in slowly changing environments, which are characterized by a positive environmental autocorrelation between subsequent generations (Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a> E). By contrast, in rapidly changing environments maternal effects evolve to negative values of a substantial magnitude, again in line with the environmental autocorrelation. To conclude, the strength of phenotypic selection matters considerably to the evolution of maternal effects, as only slight negative maternal effects were found in a corresponding scenario of weak selection (compare gray lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="evo12635-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#evo12635-fig-0004">4</a>B and D). Strong selection is conducive to the evolution of maternal effects, as it gives rise to a distribution of maternal phenotypes 
  <div id="nlm-math-202" class="math">
   <div class="mrow">
    <span class="mi">p</span>
    <span class="mo">(</span>
    <div class="msubsup">
     <span class="mi">z</span>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">t</span>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <span class="mn">1</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">*</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">)</span>
   </div>
  </div> that is closely centered around the selective optimum 
  <div id="nlm-math-203" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <span class="mi">θ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mi">t</span>
     <span class="mo">−</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>. As a result, the maternal phenotype is more informative about the location of the selective optimum to offspring.
 </p>
</sec>
