<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par31" class="p">It should be noted that our study measured egg survival rates under laboratory conditions. In nature, survival rates should be considerably lower due to eggs being consumed by generalist predators, such as flatworms [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>] and oribatid mites (unpublished data), blown away by strong winds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>] or washed away when ponds overflow [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. Therefore, our calculations most likely overestimate future egg survival rates. Still, this does not necessarily mean that the studied populations would perish under climate change. For instance, predator and competitor populations may be affected by climate change as well, which would change biotic interactions. Next to that, vulnerability is also determined by the capacity of organisms to acclimate or adapt to novel environmental conditions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>]. Finally, spatial rescue-effects could reduce risks of, at least permanent, population extinction [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. Although a sequence of short inundations in one pool could lead to a local extinction, it could be followed by recolonization from neighboring populations if these source populations are able to persist under climate change. Yet, in pools with median inundation lengths shorter than 9 days, the number of dispersing eggs required to maintain long term positive population growth under future conditions would be unrealistically high relative to field estimates of passive dispersal rates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>] as is discussed further in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref>. Selection, followed by local adaptation, could also moderate the fitness effects of climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>] and a number of studies have picked up signatures of rapid selection for specific genotypes in response to increased temperatures in freshwater invertebrates [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>]. However, it seems as if 
 <italic class="italic">B. wolfi</italic> populations are approaching their limits for adaptation because even under present-day conditions they cannot maintain permanently viable populations in the most ephemeral pools within the Korannaberg cluster. Future work should include experimental evolution trials during which zooplankton populations are exposed to realistic changes in temperature and inundation regime so that potential adaptation can be tracked across generations.
</p>
