<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, leaving aside the potential causes and the mechanistic basis for the observed changes, doubts have been raised recently about the validity of a relationship between temperature and body-size in endothermic species [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. In line with this, our semi-quantitative review of current evidence on temporal change in body size for endothermic vertebrates suggests that no clear pattern is evident. Specifically, after analyzing data from 46 studies, comprising a total of 369 populations of birds and mammals (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0183051.s002" class="xref">S1 Dataset</xref>), we conclude that: (i) regardless of the statistical significance of the changes, the proportion of populations that increase their size is similar to the proportion of populations that decrease their size (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183051.g001" class="xref">Fig 1a</xref>), and (ii) when the statistical significance of the changes is taken into account, nearly two-thirds of populations analyzed to date showed no significant temporal changes in body size (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183051.g001" class="xref">Fig 1b</xref>). In addition, two intriguing points emerge from this semi-quantitative assessment. First, with a couple of exceptions, all the studies analyzing only a single population reported significant temporal change in size, while all the studies analyzing more than one population (or species) indicate that no significant changes are common. Such differences clearly suggest a publication bias that could affect impressions about the ubiquity of temporal changes in body size (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]). Second, with very few exceptions, studies analyzing more than one population of the same species, or the combination of different studies evaluating different populations of the same species, indicate that observed responses usually vary, in both the sign of the trend and statistical significance, from one population to the other. That is, there is significant variation in body size changes from site to site, which suggest that idiosyncratic responses, probably linked to differences in local conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] or even to dispersal events between localities [
 <xref rid="pone.0183051.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], are common. In summary, it is clear that we need to evaluate much more data before accepting that a reduction in body mass associated with global warming or, more generally, with global environmental change, comprises a general rule for endotherms. In particular, we need to conduct more multi-species comparative studies, to understand the natural variation in phenotypic responses, and use similar methods (e.g., the same measurement of body size) across large geographic areas, to reduce the incidence of confounding factors and to account for potential site-to-site fluctuations.
</p>
