<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although MaxEnt cannot be viewed as an entirely objective modeling method due to the effects of choosing different settings (Merow et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), we consider the final models not to be unnecessarily complex based on the knowledge of vegetation types, the environmental space, and the specific data set used in this study. In our study, the results may be influenced by several factors. Firstly, we compiled the presence‐only data from different sources, and it is highly likely that not all native occurrence records of the species have been included in this study. Secondly, the distributions of Dipterocarp trees are relatively well known across India, Bangladesh, Nepal, and Myanmar (e.g., Alam et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Appanah &amp; Turnbull, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Champion &amp; Seth, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1968</xref>; Chitale &amp; Behera, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This may be partly responsible for the higher number of species occurrence records in these areas compared to other native ranges. As the main objective of our study was to assess species vulnerability to climate change, we used only bioclimatic variables in the model. The realized climatic niche for the Dipterocarp trees that we describe here represents a close approximation to reality (Alam et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Champion &amp; Seth, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1968</xref>; Chitale &amp; Behera, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Future research needs to focus on mechanistic modeling of the Dipterocarp trees using detailed understanding of the physiological response of species to environmental factors (Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece32846-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
