<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> Gene
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total genomic DNA was extracted from blood samples collected from the brachial vein in heparinized capillary tubes. Blood was stored in a cool bag while in the field and subsequently at -20°C in the lab, until used. DNA extraction was performed by alkaline lysis using 6 µL of blood in 100 µL of a 50 mM NaOH at 100°C for 20 minutes. Extracted DNA was quantified using a spectrophotometer and diluted to a final concentration of 50–100 ng/µL 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino2">[44]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to design species-specific primer for genotyping purposes, we initially used the primers published by 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Johnsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Johnsen1">[31]</a> on barn swallow DNA samples. The amplified PCR fragments were then sequenced (BMR genomics, Padua, Italy) and a new set of primers designed on barn swallow genomic sequence. Genomic DNA samples were screened for length polymorphism in the 
  <span class="italic">Clk</span>polyQcds by PCR amplification followed by resolution and detection on a conventional DNA sequencing machine using a commercial GeneScan service for genotyping (Macrogen Inc., Seoul, Korea). We used PCR forward primer (5′-labelled with 6-FAM dye) 5′-(6FAM)GGGACAGGTGGTGACAGCTTATC-3′ and reverse primer 
  <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">5′- CTGCTGATGGTCCTGCTGACT-3′</div> (Sigma-Aldrich). Amplification reactions were as follows: 2 µL of extracted DNA (100–200 ng), 1.5 mM of Mg
  <span class="sup">2+</span>; Taq DNA polymerase 1.35 U (Genespin, Milano, Italy); 0.4 µL of each primer (stock 10 µM); 2 µL of dNTPs (stock 2mM), in a final volume of 20 µL. PCR amplification profile was as follows: 95°C/2 min, followed by 5 cycles at 95°C/30s, 65°C/30s 72°C/30s, decreasing 1°C each cycle (touchdown PCR), then by 30 cycles at 95°C/30 s, 60°C/30 s, 72°C/45 s. A final extension step was included at 72°C for 7 min. Samples were kept at 7°C until analyzed. Two internal size standards were used: the conventional molecular size standard HD400 ROX (Applied Biosystems) and a molecular weight standard generated ‘in-house’ by using a previously characterized swallow DNA sample, homozygous for the most common (Q
  <sub>7</sub>; see below) allele using the same forward primer, this time labeled with HEX. The PCR amplification with 6-FAM and HEX labeled primers were carried out separately and then 2 µL of the HEX-labeled PCR amplification reaction were added to each sample.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reliability of molecular data were confirmed by randomly picking 80 samples and repeating the GeneScan analysis independently. Moreover each heterozygous genotype was double checked by repeating the PCR amplification reaction and sequencing. The most common allele was sequenced and its PCR amplification fragment proved to be 112bp long, coding for a CLOCK protein containing a stretch of 7 glutamine residues. In accordance with 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Johnsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Johnsen1">[31]</a>, the allele was named Q
  <sub>7</sub> (or 
  <span class="italic">Clk</span>polyQ
  <sub>7</sub>). Recently, the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene sequence of the barn swallow has been published in GenBank 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Dor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Dor1">[34]</a>. Our sequences perfectly match those published (acc. no. JN642465-JN642524) The screening of 922 barn swallow individuals led to the identification of a total of 4 alleles, each differing by multiple of 3 base pairs. The alleles were named according to the number of glutamine residues predicted in the mature protein, as Q
  <sub>5</sub>-Q
  <sub>8</sub>
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Dor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Dor1">[34]</a> Statistical tests were conducted using genotype classes.
 </p>
</sec>
