<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field Procedures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During four breeding seasons (2002: n  =  173 individuals from 6 different farms; 2005: n  =  74, 7 farms; 2009: n  =  89, 4 farms, 2011: n  =  586, 19 farms) we studied barn swallows breeding at a total of 29 farms in an intensively cultivated farmland area near Milano (N Italy). We chose to consider birds from different, non-consecutive years in order to reduce the odds of stochastic extremeness both in breeding dates and gene frequencies, and to reduce any effect of temporal autocorrelation in the data. Owing to low levels of genetic diversity at 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span>, in the analyses we pooled the data from different years. In the analyses, however, we also appropriately controlled for any effect of inter-annual variation in mean breeding dates due to e.g. meteorological conditions by including year as a random effect in linear mixed models (see 
  <span class="italic">Statistical analyses</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We regularly visited the colonies to record breeding events and capture breeding adults. Because adults normally spend the night inside the buildings where they breed, they were efficiently captured by placing mist nets at all entrances before dawn. All individuals were subjected to a number of standard measurements and a blood sample was collected by puncturing the brachial vein. Before being released, all individuals were marked with a unique combination of colour rings and patches on breast and belly feathers. Sex of adults was identified by inspection for a brood patch (indicating female, as males do not incubate in European populations) and for a prominent cloacal protuberance (indicating male), and by direct observation of sexual and social behaviour at the nest. In case of any doubt, sexing was confirmed molecularly 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino2">[44]</a>. For the purpose of the present study, we recorded Julian date of laying of the first egg in the first clutch for females or social mate of individual males. This variable was used as the core phenological indicator of timing of breeding throughout the study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To obtain information on age of the breeding adults we took advantage of the extremely high breeding philopatry of barn swallows in our study area as well as in other parts of their European range, which implies that individuals that have bred in a particular farm in one year return to breed in the same farm in the following year(s) 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Mller3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Mller3">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino3">[45]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino4">[46]</a> (C. Scandolara pers. comm.). The farms for which information on age of breeding adults was available were those where we managed to capture the vast majority of the breeding adults in the year (
  <span class="italic">i</span>-1) preceding that (year 
  <span class="italic">i</span>) to which individual phenological data refer. High breeding philopatry in combination with effectiveness of our effort to capture the vast majority of the breeding adults imply that adults that had not already been captured as adults during year 
  <span class="italic">i</span>-1 in year 
  <span class="italic">i</span> could be assumed to be yearlings hatched in year 
  <span class="italic">i</span>-1. Conversely, individuals that had already been captured as adults in year 
  <span class="italic">i</span>-1 were considered as two- or more years old. Thus, for the purpose of this study we classified swallows as yearlings (1-year old) or older (≥ 2 years old) birds 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Mller3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Mller3">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino3">[45]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Saino4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Saino4">[46]</a>. The core sample of the present study consists of 632 adults for which both age and breeding date were known (see 
  <span class="italic">
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="s3" href="#s3">Results</a>
  </span> for age by sex sample sizes). Because breeding dates are strongly affected by age (see above) and the frequency of particular genotypes among older birds was very low (see below), the analyses were run on either age class separately. However, an additional 290 genotyped individuals of unknown age/breeding date were included in the statistics of allele frequencies and heterozygosity, and in the tests on deviation from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most nestlings were ringed every year in the study farms, and we could thus confirm that no pairs of the very few siblings (see also below) that are recruited in their original colony were included in the sample. Indeed, barn swallows have very low natal philopatry, as only less than 5% of offspring were recruited locally on average. Hence, given: 1) the very low natal philopatry and large natal dispersal of barn swallows 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Mller3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Mller3">[41]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Turner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Turner1">[43]</a>; 2) the very large size of the population of swallows breeding at a distance from the study colonies within the natal dispersal of barn swallows 
  <a rid="pone.0035140-Ambrosini1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035140-Ambrosini1">[47]</a>; 3) that siblings seem not to disperse together (our unpublished data); and 4) that less than 40% of the swallows breeding in any given colony were included in the study, the chances that siblings that could not be recognized as such (because they had not been ringed as nestlings) were included in the analyses are likely to be very small. Moreover, due to large natal dispersal and point 4 above, the chances that parent-offspring pairs were included also appear to be very small and in no case this occurred for local recruits whose parents could be identified by direct observation at the nest.
 </p>
</sec>
