<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Buffalo River originates in the Boston Mountains region of Arkansas, USA and flows 238 km before entering the White River with a drainage area of 3,465 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Beginning in 1972, the National Park Service has protected approximately 90% of the river length. The Arkansas Game and Fish Commission sampled smallmouth bass in the Buffalo River twelve years between 1992 and 2012 using boat electroshocking (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202737.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Sites were sampled a single time each year and during each sample fish were measured to the nearest millimeter and weighed to the nearest gram. We selected a subset of data from sites sampled at least three years in the month of October, and during nighttime boat electrofishing. This left 15 samples, collected from four different sites over the course of six years (
 <xref rid="pone.0202737.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The sites were all located in the lower Buffalo River with approximately 24 miles between the most upstream (Rush) and the farthest downstream site (Elephant Head; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202737.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Specific habitat data for each sample was not collected, however, the lower reach of the Buffalo River is characterized by large, deep pools with gravel and boulder substrate, separated by relatively short riffles and runs. We selected only sites sampled during October in order to reduce bias associated with small age-0 fish recruitment to the sampling gear and also because autumn can be a reliable indicator of year-class strength for lotic smallmouth bass [
 <xref rid="pone.0202737.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. We then removed any outliers by examining fish length and weight data. We did this by calculating relative weights (Wr) for each fish &gt; 150 mm [
 <xref rid="pone.0202737.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] and removing any fish with an extreme Wr (Wr &lt; 55 or &gt; 145).
</p>
