<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">Table 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Summary of results and outcomes from the pilot workshops</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" class="table">
  <thead class="thead">
   <tr class="tr">
    <th align="left" class="th">Activity</th>
    <th align="left" class="th">Results Amazon</th>
    <th align="left" class="th">Results Otun</th>
    <th align="left" class="th">Outcomes</th>
    <th align="left" class="th">Feedback</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">PA-BAT workshop</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">PA main benefits identified, in order of priority:
     <break class="break"/> Reducing climate change impacts
     <break class="break"/> Water quality, quantity and access
     <break class="break"/> Sacred places/sites
     <break class="break"/> Tourism
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">PA main benefits identified, in order of priority:
     <break class="break"/> Water quality and quantity
     <break class="break"/> Sites of unique beauty
     <break class="break"/> Reducing climate change impacts
     <break class="break"/> Tourism
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Communities and PA staff generated shared documentation of priority benefits, ranked in order of importance. Additional outputs such as maps included specific locations of sacred sites</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants Pilot #2
     <break class="break"/>“The tool is useful to engage diverse stakeholders; as there are no ‘wrong’ answers, all can participate. Wider representation of other community groups would have improved the workshop”
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Lessons learned workshop</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants noted that:
     <break class="break"/> Risk management is linked to climate change
     <break class="break"/> Little monitoring and research completed, what has been done is uncoordinated
     <break class="break"/> Communities are aware of climate change; opportunities for education
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants noted that:
     <break class="break"/> Technical studies of climate change impacts have been completed
     <break class="break"/> Limited capacity to develop management changes based on research
     <break class="break"/> Solid foundation of cooperation across sectors and communities
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Barriers identified:
     <break class="break"/> Institutional complexity and disconnect
     <break class="break"/> Poor knowledge sharing
     <break class="break"/> Existing knowledge is too technical for many local managers
     <break class="break"/> Local knowledge is not recognised
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participant Pilot #1 “Climate is not something that depends on a specific space, we must expand … and link ourselves to a larger scale than the protected area”</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Futures dialogue</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants identified actions that could be taken now to prepare for climate change, including
     <break class="break"/> Extending networks for collaboration in planning, such as water utility departments;
     <break class="break"/> Reviewing existing and potentially establishing new monitoring programmes to document baselines for benefits as well as species;
     <break class="break"/> Integrating PABAT into existing planning frameworks to ensure benefits are considered alongside conventional objectives
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants identified actions, recognising that 
     <italic class="italic">transformation</italic> is different from 
     <italic class="italic">impacts,</italic> including
     <break class="break"/> Need to review conservation objectives in light of transformation;
     <break class="break"/> Protected areas alone cannot ‘save’ biodiversity, must involve communities;
     <break class="break"/> Larger scale (territorial) organisation and planning is needed, but difficult
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participants developed an alternate way of thinking about planning for climate change that reflected the current state of technical knowledge, incorporated values and benefits, and considered existing decision-making processes and tools.
     <break class="break"/>Participants did not follow through the change in thinking with a fully revised approach to PA policy, planning and management; ideas were generated but proposed incremental rather than transformative changes.
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Participant FD #1 Park manager “We need to manage relationships with other actors, to maintain benefits that Parks generate”
     <break class="break"/>Participant FD #1 National office: “This project has achieved a dialogue between different [park management] levels”.
     <break class="break"/>Participant FD#1 Park manager: “how do we take these ideas into policies, plans and management frameworks for conservation?”
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
