<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Given the severe consequences predicted for increased avian malaria transmission to native birds throughout the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century, it is crucial to develop effective strategies to protect Hawaiian forest birds that also consider future climate change scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Several potential mitigation strategies have been proposed to accomplish the conservation goal of reducing avian malaria impacts, including: improving bird demographics to counter malaria [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], reducing vector abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], and decreasing malaria transmission from mosquitoes to birds [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. We used our epidemiological model and alternative future climate scenarios [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] to evaluate disease management strategies with a goal of maintaining current Hawaiian forest bird populations until 2100. We considered two alternatives to improve bird demographics: evolution of malaria-tolerance (reduced malaria mortality) in native bird species and predator removal to increase bird survival and reproduction. We also evaluated potential reduction in mosquito abundance by: controlling feral pigs which create larval mosquito habitat; introducing vector-incompetent mosquitoes which compete with 
 <italic class="italic">Culex</italic> larvae for resources; and releasing either sterile male mosquitoes or male mosquitoes infected with incompatible 
 <italic class="italic">Wolbachia</italic> strains to reduce mosquito reproduction and abundance. Finally, we considered genetically modified refractory mosquitoes that block malaria parasite development and therefore decrease disease transmission from mosquitoes to birds. We evaluated the potential effectiveness of these mitigation strategies based on population growth, the ratio of model predicted bird abundance at 2100 (future) compared to 2010 (current). Our goal was to identify potential mitigation strategies that result in stable forest bird populations in high-elevation forests or increasing bird populations in mid-elevation forests.
</p>
