<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Spatially continuous current and future climate data were downloaded from the WorldClim database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</ext-link>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al. 2005</xref>). The current data represented interpolation of average monthly climatic records obtained from weather stations between 1950 and 2000, while projected future climate for the year 2075 was estimated using the Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research Organization (CSIRO-MK30) general circulation models (GCM) at 2.5 arcmin resolution. Although the spatial resolution of WorldClim dataset used to infer the thermal niche of small ectotherms affects the final model outputs (
 <xref rid="zox021-B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hannah et al. 2014</xref> and references therein), this topic is still highly debatable in scientific literatures (see 
 <xref rid="zox021-B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bennie et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hannah et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Storlie et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebaudo et al. 2016</xref>). In this study, we used the WorldClim datasets following the same line of thought as 
 <xref rid="zox021-B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rebaudo et al. (2016)</xref> and included all 19 bioclimatic variables as potential predictors (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" class="xref">Supplementary Table S1</xref>). For future climate projections, we considered 3 representative concentration pathways (RCPs) or emission scenarios, to account for differences across climate scenarios. For the current study, we choose 3 scenarios representing different magnitudes of greenhouse gas emissions: a high RCP 6.0 characterized by a rising radiative forcing pathway leading to ∼1370 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with a global mean temperature rise of 2.2 °C; a medium RCP 4.5 where greenhouse gas emissions stabilizes at ∼650 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with a global mean temperature rise of 1.8 °C; and lastly, the lowest RCP3PD 3.0 where greenhouse gas emissions peak at ∼490 ppm CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with a global mean temperature rise of 1.0 °C by 2100 (
 <xref rid="zox021-B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Riahi et al. 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thomson et al. 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="zox021-B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van Vuuren et al. 2011</xref>). For convenience, in this study we refer to these RCPs as “low mitigation” (RCP3PD), “medium mitigation” (RCP4.5), and “high mitigation” (RCP6.0).
</p>
