<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was done in five nursing homes in Tønsberg, Norway. The total number of wards in the five nursing homes was 34, varying from three to 13 wards. In all, the five nursing homes cared for 366 patients, varying from 38 to 101 patients in each nursing home. There were totally 765 health care professionals working in the nursing homes. We did not include in the analyses employees that were working less than/equal to 20% (equivalent to one working day per week), or those being on leave during the study period (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 302). Out of the remaining 463 employees, 288 (62.2%) answered the questionnaire (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The response rates varied between 56.9 and 72.2% across the five nursing homes.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Patients, employees and response rates in five nursing homes in Tønsberg, Norway, 2016</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th/>
       <th>Patients (n)</th>
       <th>Employees total (n)</th>
       <th>Employees ≤ 20% &amp; leave (n)</th>
       <th>Employees &gt;  20% invited (n)</th>
       <th>Respondents (n)</th>
       <th>Response rate (%)</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing home 1</td>
       <td>46</td>
       <td>80</td>
       <td>26</td>
       <td>54</td>
       <td>39</td>
       <td>72.2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing home 2</td>
       <td>38</td>
       <td>65</td>
       <td>17</td>
       <td>48</td>
       <td>29</td>
       <td>60.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing home 3</td>
       <td>92</td>
       <td>201</td>
       <td>51</td>
       <td>150</td>
       <td>95</td>
       <td>63.3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing home 4</td>
       <td>101</td>
       <td>215</td>
       <td>92</td>
       <td>123</td>
       <td>70</td>
       <td>56.9</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing home 5</td>
       <td>89</td>
       <td>204</td>
       <td>116</td>
       <td>88</td>
       <td>55</td>
       <td>62.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Total</td>
       <td>366</td>
       <td>765</td>
       <td>302</td>
       <td>463</td>
       <td>288</td>
       <td>62.2</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>Patients = Total number of patients in nursing home</p>
     <p>Employees total = Total number of employees in nursing home</p>
     <p>Employees ≤20% &amp; leave = Number of employees working 
      <span class="bold">≤</span>20% in nursing home, or being on leave during the study period
     </p>
     <p>Employees &gt; 20% invited = Number of invited employees working &gt; 20% in nursing home</p>
     <p>Respondents = Number of employees working &gt; 20% answering the SAQ</p>
     <p>Response rate = Proportion of invited employees working &gt; 20% answering the SAQ</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The characteristics of the 288 respondents have previously been published in another paper [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] and are presented in Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>.
   <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Characteristics of 288 employees in five nursing homes, Norway, responding to the SAQ-A, 2016</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th/>
       <th/>
       <th>Number</th>
       <th>Percent</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="8">Profession</td>
       <td>Registered nurse</td>
       <td>78</td>
       <td>30</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Nursing assistant</td>
       <td>124</td>
       <td>47</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Health worker</td>
       <td>41</td>
       <td>16</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Kitchen personnel</td>
       <td>7</td>
       <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Laundry personnel</td>
       <td>3</td>
       <td>1</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Secretary</td>
       <td>1</td>
       <td>0.4</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Other personnel</td>
       <td>9</td>
       <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>25</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Gender</td>
       <td>Female</td>
       <td>241</td>
       <td>94</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Male</td>
       <td>16</td>
       <td>6</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>31</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="6">Age</td>
       <td>≤ 30 years</td>
       <td>47</td>
       <td>18</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>31–40 years</td>
       <td>44</td>
       <td>17</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>41–50 years</td>
       <td>65</td>
       <td>25</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>51–60 years</td>
       <td>78</td>
       <td>30</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>≥ 61 years</td>
       <td>30</td>
       <td>11</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>24</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="7">Work experience in total</td>
       <td>≤ 5 years</td>
       <td>44</td>
       <td>17</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>6–10 years</td>
       <td>29</td>
       <td>11</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>11–20 years</td>
       <td>60</td>
       <td>23</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>21–30 years</td>
       <td>68</td>
       <td>26</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>31–40 years</td>
       <td>56</td>
       <td>21</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>≥ 41 years</td>
       <td>9</td>
       <td>3</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>22</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="7">Work experience in nursing home</td>
       <td>≤ 2 years</td>
       <td>59</td>
       <td>22</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>3–5 years</td>
       <td>60</td>
       <td>22</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>6–10 years</td>
       <td>56</td>
       <td>21</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>11–20 years</td>
       <td>57</td>
       <td>21</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>21–30 years</td>
       <td>30</td>
       <td>11</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>≥ 31 years</td>
       <td>6</td>
       <td>2</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>20</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="5">Position job</td>
       <td>21–40%</td>
       <td>30</td>
       <td>12</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>41–60%</td>
       <td>42</td>
       <td>16</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>61–80%</td>
       <td>78</td>
       <td>30</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>≥ 81%</td>
       <td>107</td>
       <td>42</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>31</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Norwegian native speaker</td>
       <td>Yes</td>
       <td>226</td>
       <td>83</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>No</td>
       <td>47</td>
       <td>17</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Missing</td>
       <td>15</td>
       <td/>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>Proportions (%) not including missing data</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Translation procedures</div>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The original SAQ-A was translated according to the principles adapted from Beaton et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. The procedures with translation, back-translation and adaptation by an expert committee with clinicians and researchers are described in another paper [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Completing the SAQ-A takes approximately 15 min.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scoring</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SAQ-A has 62-items where the health care workers give their responses using a 5-point Likert scale: 1 = disagree strongly, 2 = disagree slightly, 3 = neutral, 4 = agree slightly, 5 = agree strongly. The category “Not applicable” was recoded into missing values in the data analyses. We reversed scores of negatively worded items. Factor scores were calculated by summing scores on items hypothesized to belong to each factor.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypothesized factor structure</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The original SAQ, developed at the University of Texas at Austin [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], described six factors: Teamwork climate, Safety climate, Working conditions, Job satisfaction, Perceptions of management and Stress recognition (Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). Not all the items in the original SAQ were covered by these six factors. The remaining items were included to provide information considered useful for local quality improvement interventions.
   <div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The six factors and corresponding items in the original Safety Attitudes Questionnaire (SAQ) version (Sexton et al, 2006)</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="6">Teamwork climate</td>
       <td>Nurse input is well received in this office</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>In this office, it is difficult to speak up if I perceive a problem with patient care.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Disagreements in this office are resolved appropriately (i.e., not 
        <span class="italic">who</span> is right but 
        <span class="italic">what</span> is best for the patient).
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I have the support I need from other personnel to care for patients.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>It is easy for personnel in this office to ask questions when there is something that they do not understand.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>The physicians and nurses here work together as a well-coordinated team.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="7">Safety climate</td>
       <td>I would feel safe being treated here as a patient.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Medical errors are handled appropriately in this office.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I receive appropriate feedback about my performance.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>In this office, it is difficult to discuss errors.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I am encouraged by my colleagues to report any patient safety concerns I may have.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>The culture in this office makes it easy to learn from the errors of others.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I know the proper channels to direct questions regarding patient safety in this office.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="4">Working conditions</td>
       <td>This office does a good job of training new personnel.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>All the necessary information for diagnostic and therapeutic decisions is routinely available to me.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>This office deals constructively with problem personnel.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Trainees in my discipline are adequately supervised.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="5">Job satisfaction</td>
       <td>I like my job.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Working in this office is like being part of a large family.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>This office is a good place to work.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I am proud to work at this office.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Morale in this office is high.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="4">Perceptions of management</td>
       <td>The management of this office supports my daily efforts.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Office management does not knowingly compromise the safety of patients.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>The levels of staffing in this office are sufficient to handle the number of patients.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I am provided with adequate, timely information about events in the office that might affect my work.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="4">Stress recognition</td>
       <td>When my workload becomes excessive, my performance is impaired.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I am less effective at work when fatigued.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>I am more likely to make errors in tense or hostile situations.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Fatigue impairs my performance during emergency situations (e.g. code or cardiac arrest).</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For Teamwork climate in the present study, two items (Q35: It is easy for personnel in this nursing home ward to ask questions when there is something that they do not understand; and Q38: The physicians and nurses here work together as a well-coordinated team) were removed from the hypothesized factor structure model. One of these items (Q38) referred to cooperation with physicians, and was removed since physicians are more seldom present in nursing homes than in hospitals and GP practices. The other item (Q35) was removed as the need to ask questions may be perceived less prevalent in nursing home care. Based on the previously validated factor structure of the Norwegian SAQ-A [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>], we hypothesized that Q18 (The levels of staffing in this nursing home ward are sufficient to handle the number of patients) should be moved from Perceptions of management to Working conditions, and that Q17 (The nursing home ward management does not knowingly compromise the safety of patients) in Perceptions of management should be exchanged with Q9 (Senior management of this nursing home ward is doing a good job).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data were collected in the five nursing homes in February 2016. Paper versions of the SAQ-A were distributed by administrative contact persons to the health care workers. Filled-in questionnaires were returned anonymously in boxes. Questionnaires were scanned into an SPSS data file for analysis.</p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reports with the SAQ-A results were sent to nursing home wards with at least five responders. The employees were recommended to discuss local patient safety factors, and to develop strategies for improvement in their own nursing home ward.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To reduce loss of cases by listwise deletion of cases with missing data, imputation of missings were done by multiple regression analysis with SPSS v.24. Values were imputed for the “real missing”s (but not for those who failed to return a valid value by ticking the box “Not applicable”). For each variable with missing values imputed scores were predicted by the five answers (among the answers to the 28 questions in the confirmatory factor analysis) most strongly correlated to the variable in question.</p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SPSS was used to estimate the Cronbach alphas, corrected item-total correlation, item-to-other-factor correlations and item-descriptive statistics. An indicator of an item not belonging where it was hypothesized to sit is whether its removal would markedly improve the variable set’s Cronbach’s alpha, a measure of the extent to which the responses of items within a factor correlated pairwise. Cronbach alpha scores were considered good if between 0.70 and 0.90, and acceptable if above 0.60 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. Corrected item-total correlations were checked and compared to item-to-other-factor correlations to see if the items correlated more strongly with the factor they were hypothesized to belong to than with the other factors.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hypothesized six factor model was tested by confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) in AMOS, using data from respondents answering all of the items, including the imputed responses. As factors reflect the correlation structure in the item responses, valid factors should reflect a thematic logic that is coherent with the purpose of the questionnaire. CFA provides goodness-of-fit indices which show how the survey responses comply with the pre-hypothesized factor model.</p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The following goodness-of-fit indices (indicators of how well the factor pattern in the survey responses conforms with the hypothesized factor model) were calculated: the chi-square/degrees of freedom ratio (χ
   <span class="sup">2</span>/d.f.), the p, the Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA), the p
   <sub>close</sub>, the Comparative Fit Index (CFI) and the Hoelter 0.05. Acceptable goodness-of-fit values indicate that the SAQ-A measures patient safety climate by the hypothesized factors. The χ
   <span class="sup">2</span>/d.f. should be below 2.5 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>], the 
   <span class="italic">p</span> value should exceed 0.05, the RMSEA should not exceed 0.08, the p
   <sub>close</sub> value should exceed 0.05 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>], the CFI should exceed 0.90 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. The Hoelter 0.05 - an estimate of the largest sample for which a data set with these intercorrelations among the variables would confirm the model – should exceed 200 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical considerations</div>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This was a study on patient safety climate among employees in nursing homes, conducted in compliance with the Helsinki Declaration. The participants received written information about the purpose of the study, that data would be collected anonymously and treated in confidence. As this study did not involve patients, it was not regarded as a medical and health research project - and was thereby not affected by the Norwegian Health Research Act. Approval from the Committee for medical and health research ethics was therefore not needed. The study was approved by the Norwegian Social Science Data Services: the governmental agency for protecting survey research respondent privacy according to the Norwegian Personal Data Act (Ref. No. 2015/42892).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
