<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Future climate change poses an intensifying threat to many bird species, with global to local implications. A global assessment of climate change vulnerability based on climate change exposure and trait-based measures of sensitivity and adaptive capacity (considering traits such as habitat specialization, lifespan, dispersal capacity, and fecundity) suggests 24–50% of birds are highly vulnerable to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In the U.S. and Canada, a model-based assessment of climate sensitivity suggests 21% of bird species are highly sensitive to climate change, such that they may lose half of their climatically suitable ranges by mid-century [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. In the Great Lakes region of North America, 26% of 46 migratory species were classified as vulnerable to climate change when their full annual cycle was considered [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Locally, 36% of 358 birds in California were classified as vulnerable to climate change with 72% of the 29 state or federally listed species among them [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. A changing climate will impact a park’s suitability for species, with corresponding effects on community composition and relative abundances. Climate suitability for a species is characterized using ecological niche models, which correlate species occurrence data with environmental covariates including climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Model predictions can be transferred into geographic space to map species distributions under projected future climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Estimates of climate suitability may correlate with relative abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], and changes in climate suitability track population trends over time [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Thus, projections of changing climate suitability can provide insight into how populations and assemblages may respond to future climate change.
</p>
