<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The limiting temperature for winter survival depends on a range of factors, including tick species, developmental stage, number of days of tick exposure to a given temperature, and snow cover. For instance, 
 <italic class="italic">I. ricinus</italic> can survive 24-h exposure to temperatures ranging from −14.4 °C to −18.9 °C, but exposure for 30 days to only −10 °C can be lethal for a high proportion of unfed nymphs and diapausing engorged larvae and nymphs (
 <xref rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Knülle and Dautel, 1997</xref>). Northern temperate tick species (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">I. ricinus</italic> and ornate cow tick 
 <italic class="italic">Dermacentor reticulatus</italic>) are well adapted to survive in sub-zero temperatures (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Medlock et al., 2013</xref>), but the capacity to supercool to temperatures of ≤ −17 °C appears to be an inherent ability of many tick species, regardless geographic origin (
 <xref rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dautel and Knülle, 1996</xref>). Paradoxically, enhanced snow cover may promote overwintering tick survival by preventing repeated freeze–thaw cycles, which may be more detrimental (
 <xref rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Medlock et al., 2013</xref>). On the Antarctic Peninsula, the seabird tick 
 <italic class="italic">Ixodes uriae</italic> is exposed to extreme environmental conditions during the off-host phase of its life cycle (
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Benoit et al., 2007</xref>). An interesting study has demonstrated that winter temperature affects the prevalence of 
 <italic class="italic">I. uriae</italic> in the Brünnich's guillemot 
 <italic class="italic">Uria lomvia</italic>; an increase of 1 °C in the average winter temperature at the nesting colony site was associated with a 5% increase in the number of infested birds in the subsequent breeding season (
 <xref rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Descamps, 2013</xref>).
</p>
