<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effect of climate change (particularly of increased temperatures) in tropical zones may be deleterious to some species, adversely affecting habitat suitability and forcing certain tick species to colonize new areas. In South Africa, for example, it has been predicted that increasing the temperature by 2 °C will decrease habitat suitability for four tick species (i.e., the African blue tick 
 <italic class="italic">Rhipicephalus decoloratus</italic>, the South African bont tick 
 <italic class="italic">Amblyomma hebraeum</italic>, the brown ear tick 
 <italic class="italic">Rhipicephalus appendiculatus</italic> and the small smooth bont-legged tick 
 <italic class="italic">Hyalomma truncatum</italic>) (
 <xref rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Estrada-Peña, 2003</xref>). Another study suggested that the progressive increase in temperatures seems to be forcing the dispersion of tropical bont tick 
 <italic class="italic">Amblyomma variegatum</italic> towards areas outside of zones that have a prolonged dry period in Zimbabwe (
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Estrada-Peña et al., 2008</xref>). Indeed, high temperatures adversely affect tick questing activity, especially at dry conditions (
 <xref rid="bib83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Randolph, 2009</xref>). In southern Italy, we observed a decline in the questing activity by nymphs and adults of 
 <italic class="italic">I. ricinus</italic> during summer (
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dantas-Torres and Otranto, 2013a</xref>). Interestingly enough, questing activity by larvae was apparently not affected in the same area. We have also observed a seasonal variation in the effect of climate on the biology of brown dog tick (
 <italic class="italic">Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> sensu lato) in southern Italy (
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dantas-Torres et al., 2011</xref>). Indeed, high temperatures may be deleterious under low humidity conditions, even for ticks that are physiologically adapted to drier environments, such as the brown dog tick (
 <xref rid="bib107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yoder et al., 2006</xref>).
</p>
