<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The concept of adaptation is not new as it is widely used. Adaptation remains to be a common practice that has been widely used before (Burton, Diringer &amp; Smith 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). Burton et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>) went on to further explain that human beings are amongst the most adaptable animal species on earth. Humans have been adjusting to changes in the environment few decades ago. Adaptation in the context of climate change is viewed as a means of strengthening resilience of individuals and systems to climate change and climate vulnerability (Elmum, Modise &amp; Marr 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Apparently, adaptation has most often been assessed in the context of vulnerability to climate change. As a result, adaptation to climate change is usually preceded by analysis of perception of climate change as this is what spurs an individual or group to want to respond to perceived climate change or not (Elmum et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Adaptation measures in agricultural practices include crop and livestock variation, community-based adaptation, water storage, irrigation, rainwater harvesting, water-conserving techniques and the use of drought-resistant crop varieties (Mugambiwa 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>).Current induced climate change experiences in developing countries are huge and causing devastating experiences to the poor (Dujardin, Hermesse &amp; Dendoncker 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). The huge challenge of this exposure to changing climate is exacerbated by high levels of sensitivity of social and ecological systems coupled with limited capacity of developing states to respond to the effects. With climate change, adaptation has gained new prominence and probably a new meaning. Climate change present not only threats to human lives and livelihoods but also risks to the economy and infrastructures (Mashizha, Monga &amp; Dzvimbo 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017a</xref>). Developing countries need to invest in environmental practices that are resilient to climate change as it goes a long way in addressing the challenges and risks posed by climate change.
</p>
