<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nuclear microsatellite genotyping and data analysis</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eleven microsatellite markers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> were selected based on allelic size range, annealing temperature and scoring performance. Primers (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>) were synthesised and labelled with fluorescent dyes at the 5′ ends for PCR amplification
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Capillary separation and allele size scoring were performed following Wei 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> and Guo 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Because 
  <span class="italic">S. waltoni</span> is a tetraploid fish, and because it is unknown which alleles form pairs, we were unable to use software such as LOSITAN
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span> to test for outlier loci. Therefore, microsatellite loci were considered as dominant markers and multilocus allelic phenotypes were transformed into presence (1) or absence (0) for each individual. Each band was considered as a single bi-allelic locus with an amplifiable (dominant) and a null (recessive) allele. To detect candidate bands under selection, the 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub> outlier method was performed using three softwares: BayeScan 2.1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, Arlequin 3.5 and Mcheza
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. For BayeScan, we used the default values with respect to the thinning interval, tuning of the proposal distributions, the number of pilot runs, and the uniform prior boundaries for 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>IS</sub> and included a burn-in period of 50,000 iterations and prior odds of the neutral model of 10. Default settings were also used in the Arlequin and Mcheza analyses. The data set was divided in two subgroups, “neutral” and “selected” (outlier) loci following Luikart 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. For the neutral data set, we removed the bands putatively identified as outliers, both those classified as under directional and stabilizing selection, by any two of the three methods (BayeScan, Arlequin and Mcheza). All analyses were performed on the all bands and the neutral bands data sets.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic diversity indices such as Nei’s gene diversity index (
  <span class="italic">H</span>), Shannon’s information index (
  <span class="italic">I</span>), the percentage of polymorphic loci (
  <span class="italic">PPL</span>), Nei’s unbiased genetic distance, and the relationships between populations and individuals (PCoA) were evaluated following Guo 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Using the binary data set, a Bayesian clustering analysis was carried out in STRUCTURE 2.3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> to determine the expected number of genetic clusters, as described by Guo 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Ten independent runs were performed for each cluster set (
  <span class="italic">K</span>) from 1 to 5. The Δ
  <span class="italic">K</span> metric
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> was used to assess the best fitting 
  <span class="italic">K</span> through Structure Harvester (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://taylor0.biology.ucla.edu/structureHarvester/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://taylor0.biology.ucla.edu/structureHarvester/</span>) and runs were grouped and visually displayed using CLUMPAK (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://clumpak.tau.ac.il/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://clumpak.tau.ac.il/</span>). To confirm the distribution of individuals amongst genetic groups and verify the adscription of individuals to the clusters revealed by STRUCTURE, we also used the clustering approach implemented in BAPS 6.0
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. BAPS analyses were carried out on groups of individuals (i.e. site-samples) rather than individuals, with simple model assumptions (i.e. no admixture and uncorrelated allele frequencies). BAPS was set with 10 replicate runs for each 
  <span class="italic">K</span> (from 2 to 5) and another 100 replicate runs with 
  <span class="italic">K</span> fixed to the inferred number of genetic clusters (best 
  <span class="italic">K</span>). The best fitting 
  <span class="italic">K</span> was assessed using the highest Log marginal likelihood [Log(ML)] value. And then, an admixture model was run for the inferred number of clusters (1000 iterations, minimum individuals per cluster = 5, reference individuals = 200, iterations for reference individuals = 10).
 </p>
</sec>
