<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample collection, sample sizes and DNA isolation</div>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling was designed to collect 
  <span class="italic">S. waltoni</span> from as many sites as possible in the YLTR (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) because 
  <span class="italic">S. waltoni</span> is only found in the main channel and most tributaries (e.g. Lhasa River (LSR) and Nyang River (NYR)) of the YLTR above the Yarlung Tsangpo Grand Canyon
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. However, in our sampling, it was difficult to find 
  <span class="italic">S. waltoni</span> in the tributaries (e.g. Nyingchi along the NYR), and even in the main channel (e.g. Paizhen). Therefore, based on sampling success rather than on number of sites visited, fish were collected from five populations (Shigatse (SG), Maldrogongkar (MG), Quxu (QX), Shannan (SN) and Mainling (ML)) during 2012 to 2013 (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S8</a>). Based on their position relative to the 30 m high Nierikar Waterfall (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), the populations were divided into western and eastern regions (west of NW: SG, MG, QX and SN; east of NW: ML). All fishes were captured by gillnetting or electro-fishing; fin clips were preserved in 95% ethanol at −20 °C.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population-specific sample sizes reflect a balance across a range of different factors, including time/sampling effort, cost, information content of the marker itself, and the fact that 
  <span class="italic">S. waltoni</span> is a threatened species that is difficult to capture and which now exists at low population numbers. Clearly sample size is important and will influence the results and their interpretation. For microsatellite analyses, 25 to 30 individuals per population is enough to accurately estimate allelic frequencies if locus-specific levels of polymorphism are not very high for this biparentally inherited nuclear DNA marker type
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. For mtDNA, which is maternally inherited and does not experience recombination, it is generally accepted that half of the microsatellite sample size is enough for phylogeography and population genetics analyses. In this study, sample sizes for the microsatellite analyses averaged 44.2 and for the mtDNA averaged 22.8 individuals per population.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic DNA isolation and concentration estimation were performed following Guo 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
