<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P31" class="p">The magnitude of an exposure or dose metric may be impacted by a combination of high, moderate, or low concentrations. In this section, we discuss the evidence for specific concentration ranges within the distribution that are important for human health and vegetation. The specific form of metrics used to assess human health, and vegetation effects vary between regions and countries. Studies which investigate human health or vegetation impacts can reach different conclusions on the nature of exposure- or dose-response relationships because of different biological endpoints and processes. As a result, the metrics used for assessing human health and vegetation impacts provide varying degrees of weighting on the absolute values of the hourly average ozone concentrations that are related to exposure and dose (see description of individual metrics in 
 <xref rid="S11" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Section 2.3</xref>). For both human health and vegetation, in some cases, there have been attempts to identify concentrations, exposures, and doses, below which no effects are observed (
 <xref rid="R210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">de Leeuw and Ruyssenaars, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R199" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">US EPA, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R203" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">US Federal Register, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">CLRTAP, 2017</xref>). There is no consistent evidence of a human health population cutoff for ozone below which no effect is measurable. Other approaches have also been used, including the use of a concentration weighting scheme (e.g., sigmoidal weighting), for assessing potential cumulative vegetation and human health impacts (
 <xref rid="R114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn and Runeckles, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn et al., 1988</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McDonnell et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
