<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47" class="p">Water scarceness will hence largely affect alluvial aquifers and their nitrate content. Large hydrogeological systems, as the Selva basin, may even reduce their concentrations as shown by the simulations (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). However, the fact that they are also recharged by large-scale regional groundwater flows originated from the surrounding ranges (usually without agricultural land uses and therefore with a very low-nitrate content) or even from the basin basement provides and additional diluting flow. The reducing conditions of these deep flows locally enhance natural nitrate attenuation (Puig et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2013</xref>). In consequence, they will be better off than those that just depend on local inputs (i.e., stream recharge and rainfall recharge). These large-scale regional flow systems store and transmit groundwater to the adjacent aquifers systems. From a groundwater quality perspective, their contribution alleviate nitrate content in the deep aquifer levels which, as in the case of La Selva basin, presently show a lower nitrate content than the shallow unconfined aquifers (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). Regional flows additionally have a second advantageous factor: they will unceasingly contribute to the recharge of other systems, usually located in basins, as mountain areas are expected be more resilient to climate change effects on groundwater recharge, as infiltration rates in mountain areas is permeability-limited rather than recharge-limited due to the thin soil layer overlying low permeability rocks (Flint et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2008</xref>; Meixner 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2016</xref>). These regional flows balance the loss of surface rainfall infiltration in low altitude areas. Such flows, as in the Selva and Baix Ter alluvial plains, presently contribute with a high-quality recharge, and it should be expected to remain so for the next decades (Vilanova et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">2008</xref>; Boy-Roura et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
