<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42" class="p">Nevertheless, economic activity and productive and reproductive responsibilities, even if burdensome, may offer women certain bargaining power (Jabeen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">2014</xref>) and render them an opportunity to become resourceful agents of change with adaptive capacity (Gabrielsson and Ramasar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2013</xref>). Albeit causality is difficult to establish between power and desired outcomes, feminist economists see intra-household bargaining power as a discursive resource that women use to improve decision-making and social position (Doss 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2013</xref>). And based on the following typology of power, researchers can explore social relations in climate change adaptation in terms of ‘power to’ meaning the ability to adapt, improve or transform; ‘power with’ involving a joint or collective action with other people; ‘power over’ such as challenging and overcoming an instance of social exclusion or subjugation; and ‘power within’ as an individual cognitive process of confidence and consciousness (De Haan and Zoomers 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2005</xref>). Further, Kabeer (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2011</xref>) sees empowerment as a specific, structural and path-dependent process influencing ability, capacity, and willingness—in a given place or situation—to accept gender norms and other social constraints or influence, challenge, and change them. She (Kabeer 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2011</xref>, p 499) speaks of the ability to participate on equal terms with men in reshaping society, the capacity to exercise strategic control over one’s own life, and the willingness to question one’s position in society. Such reasoning is applicable also to vulnerability and climate change adaptation, showing that gender, and changes in gender norms, is both an individual and societal process, both agency and structure.
</p>
