<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-sensors-19-02940" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The last century has experienced a very intense urbanization transition. It is foreseen that in 2050, 68% of the population will live in the cities. The growing of urban populations is manly driven by social and economic opportunities and the extended availability of services such as health, education, or public transportation [
  <a rid="B1-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-sensors-19-02940">1</a>]. Understanding the key trends in urbanization is crucial to understand the challenges in meeting the needs of their growing urban populations. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nowadays, cities generate 75% of the carbon emission, which means the urban population is highly exposed to pollutants and vulnerable to climate changes [
  <a rid="B2-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-sensors-19-02940">2</a>]. The World Health Organization (WHO) estimates that 63% of global mortality (about 36 million deaths per year) is the result of non-communicable diseases (e.g., cardiovascular disease, cancer, diabetes, and lung disease). A large proportion of these are attributable to the increasing exposure to air pollution concentration. According to the WHO, among all cities in the world, only 20% of the urban population lives in areas that comply with WHO air quality guideline levels regarding particulate matter (PM2.5) [
  <a rid="B3-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-sensors-19-02940">3</a>]. Thus, a high proportion of citizens are exposed to high levels of pollution, putting their health and development at serious risk in the long term [
  <a rid="B4-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-sensors-19-02940">4</a>]. This situation has driven to consider as a priority the need to create tools, guidelines, and recommendations to enable healthier, climate-friendly, and resilient lifestyles within urban environments [
  <a rid="B5-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-sensors-19-02940">5</a>]. Open data initiatives have been launched to provide broad access to data from the public sector, business, and science. In this regard, cities can leverage on digital and Internet of Things (IoT)-enabled technologies to provide actionable insights that help improve the health and wellbeing of citizens. Nowadays, digital technologies integrating sensors from homes, smartphones, wearables, and IoT devices are coming to the market at affordable prices for end users [
  <a rid="B6-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-sensors-19-02940">6</a>]. These technical trends allow citizens to gather and share information about themselves and the environment that surrounds them, known as citizen science. Furthermore, current technological resources represent an opportunity to assess the health status at the population and individual level, as well as identify the barriers and stressors that jeopardize citizens’ health and offer routes to develop new health policies [
  <a rid="B7-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-sensors-19-02940">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this context, the European funded project PULSE (Participatory Urban Living for Sustainable Environments) [
  <a rid="B8-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-sensors-19-02940">8</a>] aims to develop a public health observatory, related policies, and new procedures based on real evidence using data from different sources. Information from the public health systems, remote and fixed environmental sensors, and citizens’ mobile devices is collected in seven cities (Paris, Singapore, Birmingham, Barcelona, New York, Pavia, and Keelung) through a platform architecture and mobile application. Furthermore, the collected data are used to nourish the spatio-temporal and risk stratification models based on modifiable and non-modifiable asthma and type 2 diabetes (T2D) risk factors in each city, including behavioural, environmental, and social risks. The principles of citizens in science are integrated to enable public participation in scientific discovery, monitoring, and experimentation for improving and integrating the data generated into improved health and environmental policies. Following this approach, citizens become active in gathering, sharing, and understanding the data on the local environment using the PulsAir mobile application. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper presents the design and development process of the PulsAir mobile application and data ecosystem model, which enable large quantities of public data collection and processing for striving on the yield potential of scientific research regarding the predictive environmental-health domain, sustainable healthier and greener oriented behaviours in urban environments, and new public policy tools for sustainable urban designs. The combination of the PulsAir application and the data ecosystem is conceived as a novel data-driven technological development designed to overcome information gaps, enabling the fusion of environmental and health data in cities, especially in local areas. Conventional approaches to air quality monitoring in cities are based on networks of static and mobile measurement stations, which are usually sparse and do not allow capturing tempo-spatial heterogeneity or identify pollution hotspots, contributing to the lack of information on health impact at the local level and on polluted areas [
  <a rid="B9-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-sensors-19-02940">9</a>]. Citizens consider that pollution is a main problem with a direct effect on their daily life and health requiring more actions to protect the environment [
  <a rid="B10-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-sensors-19-02940">10</a>]. The main contributions comprise the following: (1) the design and development of the PulsAir gamification-based application; and (2) the data production and consumption ecosystem and backend that integrates all data sources and allows data fusion, in order to link environmental data under a health-focused approach.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through PulsAir, citizens provide information from the environment, position, or mobility, as well as data from activity sensors (e.g., Fitbit). Also, a set of questionnaires are triggered gathering scientific oriented information regarding environment and health aspects of the citizens. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data-driven ecosystem empowers citizens by enabling the data gathered processing to assess the citizens in terms of health risks (i.e., risk of the onset of type 2 diabetes, asthma, and cardiovascular disease (CVD)). The bidirectional path between the application and the data ecosystem allows generating a direct connection between the city and its inhabitants, empowering them to take actions towards improved and healthier behaviours. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides citizen engagement and data processing, the data ecosystem and PulsAir application have been developed, integrating models that support the citizen science data generation and processing, including the fact of acquiring or vetting collected data. The data monitoring process links with the scientific environmental-health research goals through questionnaires that are related to scientifically validated protocols that trigger the tracking of physical activities and environmental pollution information.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The paper is organized as follows. 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-sensors-19-02940" href="#sec2-sensors-19-02940">Section 2</a> presents the materials used and the methods followed to design and develop the PulsAir application. 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3-sensors-19-02940" href="#sec3-sensors-19-02940">Section 3</a> presents the results including the user needs and requirements collected from previous research and focus groups with key stakeholders, the prototype designs and gamification strategy followed, and the final application development, providing information of the workflow and the big data architecture. Finally, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec4-sensors-19-02940" href="#sec4-sensors-19-02940">Section 4</a> presents the discussion and conclusions, as well as future research directions including evaluation of the application within the seven pilot cities.
 </p>
</sec>
