<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2dot2-sensors-19-02940" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2. Application System Design</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The system was designed following a user-centred approach based on the goal-oriented design (GOD) methodology [
  <a rid="B20-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-sensors-19-02940">20</a>], in which end users and stakeholders guide the process, as they will ultimately validate the final product. This application was co-designed with public health organizations (PHOs), defining five different phases that are summarized as follows:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>First phase: definition of the user needs and focus.</p>
    <p>In this phase, research regarding the effects of environmental pollution on the quality of life of people, as well as the effects of an unhealthy lifestyle, was carried out in order to define the metrics for a multidimensional evaluation [
     <a rid="B21-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-sensors-19-02940">21</a>,
     <a rid="B22-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-sensors-19-02940">22</a>]. Furthermore, a benchmark assessment was conducted to identify applications and solutions that raise awareness among users of the effects of environmental pollution on health. Gamification techniques were analysed in order to define, in the second phase, the gamification strategy, to enhance users’ motivation [
     <a rid="B23-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-sensors-19-02940">23</a>]. Finally, focus groups were conducted with PHOs and users to define their needs and requirements to improve citizens’ quality of life.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Second phase: creation of a non-functional prototype and gamification strategy.</p>
    <p>The first version of the system is a non-functional prototype that was built as a set of mock-ups that described the appearance and functionalities of the system. Mock-ups were revised and improved later considering the feedback received from end users. This approach allows to simulate/anticipate the possible user experience through two activities: (1) the definition of the most relevant screens of the application to specify the minimum viable set of functionalities; (2) the definition of the user interaction, which describes the workflow of the screens and its elements to perform a specific task. The non-functional prototype was conceived together with a gamification strategy. The gamification strategy defined is based on the application of game-design elements and game principles in non-gamified contexts [
     <a rid="B24-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-sensors-19-02940">24</a>] in order to produce positive effects on individuals [
     <a rid="B25-sensors-19-02940" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-sensors-19-02940">25</a>]. Concretely, the main goal of the gamification process was to get a positive behaviour change regarding healthy and green habits.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Third phase: development of the prototype.</p>
    <p>In this phase, the different elements of the application were developed, based on the feedback received of the non-functional prototype from phase two. These elements are as follows: (1) interfaces, from home screen to the different modules of the application; (2) communication and interaction with external services such as activity tracker devices and APIs; (3) application workflow, which includes trigger activities, feedback to user, educational content, monitor activities, gamification strategy, and so on. The development of the prototype followed a cross platform application approach, supporting Android and iOS devices, in order to cover all kinds of smartphone users.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
