<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mobile Application Interface</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a> shows the final interface design of the application, specifically the following main elements:
 </p>
 <div list-type="bullet" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Homepage, final design follows a card layout style with a simple and clean background. The cards give access to the different modules of the application, as shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>a. From top to bottom, the cards show the following elements:
   </p>
   <div list-type="order" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>“Me” card, shows the information about the number of questionnaires completed and the risk of developing cardiovascular disease, type 2 diabetes, or asthma, based on the results of the questionnaires completed.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>“My City” card, presents a summary of the air quality and weather conditions at the current location of the user.</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>“Weekly Activity” card, presents the summary of the activities performed in terms of calories burnt, steps, and kilometres travelled. This information is collected through the activity tracker device.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div list-type="bullet" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The “Me” module screen shows the information gathered from the users; the wearable data and the health risks (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>b). The menu, at the bottom of the screen, is used to access the answered questionnaires and suggested educational content and recommendations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The “My City” module shows the air quality and weather information about the city and the current user’s GPS position (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>c). The menu, at the button on the screen, gives access to a pollution map and content related to air pollution.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The usage of the application triggers the gamification engine, allowing users to earn points to level up through the five levels available (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>d). The application starts with a sad avatar living in a dirty city; if the users perform the suggested activity within the application (i.e., questionnaire, educational contents, changes in habits), they will be taken to the next level until they reach the final level that shows a happy avatar living in a clean city (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>e). The Leaderboard screen shows the user’s collected points (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f003" href="#sensors-19-02940-f003">Figure 3</a>f) in order to boost competitions among the citizens.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
