<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mobile Application Workflow</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The application workflow was conceived as a bidirectional interactive path. On one hand, the user shares gathered data with the platform, from physical activity measurements through wearable activity trackers and by answering the questionnaires. On the other hand, users receive back general or customized interventions depending on their profile. This intervention is composed of educational health and environmental guidelines or content, health risk awareness, geo-localized air pollution exposure and data, as well as gamification-oriented information and rewards based on their performance. This intervention aims at making data relevant to citizens to support greener and healthier sustainable behaviours. The process was defined using an incremental strategy, which comprises the following steps:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Monitor: the application tracks GPS position and integrates data of wellness sensor (e.g., Fitbit) and air quality. From time to time, some questionnaire are triggered to the users. The application also tracks the degree of use of the application.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Assess: the gathered information is used to assess the citizens in terms of health risks (risk of the onset of T2D, asthma, and cardiovascular disease).</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Personalize: according to the assessment, the application triggers specific contents and recommendations to the users. The application can identify healthy or green behaviour that needs to be improved and prepare a set of tips to help the user to be aware and understand the importance of modifying a specific behaviour.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Act: the application promotes specific healthy habits by proposing a specific goal to the users (e.g., 8000 daily steps). According to this goal, the application creates a follow-up procedure to check if the goal is achieved in the proposed time (e.g., one day).</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Support and reward: when the user finish the proposed activity, the application triggers a mechanism of reward and supports the user to be motivated.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="sensors-19-02940-f004" href="#sensors-19-02940-f004">Figure 4</a> shows an example of the workflow of a specific case: health risk.
 </p>
</sec>
