<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In relation to climate drivers, the potential future distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.l. and its two major siblings: 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s. and 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> in Nigeria is highly worrisome. Climate change under both high and low emissions scenarios is expected to cause large geographic range expansions with increased distribution density, species shifts and invasions in areas previously too cool for the 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> species population [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Higher prevalence of the malaria vectors projected for high emission scenario corroborates with the prediction of ecological models about shift in the distribution of world biomes in response to changes in climate system associated with increased greenhouse gases [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. Confirming earlier claim that areas with low presence of the studied 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles gambiae</italic> species will possibly experience high prevalence with species migration and invasion, in response to changes in environmental variables fundamental to their distribution patterns [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. This is evidenced in the scenario that the less suitable areas of Sudan, Sahel, Northern and Southern Guinea savannas within Gombe, Bauchi, Yobe, Adamawa and Borno states in North Eastern region [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], are becoming more suitable for the occurrence and distribution of these 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> species under the changing climate regimes. This is expressed in longer rainy season and warmer nights that promote vectors proliferation in a continuous high emissions 21st Century’s world [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The general decline or near dynamic equilibrium in vector species population between 2050s and 2070s under the mitigation scenario—RCP2.6 is assumed to follow indirect effect of mitigation scenario, where increase in global mean temperature is limited to 2°C as regional mean temperature within the tropical country is limited to about 1.4°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Nevertheless, low environmental suitability has been projected to continue in some areas for 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.l., 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s., and 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> based on topography and other ecological gradients [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. This is of course highly noticeable in some high elevation areas of Kaduna, Zamfara, Kebbi, Niger, Bauchi, Gombe and Borno states within Northern and Southern Guinea savannas, and parts of Plateau, Adamawa, Bauchi, and Taraba states within Mid Altitude zone [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. The projected scenario also supports the assertion by Siteti 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>], that, topographic and human settlement patterns affect the spatial distribution of malarial mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. It is also apparent from this study that 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s. and 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> are likely to be more widespread with higher relative probability of occurrence in lowlands and areas with human settlements [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> exhibits low probability of occurrence in Fresh water and Mangrove swamp forests [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] along humid Atlantic coast of the Humid forest within South South region, either based on landforms [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>], soil or climatic characteristics [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]; corroborating with Ayala 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>] who classified these zones unsuitable for 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">arabiensis</italic> in Cameroon. However, 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s. is expected to continue its highest prevalence amongst other species, in line with Okwa 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>] that, 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s. is the most efficient and most widespread within the 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> complex [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. According to Olayemi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0218523.ref079" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>], the epidemiological success of 
 <italic class="italic">An</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gambiae</italic> s.s. is largely dependent on its highly dynamic ecological behaviour, which it evolved over a long time to take advantage of certain tropical weather conditions that encourage mosquito proliferation and human / vector contact.
</p>
