<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Experts were required to provide three types of ordinate scores: an indicator score (for exposure, sensitivity, adaptive capacity and cumulative non-climatic factors), weight scores (to determine the relative importance of an indicator to the overall species vulnerability) and confidence scores (to account for uncertainty in the scoring). A scoring scale of low, moderate, high and very high was used for all vulnerability indicators while low, moderate and high, was used for weight scores and confidence scores. Numerical values of 1 to 3 were attributed to the scoring scales of the weight and confidence scores where low = 1, medium = 2, high = 3. In assigning numerical values to vulnerability indicators, the scoring bins for exposure and sensitivity were attributed values corresponding to low = 1, moderate = 2. high = 3 and very high = 4. In this way, the higher the exposure and sensitivity index for a species the higher its overall climate change vulnerability. Since adaptive capacity has an inverse relationship with vulnerability [
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], the numerical values attributed to the scoring scale was reversed. Therefore, adaptive capacity had values corresponding to low = 4, moderate = 3, high = 2, very high = 1. Using this, the higher the adaptive capacity index (i.e. low vulnerability) the higher the climate change vulnerability. Each indicator score was calculated using the weighted means of the expert’s scores. The exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity index scores were derived using a modified logic rule [
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] instead of averaging the respective indicator scores. Simply averaging all indicator scores has been noted to de-emphasize the effects of high scoring indicators on a species vulnerability [
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Hence, to account for the significance of high scoring indicators, a logic rule was applied, resulting in an adjusted exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity index. The logic rule was applied when more than two indicator-scores within the exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity component was greater than 3.0, therefore, the final component score was adjusted by 0.5. The logic rule ensures that the final vulnerability score of the species reflects the potential for ‘multiple risks and highlights species with ‘life history requirements that environmental changes could impact through multiple mechanisms’ [
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The final cumulative vulnerability score for each species was computed by adding the adjusted scores for exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity index: V = f (E, S, AC), where, V = cumulative vulnerability score, E = exposure index, S = sensitivity index and AC = adaptive capacity index. The final scores, therefore, ranged from 3 (minimum) to 12 (maximum). Species with higher scores were placed in a higher vulnerability rank to the projected changes by mid-century. Seven rank levels were developed to categorize the vulnerability score. No specific standard currently exists in literature to set vulnerability thresholds [
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], hence, to present an easy mechanism to communicate and rank vulnerability, the categories were evenly sub-divided (
 <xref rid="pone.0208182.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Uncertainty was analyzed by averaging expert’s confidence scores for each indicator. A scatterplot was developed to highlight the potential climate impact on the species. A Mann-Whitney U rank test was conducted on the expert’s vulnerability scores to determine if there were significant differences between native and non-native species. Finally, to ascertain the factors driving vulnerability of freshwater fish to climate change, the average of all vulnerability indicators across all species was computed. All computations were derived using Microsoft office Excel 2013 and Minitab Statistical Software.
</p>
