<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changing climate has been linked to changes in phenology or distribution in more than half of nearly 1600 marine, freshwater, and terrestrial species studied 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Parmesan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Parmesan1">[1]</a>. Advancing lay date of birds in warmer springs is one of the most widely reported responses 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-McCleery1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-McCleery1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Crick1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Crick1">[3]</a>. Indeed, a recent review 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Dunn1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Dunn1">[4]</a> documented that 75% of species studied laid eggs earlier in warmer years, and 59% have advanced their mean lay date over time. Very little is known, however, about the fitness consequences of such phenological changes for most of these species, which limits our ability to draw inferences about the effects of warming climate trends on avian population dynamics and trends.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fitness effects of earlier breeding vary among the species of birds that have been studied. In a population of year-round resident song sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Melospiza melodia</span>) in North America, for example, birds initiated breeding earlier in warm springs, and had higher reproductive success when breeding began earlier 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Wilson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Wilson1">[5]</a>. In contrast, among tits (
  <span class="italic">Paridae</span>) and flycatchers (
  <span class="italic">Muscicapidae</span>) in Europe, breeding success generally declines in warm springs, when timing of peak offspring energy demands mismatches with peak prey abundance 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Visser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Visser1">[6]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Both1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Both1">[7]</a>. Based primarily on data from the great tit (Parus major) and pied flycatcher (Ficedula hypoleuca), some authors have suggested that these phenological mismatches and associated fitness declines might become more pronounced as global climate continues to change 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Visser2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Visser2">[8]</a>, particularly for insectivores specializing on prey with a narrow period of peak abundance 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Both1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Both1">[7]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migratory birds with relatively fixed cues for spring migration (e.g., photoperiod) comprise one group that might have particular difficulty matching breeding phenology with changing climatic conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Strode1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Strode1">[9]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Both2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Both2">[11]</a>. The capacity of pied flycatchers to advance their lay date to match advancement of peak prey abundance, for example, appears to be constrained by day-length cues that determine departure from their tropical winter quarters, leading to intensified selection pressure for earlier lay date: early-breeding birds have increasingly higher reproductive success than later-breeding birds 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Both3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Both3">[12]</a>. Likewise, a recent study of six woodland songbird species in the UK suggested that selection pressure for earlier breeding is intensifying among migratory (but not resident) birds 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Goodenough1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Goodenough1">[13]</a>. Overall, avian responses to climate change appear to be slower or more constrained for long-distance migrants than for residents and short-distance migrants 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Jenkins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Jenkins1">[14]</a>, which might contribute to population declines among long-distance migratory species 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Mller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Mller1">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Saino1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Saino1">[16]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not all insectivorous birds, however, might experience fitness or population declines in response to warming climate trends. Differential responses could arise from differences in life history or ecology. The relationship between fitness and the timing breeding, for example, might differ between species that produce only one brood (single brooders) or more than one brood (double brooders) per breeding season 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Wilson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Wilson1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Jiguet1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Jiguet1">[17]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Husby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Husby1">[20]</a>, or might depend on the timing and duration of peaks in food abundance 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Visser3">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Dunn2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Dunn2">[22]</a>. Additional demographic data are needed to test hypotheses about how climate change will affect avian fitness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we used a long-term dataset to examine the effects of spring temperature on breeding initiation date, double brooding, annual fecundity, and selection pressure for early breeding in the black-throated blue warbler (Parulidae: Setophaga caerulescens), a Nearctic – Neotropical migratory passerine. The study was conducted over a 25-year period in the Hubbard Brook Experimental Forest, New Hampshire, United States of America 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes1">[23]</a>, where temperatures have increased 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Reynolds1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Reynolds1">[24]</a> and spring leaf phenology has advanced 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Richardson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Richardson1">[25]</a> between 1957 and 2004. We used temperature and warbler demographic data from this site to address the following questions:
 </p>
 <div list-type="roman-lower" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Does variation in temperature affect mean first lay date?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>How do first lay date and temperature affect the probability of double brooding and annual fecundity?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Does selection pressure to breed earlier intensify in warm years?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>What are the implications of these findings for how double brooded migratory passerines could respond to projected climate warming?</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We emphasize mean lay date because arrival date might be constrained by relatively fixed migratory cues 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Strode1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Strode1">[9]</a> or by events occurring in non-breeding areas 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Marra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Marra1">[26]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Reudink1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Reudink1">[27]</a>. Mean lay date at the population level could advance, despite constrained arrival date, if birds have flexibility in the timing of breeding after arrival 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Both3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Both3">[12]</a>. Furthermore, detection of mean first lay date is likely to be less sensitive to fluctuations in population density or observer bias than detection of first occurrences 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-MillerRushing1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-MillerRushing1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Huppop1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Huppop1">[28]</a>. Because older black-throated blue warblers tend to arrive and settle earlier on breeding grounds than do yearlings 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes2">[29]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes3">[30]</a>, we also examined the effects of breeder age class on timing of breeding and annual fecundity.
 </p>
</sec>
