<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection for Early Breeding</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Black-throated blue warblers, on average, had higher reproductive success when they initiated breeding earlier, and they were under apparent selection pressure to breed earlier in most years of this study. However, the strength of selection on breeding initiation date appeared to fluctuate across years: the correlation between the residuals of the strength of selection on earlier breeding (φ) was −0.54, suggesting that years with relatively strong, negative selection differentials (i.e., strong selection for earlier breeding) were frequently followed by years with relatively weak or even positive selection (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0059467-g003" href="#pone-0059467-g003">Fig. 3A</a>). The reasons for these fluctuations in the strength of selection are unclear, but nonetheless breeding date did not advance over time despite overall selection for earlier breeding. At least three non-exclusive reasons could explain this lack of response to selection for earlier breeding 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Price1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Price1">[50]</a>. First, delayed breeding might be a conservative strategy (i.e., “conservative bet-hedging;” 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Goodenough1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Goodenough1">[13]</a>) that persists because of the potentially high, but unpredictable, costs of beginning too early, such as nest failure due to late spring storms and unseasonably cold temperatures. Such weather-related nest failures have been observed at Hubbard Brook 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes3">[30]</a>. Second, birds in poor condition due to non-heritable causes might be unable to breed as early in the season as birds in superior condition, or they might have a later optimal breeding initiation date, leading to a mean first lay date that is later than the population-level optimum 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Price1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Price1">[50]</a>. Indeed, yearling males initiated first clutches later than older birds, and indirect evidence indicates that yearlings might be in poor condition relative to older birds at the time of arrival: yearlings arrive later on the breeding grounds at Hubbard Brook 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes3">[30]</a> and settle on territories of poor quality 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes2">[29]</a> relative to older birds. Such delayed arrivals have been linked to poor physiological condition on non-breeding grounds in another Neotropical-Nearctic migrant, the American redstart S. ruticilla 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Marra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Marra1">[26]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Reudink1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Reudink1">[27]</a>. Last, selection pressures may differ across this warbler’s broad range 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Webster1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Webster1">[51]</a>. Because natal dispersal in this species is broad 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Holmes3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Holmes3">[30]</a> and the population is well mixed 
  <a rid="pone.0059467-Webster1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0059467-Webster1">[51]</a>, selection pressure in one area might be muted or balanced by opposing pressures in other areas.
 </p>
</sec>
