<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessing the migratory behavior of individuals</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals from two populations of 
  <span class="italic">J. h. thurberi</span> residing in southern California were captured as recently independent offspring and held in captivity under identical conditions in a ‘common garden’. Individuals were held individually (0.61 m × 0.61 m × 0.61 m cages) in a climate controlled indoor aviary with 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> access to food and water. Individuals were neither visually nor acoustically isolated, and light regimes were changed bi-weekly to match photoperiod at their home latitude. All methods were reviewed and approved by the IACUC at Indiana University (protocol #09-037). To reduce the probability of capturing siblings and pseudoreplication, individuals were captured from multiple locations, and one individual from each identified sibship (one in each population) was randomly included in all analyses, as in previous studies 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
  </span>. Additional studies of these captive common garden populations are reported elsewhere ( 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">48</a>
  </span>; Atwell 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> in review).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Briefly, spring nocturnal restlessness behavior was scored from 3 March to 1 August 2010 by recording intervals of night-time perch-hopping activity of birds housed indoors in individual cages equipped with microswitched perches. This method is considered effective to capture 95% of migratory behavior observed in infrared video and ultrasound methods 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">49</a>
  </span>, and even non-traditional songbird migrations tend to occur at night 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">50</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">51</a>
  </span>. Juncos typically migrate at night 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>
  </span>, and this sampling period overlapped with the typical spring migration as well as breeding seasons of dark-eyed juncos 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
  </span>. As was found in prior studies of migratory restlessness in the junco (e.g., Ketterson and Nolan 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">52</a>
  </span>) and other species, migratory restlessness extended into the typical breeding period, perhaps due to caged birds’ inability to perform reproductive activities 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">53</a>
  </span>. Nocturnal hops were recorded starting 30 minutes after dusk until 30 minutes before dawn under a daylight regime that simulated the photoperiod at their native latitude. GraphPad Prism 3.0 (GraphPad, USA) was used to quantify the seasonal intensity of individual spring migratory restlessness by calculating the area under each fitted seasonal profile curve, which provided a total migratory propensity score for each bird (n = 36 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">14</a>
  </span>; Atwell 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> in review).
 </p>
</sec>
