<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to assess the relationship between allele length and migratory behavior among populations for both loci, we performed Spearman's correlations between population mean allele length and population migratory status. Qualitatively similar results are obtained with major allele count methods that have been applied in previous studies 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
  </span> and when only dark-eyed subspecies were considered (data not shown). Within the sub-species groups for which we sampled multiple populations (Oregon juncos and slate-colored juncos, see 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a>), we additionally performed a nested ANOVA on allele lengths with population as a grouping factor within each subspecies to determine whether mean allele length differed significantly between populations or these subspecies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To relate individual variation in allele length of 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> to migratory restlessness, we fit linear models with migratory restlessness as the dependent variable and all combinations of population, mean allele length of the individual, sex, and each pairwise interaction as predictors. The resulting models were compared against each other using Akaike's Information Criterion. When the best fit model yielded a significant interaction term, we followed with a separate linear model for each population 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">56</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in R version 2.15.2 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">57</a>
  </span>. Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and heterozygosity were calculated with the package 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/genetics/index.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">genetics</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">58</a>
  </span>. All reported p-values are two-tailed, and hence conservative with respect to 
  <span class="italic">a priori</span> directional hypotheses.
 </p>
</sec>
