<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have related migratory behavior in birds and fish to allelic variation in 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>. This study examined whether variation in these genes also relates to migratory behavior in the avian genus 
  <span class="italic">Junco</span>. At the level of populations, we found that longer 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> alleles were associated with longer migratory distance within two sub-specific groups, 
  <span class="italic">J. h. oreganus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">J. h. hyemalis</span>. 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> was not, however, significantly associated with migratory distance across the genus as a whole or with individual intensity of migratory restlessness. In the case of 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, longer alleles were not associated with migratory distance among populations within subspecies groups or across the genus. However, longer alleles were associated with higher levels of individual migratory restlessness in one of two populations studied. Together these findings suggest that allelic variation in both 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> may contribute to differences in migratory behavior at some levels of analysis (within-subspecies or within-populations) but not reliably across the genus.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of consistent relationships between molecular genetic variation and migratory variation suggested by our data are overall consistent with previous research on both 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, as these genes are related to migratory and breeding behavior in only some of the species investigated. Within birds, 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> is associated with migratory and breeding behavior in blue tits 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">19</a>
  </span>, but not black caps, bluethroats, great tits, or swallows 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">25</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">59</a>
  </span>. Similarly, a relationship between 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and migratory behavior has been found only in blackcaps 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
  </span>, but has yet to be reported in other species. Despite these conflicting results, allelic variation in each of these genes is potentially consistent with a direct relationship with migratory behavior (see below), suggesting that these genes may indeed be important to the evolution of migratory and breeding behavior.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are at least three reasons why the associations reported here might differ according to which populations or species were investigated: 1) variation in other, related genes (i.e., genetic background); 2) variation in the degree of linkage between the allelic variation we measured and functional genetic differences; or 3) variation in the environment under which the association was sought. These explanations have been suggested for other genes with variable patterns of association with phenotype (e.g., Korsten 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">32</a>
  </span>). We consider how each of these three explanations for variation in relationship applies to migratory behavior and 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, and we suggest that population differences in genetic background are the most likely explanation. If this is indeed the case, then future studies of candidate genes will benefit from expanding the number of target genes examined to include related genes that may contribute to differences in genetic background.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanisms relating allelic variation to migratory phenotype</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> alleles differ by multiples of three base pairs ( 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">Table 4</a>), consistent with previous results in other avian species (e.g., Johnsen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>
   </span>, Steinmeyer 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span>) and with the location of the repeat within the coding region of 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span>. It has previously been suggested that presence in the coding region might make these polymorphisms functional 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>
   </span>, particularly because the repeat is responsible for a polyglutamine tract expansion in a region known to control the rate at which the 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> protein activates the downstream circadian pathway 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-60">60</a>
   </span>. Polyglutamine expansions control the activity of many genes (e.g., Chamberlain 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-61" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-61">61</a>
   </span>). Thus, variation in allele length could play a direct role in modifying migratory behavior by altering the threshold day length signal to activate or suspend migratory behavior, or by modifying its downstream effects.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> alleles varied primarily by 2 base pairs ( 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">Table 3</a>), consistent with previous results and the fact that this microsatellite polymorphism falls within the 3´ untranslated region (UTR) of the 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> gene 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span>. The mechanism by which this variation may relate to behavioral differences remains unknown. Di-nucleotide repeats in the regulatory regions of genes, such as 3´ UTR, can modify the expression of a gene 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-62">62</a>
   </span>. This polymorphism may simply be linked with another causative mutation in the coding region 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>
   </span>. The amino acid code of 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, however, is 97% conserved from humans to chickens 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">28</a>
   </span>, making 3´ UTR based variation in expression far more likely than a polymorphic variation in protein sequence. Studies of 
   <span class="italic">in vivo</span> expression of various alleles in multiple tissues would be necessary to confirm a role for this mutation in modifying the expression of 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> in living animals.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Role of variation in genetic background</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migratory behavior is a complex phenotype consisting of changes to movement, orientation, feeding, fattening, and sleep patterns 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">53</a>
   </span>, and therefore may be modulated by many genes. The fact that 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> are related to migration in several systems suggests that they may be some of the key regulators. However, the large component of migratory behavior that is not explained by these genes may be related to other genes in related pathways. Changes in these other, related genes may thus reduce or modify the effect of 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> on migratory behavior, and explain the pattern of relationships identified in both previous studies 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">24</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">25</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">59</a>
   </span> (described above) and this work. Similar patterns have been found for other complex traits such as response to stress, including in experimental evolution of yeast 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-63">63</a>
   </span>. Despite similar repeated phenotypes, independently evolved lineages did not duplicate the same transcriptional (and therefore genetic) responses to a novel stressor 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-63">63</a>
   </span>. This suggests that divergent 
   <span class="italic">Junco</span> populations may have utilized unique genetic mechanisms to achieve the same phenotypic end, thus masking the role of any single candidate gene across the genus.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in genetic background may explain the lack of genus-wide patterns of relationship between migratory phenotype and 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and the pattern of relationship found in previous studies. If other, as yet unidentified, genes also contribute to divergence in migratory and breeding behavior, then the relationships identified between phenotype and genotype would be limited to the groups or species in which 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> are responsible for the divergence. In contrast, those species and populations that do not demonstrate a relationship between migratory phenotype and 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> may have diverged due to changes in other genes. These genes might be involved in the circadian pathway, such as 
   <span class="italic">BMAL1</span> or 
   <span class="italic">Period 2</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-64">64</a>
   </span>; the sensing of photoperiod changes, such as thyroid hormone deiodinases 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">65</a>
   </span> or vertebrate ancient opsin 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-66">66</a>
   </span>; or transcriptional regulation of these systems 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-67">67</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in genetic background may also explain the details of the relationships found between migratory phenotype and 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>. The Oregon and slate-colored subspecies groups both demonstrate a positive relationship between 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> allele length and migratory behavior. Importantly, the population mean 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> allele lengths are not different between the subspecies groups, and all of the slate-colored juncos migrate longer distances than the Oregon juncos. Similarly, allele length of 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> predicts migratory restlessness in the altitudinal migrant Laguna Mountain population, but not in the sedentary San Diego population despite the fact that both populations exhibit variation at the locus and in migratory restlessness. While sedentary populations are known to exhibit seasonal migratory restlessness 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-68">68</a>
   </span>, it is possible that changes in other genes inhibit migration in this sedentary population sufficiently to overwhelm the variation in restlessness contributed by 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>. Together, these results suggest that variation in other genes across the genus account for some of the shifts in migratory phenotype, but that 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> may still play important roles in further modification of migratory behavior.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of linkage</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An alternative explanation for the finding that allele length of both 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> were related to migratory behavior at only some levels (within subspecies or population) of analysis is that the alleles we assessed are not functional, but are instead genetically linked to functional differences. If so, this linkage may be distorted in some populations due to recombination or mutation. For those populations, the alleles we measured would no longer be informative as indicators of migratory behavior. The presence of the relationship in multiple independently derived lineages could be explained by independent events that link the allele at the causal locus to the same microsatellite alleles. For example, in great tits ( 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), only one of four populations studied, demonstrated a relationship between a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in dopamine receptor 4 ( 
   <span class="italic">DRD4</span>) and exploratory behavior 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">32</a>
   </span>, perhaps due to the breaking of a genetic linkage 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">69</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, however, several pieces of evidence point against disrupted linkage as the source of variation in the genotype-phenotype relationship. Similarly to previous studies that found a significant relationship between 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and migratory behavior (described above), the alleles associated with increased migratory behavior in this study were always longer. If linkage were responsible for the association, there is no reason to predict that longer alleles would repeatedly be linked to increased migratory propensity. This does not, by itself, rule out linkage–it is possible that this directional pattern is coincidental and will be reversed in another species yet to be studied. In addition, unlike the length polymorphisms studied in 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span>, the SNP in 
   <span class="italic">DRD4</span> related to exploratory behavior is a synonymous mutation 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">69</a>
   </span>–that is, it causes no change in the protein that is encoded by the gene. Similarly, the variation in 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> is predicted to affect expression 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
   </span>, while the SNP in 
   <span class="italic">DRD4</span> is unlikely to do so (but see Duan 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">70</a>
   </span>). Given the existence of a known mechanism that could relate allelic variation in 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> to functional consequences (detailed above), disrupted linkage seems less likely to account for variable strength of association than other possible causes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of environmental factors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A final potential explanation for the lack of a consistent relationship between allelic variation and migratory phenotype is that the roles of 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> are modulated by the different environments that populations and subspecies experience. In three-spine sticklebacks ( 
   <span class="italic">Gasterosteus aculeatus</span>), for example, environmental variability in the presence of predators masks genetic variation related to several behavioral traits 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-71">71</a>
   </span>. Similarly, many environmental cues, such as temperature and precipitation, modulate migratory behavior 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">9</a>
   </span>; such environmental modulators may account for some of the differences between junco populations and may mask the effects of variation in 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental differences do not, however, appear to be consistent with the pattern of relationships found between migratory phenotype and 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>. First, the positive relationship between individual variation in migratory restlessness and length of 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> was found in only one of two tested populations (Laguna Mountain), despite the fact that they were tested in an identical common garden experiment 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">48</a>
   </span>, and winter in the same environment 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
   </span>. Second, the within subspecies pattern seen between 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> allele length and migratory distance is seen in both Oregon and slate-colored juncos, and these two subspecies differ in the amount of environmental divergence between populations. The sampled Oregon populations breed in divergent climates and winter in similar environments, while the slate-colored populations all breed in a similar environments, but migrate different distances to divergent wintering grounds 
   <span class="sup">
    <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
    <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
   </span>. Together, the findings in 
   <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
   <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> suggest that environmental differences between populations, while potentially important, are not sufficient to explain the pattern of associations that we found.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
