<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual variation in migratory restlessness</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested for an association between mean 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> allele length and level of migratory restlessness within the two captive populations of Oregon juncos ( 
  <span class="italic">J. h. thurberi</span>, Laguna Mountain and UC-San Diego). The most informative linear model described individual migratory restlessness in relation to population, mean 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> allele length, and the population by allele length interaction (with Laguna Mountain as reference: effect of allele length = 712.9, p = 0.029; effect of population = 117,459.8, p = 0.056; population*allele length effect = -732.3, p = 0.053; model R 
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.225, p = 0.036). This interaction model performed better than all other tested models (Akaike's Information Criterion = 669.3; all other models AIC &gt; 670.8; see Methods for list of models). Because the interaction term indicates a different effect of allele length on migratory behavior in each population, we ran separate linear models for each population 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">56</a>
  </span> which confirmed that longer individual mean 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> allele length marginally predicted greater migratory restlessness in the migratory Laguna Mountain population (effect of allele length = 712.9, R 
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.169, p = 0.090; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Figure 5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ST1" href="#ST1">Supplementary Table 1</a>), but not in the sedentary UC-San Diego population (effect of allele length = -19.36, R 
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.001, p = 0.844; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Figure 5</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="figure" id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5. </span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">
    <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and individual variation.
   </div>
   <p>Plot shows mean allele length of 
    <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> against individual migratory restlessness score for Oregon juncos from the migratory population at Laguna Mountain, CA, USA (solid circles, solid line) and the sedentary population in San Diego, CA, USA (open circles, dashed line). Mean allele length marginally predicts migratory behavior in the Laguna Mountain, but not San Diego, populations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="f1000research-2-1357-g0004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was no relationship between mean 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> allele length and individual migratory restlessness behavior ( 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6" href="#f6">Figure 6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ST1" href="#ST1">Supplementary Table 1</a>). The most informative linear model described only a population difference: the Laguna Mountain population displayed more restlessness than the population from UC-San Diego (with Laguna Mountain as reference: effect of population = -1299.4, p = 0.054; R 
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.102). For a more thorough treatment of this population difference, see Atwell 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (in review). This population-only model performed better than all other tested models (Akaike's Information Criterion = 670.8; AIC for all other models &gt; 671.32).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="figure" id="f6" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6. </span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">
    <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and individual variation.
   </div>
   <p>Plot shows individual migratory restlessness score for Oregon juncos against the mean length of the 
    <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> alleles from the migratory population at Laguna Mountain, CA, USA (solid circles) and the sedentary population in San Diego, CA, USA (open circles). Points are slightly jittered for each population to improve visualization. There is no significant relationship between 
    <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> length and migratory restlessness.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="f1000research-2-1357-g0005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
