<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of environmental factors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A final potential explanation for the lack of a consistent relationship between allelic variation and migratory phenotype is that the roles of 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> are modulated by the different environments that populations and subspecies experience. In three-spine sticklebacks ( 
  <span class="italic">Gasterosteus aculeatus</span>), for example, environmental variability in the presence of predators masks genetic variation related to several behavioral traits 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-71">71</a>
  </span>. Similarly, many environmental cues, such as temperature and precipitation, modulate migratory behavior 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">9</a>
  </span>; such environmental modulators may account for some of the differences between junco populations and may mask the effects of variation in 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental differences do not, however, appear to be consistent with the pattern of relationships found between migratory phenotype and 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>. First, the positive relationship between individual variation in migratory restlessness and length of 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> was found in only one of two tested populations (Laguna Mountain), despite the fact that they were tested in an identical common garden experiment 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">48</a>
  </span>, and winter in the same environment 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
  </span>. Second, the within subspecies pattern seen between 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> allele length and migratory distance is seen in both Oregon and slate-colored juncos, and these two subspecies differ in the amount of environmental divergence between populations. The sampled Oregon populations breed in divergent climates and winter in similar environments, while the slate-colored populations all breed in a similar environments, but migrate different distances to divergent wintering grounds 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">34</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">41</a>
  </span>. Together, the findings in 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> suggest that environmental differences between populations, while potentially important, are not sufficient to explain the pattern of associations that we found.
 </p>
</sec>
