<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of linkage</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An alternative explanation for the finding that allele length of both 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> were related to migratory behavior at only some levels (within subspecies or population) of analysis is that the alleles we assessed are not functional, but are instead genetically linked to functional differences. If so, this linkage may be distorted in some populations due to recombination or mutation. For those populations, the alleles we measured would no longer be informative as indicators of migratory behavior. The presence of the relationship in multiple independently derived lineages could be explained by independent events that link the allele at the causal locus to the same microsatellite alleles. For example, in great tits ( 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), only one of four populations studied, demonstrated a relationship between a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in dopamine receptor 4 ( 
  <span class="italic">DRD4</span>) and exploratory behavior 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">32</a>
  </span>, perhaps due to the breaking of a genetic linkage 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">69</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span>, however, several pieces of evidence point against disrupted linkage as the source of variation in the genotype-phenotype relationship. Similarly to previous studies that found a significant relationship between 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> or 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> and migratory behavior (described above), the alleles associated with increased migratory behavior in this study were always longer. If linkage were responsible for the association, there is no reason to predict that longer alleles would repeatedly be linked to increased migratory propensity. This does not, by itself, rule out linkage–it is possible that this directional pattern is coincidental and will be reversed in another species yet to be studied. In addition, unlike the length polymorphisms studied in 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span>, the SNP in 
  <span class="italic">DRD4</span> related to exploratory behavior is a synonymous mutation 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">69</a>
  </span>–that is, it causes no change in the protein that is encoded by the gene. Similarly, the variation in 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> is predicted to affect expression 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-43">43</a>
  </span>, while the SNP in 
  <span class="italic">DRD4</span> is unlikely to do so (but see Duan 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">70</a>
  </span>). Given the existence of a known mechanism that could relate allelic variation in 
  <span class="italic">CLOCK</span> and 
  <span class="italic">ADCYAP1</span> to functional consequences (detailed above), disrupted linkage seems less likely to account for variable strength of association than other possible causes.
 </p>
</sec>
