<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A vulnerability assessment can be a useful tool for providing information about where we are with regard to the development of the adaptive capacity of a city and the adaptation activities of the population with respect to climate change (
 <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Amaru &amp; Chhetri, 2013</xref>). The United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) notes that “adaptation emerged as a focus area under the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) in 2001. However, the attention given to it is still not equal to mitigation with regard to target-setting, financing, and institutional frameworks”. By establishing an explicit long-term adaptation goal in Article 7, the Paris Agreement (
 <xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">UNFCCC, 2015</xref>) builds on an international consensus on the need of vulnerability reduction and confirms that adaptation to climate change is a key pillar of UNFCCC. Magnan and Ribera observe as a challenge that climate change adaptation achieves ”equal prioritization with mitigation (given) the relative fuzziness of adaptation as a policy area” (
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Magnan &amp; Ribera, 2016</xref>). Ford adds that “mitigation policy constitutes a response to a clear problem (GHG emissions) and can be measured and tracked using standardized and accepted indicators (e.g., tons of carbon). In contrast, adaptation is difficult to define and track, especially in relation to policy issues like development or disaster risk management” (
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ford &amp; Berrang-Ford, 2016</xref>). Adaptation is place- and context-specific, with no single approach for reducing risks appropriate across all settings (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2014</xref>). Vulnerability to climate change can be an accepted indicator for measuring and tracking the success of the adaptation process.
</p>
