<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There are two methods for aggregating single indicators into indices in the literature. One is weighting single indicators, and the other is non-weighting single indicators. Weighting means that all single indicators will have different contributions to the integrated index, while non-weighting means that all single indicators have the same contributions to the integrated index. Weights are the measures of importance. There are three arguments for weighting indicators. (a) It is priority-based, and tends to be more realistic than non-weighted indicators. By weighting, priority issues can be addressed and emphasized, and reasonable judgments and decisions can be made. This is very important for the efficient distribution of available resources, and identifying key issues that all stakeholders are concerned about and agree upon. (b) It avoids loss of information during the indicators’ aggregation as much as possible. It is obvious that key indicators will have more weights than others, and aggregated index will have close linkages to the key indicators. The most relevant information will be used in the final index. (c) It is participation-based. The weighting process requires public participation for making judgments. Experts, stakeholders as well as citizens may be involved in the weighting process, and their opinions will have significant influence on the weights of indicators. Since there is no precise mathematical relationship between indicators that ultimately indicate or measure vulnerability, there are limitations in weighting geophysical and socio-economic indicators in measuring vulnerability (
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">El-Zein &amp; Tonmoy, 2015</xref>). Weighting indicators make more sense at local level. However, the complexity of issues and the lack of scientific weighting methodologies have been obstructing the application of weighting indicators (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tonmoy, El-Zein &amp; Hinkel, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Economic Forum, 2001</xref>). Environmental indicators can be aggregated by weighting according to their contribution to the environmental issues, which can be determined by scientific research. However, it is very difficult to integrate economic and social indicators by weighting. This is why weighting indicators have not yet been commonly used in the aggregation of social and economic indicators. In our research, the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) has been applied, together with expert judgment for integrating weighted indicators into the index of vulnerability. We find that this method is useful for cities like Beijing, where there is a lack of data, where the situation may differ in different locations and where it is impossible to use a large numbers of indicators for measuring vulnerability to climate change.
</p>
