<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par64" class="p">For 40–60°S for the period 2001–2007, we applied the energy divergence method to estimate net flux using different re-analyses, which employ different models, assimilation systems and assimilated observational data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. Area-averaged net flux differences relative to our reference estimate (derived from ERA-Interim
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>) are 3.1, 3.4, 1.4 and 2.1 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> for the ERA20C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>, JRA55C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>, JRA55
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup> and MERRA
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup> reanalysis, respectively. This suggests 40–60°S area-mean uncertainties for our net flux observational estimate are ~±3 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>, which we assume is indicative of its standard error. Note, however, that this estimate does not include structural errors common to all of the re-analyses. Differencing area means for CERES-EBAF and ISCCP suggests observational uncertainties (indicative of standard errors) are approximately ±1, 6 and 6 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> for net downward surface short-wave, long-wave and total radiative flux, respectively. Note that CERES-EBAF and ISCCP are the only two available gridded global estimates of surface radiative flux components derived from observationally constrained atmospheric column radiative transfer methods. Assuming that the observational errors in the net flux and total radiative terms are independent, and can therefore be added in quadrature, the uncertainty in turbulent flux will be ~7 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>.
</p>
