<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While it is seldom possible to determine the exact origin of non-native species, the non-native species included in our study clearly originated from lower elevation, higher latitude sites where UV-B exposure would be considerably less than our sampling locations. The majority of species (8 of 11) are listed in floras as originating from Europe or Eurasia. More detailed distributions of several species indicate they typically originate north of 30° latitude (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Weber, 2017</xref>). The remaining species also originate outside the low-latitude tropics: 
 <italic class="italic">Heterotheca grandiflora</italic> from coastal California (
 <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Munz, 1968</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">O. stricta</italic> from southern South America (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Robberecht and Caldwell, 1983</xref>), and 
 <italic class="italic">S. madagascariensis</italic> from South Africa (as determined by phylogenetic analysis; 
 <xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Le Roux et al., 2006</xref>). Whereas, it is possible that these species were pre-adapted to the extreme UV-B conditions in the tropical alpine, it seems more likely that they either (1) evolved higher UV screening over the course of their invasion and colonization of montane environments in Hawaii, or (2) that they possess high degrees of phenotypic plasticity in UV tolerance that then enabled them to acclimate to a wide range of UV-B conditions. Some of the non-native species in our study have arrived in Hawaii relatively recently and are highly invasive pests (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">S. madagascariensis</italic>) whereas others have been on the island sufficiently long enough to be considered “naturalized” (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">P. pratensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rumex acetosella</italic>) (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wagner et al., 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">USDA, 2017</xref>). Thus, the non-native species in our study have experienced various periods of time since their introductions and these historical differences may have influenced the degree to which their adjustments in UV protection reflect genetic changes in populations vs. phenotypic plasticity.
</p>
