<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Elevation gradients, such as the one in our study, are complex gradients where a number of environmental factors (e.g., solar radiation, temperature, precipitation) change in concert (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Körner, 2007</xref>). Studies such as ours linking elevation changes in UV screening to changes in UV-B are therefore, correlative at best, and other environmental factors may contribute to this variation. Indeed, it is well known that low temperatures can increase UV-absorbing compounds and UV screening in leaves (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bilger et al., 2007</xref>) and some have found elevation changes in flavonoids to be more strongly influenced by changes in temperature than UV (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Albert et al., 2009</xref>). Nonetheless, studies along elevation gradients can provide insights into how plants might respond to the changes in UV-B that occurs with migration to higher elevations as a consequence of climate change. In our study, we found a strong negative relationship between clear sky erythemal UV-B and T
 <sub class="sub">UV A</sub> in 
 <italic class="italic">V. thapsus</italic>, but we also detected strong relationships with PAR and total SW radiation. In general, radiant fluxes of biologically effective UV-B increase proportionally more with elevation than those of UV-A, PAR or SW in temperate and tropical mountains (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Caldwell et al., 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Piazena, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Blumthaler et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McKenzie et al., 2001</xref>). Such appears to be the case for this elevation gradient in Hawaii (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nullet and Juvik, 1997</xref>). Thus, while migration to higher elevations exposes plants to increases in solar radiation in all wavebands, the relative changes are greatest for biologically effective UV-B. These elevation gradients in UV-B can be further accentuated by the presence of clouds. For example, because of a persistent, dense cloud layer at ca. 2000 masl that results from trade-wind inversions, the differences in UV-B between the alpine and sea level differ considerably from the eastern, wind-ward side of Mauna Kea to the western, lee-ward side of the mountain. From continuous UV measurements, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nullet and Juvik (1997)</xref> reported that monthly erythemal UV-B, when averaged over all sky conditions, was actually 55–103% greater at 3400 masl than at a windward sea level location, depending on time of year (summer vs. winter), in comparison to the ca. 20% difference in clear sky UV-B between these elevations. Plant species that occur below the cloud layer on the moist, eastern side of Mauna Kea, and which migrate to elevations above this cloud layer would therefore likely require greater acclimation to UV-B than would those migrating comparable elevations on the drier, eastern side of this mountain.
</p>
