<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-ijerph-15-02370" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Climate-Related Shocks and Stresses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health systems regularly prepare for shocks and stresses (a shock is a single unpredictable event and a stress is an ongoing hardship) not related to climate change, such as pandemics, chronic human resource challenges, demographic changes (e.g., population aging), financial crises, and others. Preparation for stresses tends to be distinct from preparation for shocks, because stresses tend not to compromise function to the point that health systems functionality declines, although, over time, the accumulated effects of stresses can make health systems more vulnerable to shocks. Tipping points have been identified at which health systems begin to exhibit declining performance under standard conditions, highlighting thresholds beyond which operational stresses undermine essential functions [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-15-02370">25</a>]. By contrast, shocks necessitate a short-term reorientation of health systems to optimize population health outcomes, rather than their usual focus (in care delivery settings) on optimizing outcomes for individual patients [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-15-02370">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shocks and stresses differ in the burdens they impose relative to a system’s resilience and integrity, with shocks generally more intense and short-lived. Examples of shocks include environmental, climatic, or other types of events, such as floods, high winds, landslides, heatwaves or droughts, that can impact health, damage critical public health infrastructure, and impede health system functioning. By contrast, stresses can be beneficial to health systems through hormesis, which primes a system to respond effectively to stress, or be damaging, depending on the net effects. Stresses are characterized by continuous and compounding changes in environmental, climatic, or other types of factors (e.g., increasing desertification, multi-year declines in agricultural production, or chronic economic decline). Shocks and stresses affect population health and health systems through myriad pathways, including direct losses of lives, livelihoods, and infrastructure, and diverting funds from investments in social and economic development to, for example, emergency relief and reconstruction.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impacts of a shock or stress depend on the magnitude of the hazard, as well as the extent of exposure of human and natural systems to the hazard, the susceptibility of those systems to harm, and their ability to cope with and recover from exposure [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-15-02370">27</a>,
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-15-02370">28</a>]. The record 2017 wildfire season in British Columbia resulted in the temporary closure of 19 health facilities or sites, 880 patients evacuated from facilities, over 700 health services staff displaced and $2.7 million in costs to Interior Health Services for the response [
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-15-02370">29</a>]. Shocks and stresses can also result in synergistic impacts that reverberate throughout health and other key socioeconomic systems [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-15-02370">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-15-02370">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-15-02370">32</a>,
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-15-02370">33</a>,
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-15-02370">34</a>]. For example, persistent drought and food insecurity in Syria, coupled with social-political and religious tensions, resulted in civil conflict, mass displacement, and a public health crisis [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-15-02370">35</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A further challenge is that many health systems operate with little to no surge capacity, which is problematic in the context of growing risks from climate-related shocks and stresses, in both low- and high-resource settings. For example, following Tropical Cyclone Pam in Vanuatu in 2015, the destruction of healthcare infrastructure, combined with low numbers of healthcare personnel and difficulties mobilizing resources and funds, significantly impacted the capacity of health services to deliver curative and preventative services [
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-15-02370">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-15-02370">37</a>]. Similarly, addressing mental health after climate-related disasters can be very challenging for some health systems [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-15-02370">38</a>]. After Superstorm Sandy struck New York in 2012, the lack of access to care increased the odds of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), depression, and anxiety [
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-15-02370">39</a>]. Emergency department crowding is a chronic stress that severely limits capacity in the United States [
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-15-02370">40</a>] and many other locations globally [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-15-02370">41</a>]; events such as large wildfires, increasingly frequent with climate change, drive higher emergency department visit rates for a range of conditions [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-15-02370">42</a>] in facilities which are often inadequately prepared for the surge, with quality of care suffering as a result [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-15-02370">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In response to the limitations of V&amp;A assessments to effectively capture the potential challenges of climate-related shocks and stresses, we propose to supplement these assessments with climate change and health stress tests.</p>
</sec>
