<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-ijerph-15-02370" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conducting a Climate Change and Health Stress Test</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stress testing considers socioeconomic and political factors that can influence the extent of health system vulnerability and factors that can affect demands on the system by impacting population health. A stress test is designed to identify conditions under which it would be difficult for the health system to maintain its essential function of providing services to protect population health and manage climate-sensitive health outcomes, and to identify interventions that could maintain essential system functions despite these shocks and stresses. A stress test focuses on acute and chronic climate-related events and conditions, including those far outside the range of historic experience, that could directly impact health systems and/or climate-related events and conditions in non-health sectors that can indirectly impact health or health system function. This approach can be used to extend the analyses and information gathered during the process of conducting a V&amp;A assessment by leveraging the team, stakeholders, information, and multi-sectoral analyses that ideally accompany a V&amp;A assessment process. The stress test can focus on one or more of the building blocks of health systems, with the aim of improving system resilience, robustness, redundancy, and coordination [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-15-02370">7</a>,
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-15-02370">44</a>]. By doing so, stress testing may both inform ongoing and future V&amp;A assessments, and provide scenario-based analyses that may enhance stakeholder buy-in.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change and health stress test can focus on shocks and/or stresses. The stress test can be approached from the perspective of managing outbreaks of climate-sensitive health outcomes (e.g., Zika, malaria), events that directly affect population health and health system functioning (e.g., extreme weather and climate events such as heatwaves, flooding, storm surges), impacts on other sectors that affect health system function (e.g., cascading systems failures affecting power generation and transmission, hydrometeorological disasters affecting healthcare supply chains), or events from outside health systems that could indirectly affect population health and health system functioning (e.g., large scale migration associated with drought). The following description has a greater focus on shocks for illustrative purposes because these may be the most immediate need for health system officials, but the approach can be modified to address potential climate-related stresses that could compromise health system functioning.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The subsequent sections explain the stages of a climate change and health stress test, followed by a discussion. The activities described in the stages are similar to and draw upon guidance developed for gauging the climate resiliency of health facilities and for conducting V&amp;A assessments [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-15-02370">11</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-15-02370">19</a>]. Some activities, such as forming a stress test team, reviewing data and information, prioritizing health issues, and communicating results, can be shared between a V&amp;A assessment and a climate and health stress test. The three basic stages in a stress test are as follows: 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Stage 1: Prepare the climate change and health stress test</span>. Preparing for a climate change and health stress test includes forming the stress test team; reviewing the available data and information, as well as collecting new data and conducting necessary modeling to inform the scenarios developed; identifying priority health system functions and/or climate-sensitive health outcomes for the stress test; developing hypothetical situations (scenarios) of shocks and stresses that form the core of the stress test; and identifying stakeholders for inclusion in the exercise. Preparing the stress test can benefit from linking with a completed climate change and health V&amp;A assessment or one being conducted in parallel. Ideally, the stress test includes multiple aspects of health systems and services, including elements addressing all six building blocks of climate resilient health services [
     <a rid="B7-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-15-02370">7</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Stage 2: Conduct the stress test.</span> Various stress testing modalities could be used, alone or in conjunction. At a minimum, table-top or visioning exercises may be completed by the stress test team in a workshop setting, in which the participants discuss the scenarios and evaluate the extent to which health systems would likely be able to manage the shocks and stresses. Additional modalities could be employed, including agent-based and systems dynamics modeling to explore impacts in silico. Regardless of the approach(es) used, the team should review the findings to identify additional resources, tools, and policies that, if made available, could prevent adverse population health consequences associated with the hypothetical situations. Recommended changes in policies and measures should be prioritized to increase the capacity of communities and health systems to prepare for and manage the climate-related shocks and stresses considered.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Stage 3: Communicate the results to key stakeholders.</span> A summary report and other outreach materials should communicate the results to key stakeholders. This report should include an overview of climate and health risks and recommendations for actions, considering factors such as the likelihood and timing of the shocks and stresses, competing demands, windows of opportunity to build resilience based on current and planned projects, and stakeholder concerns and preferences.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
