<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5dot1-ijerph-15-02370" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. Stage 1: Prepare the Study</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Decide the key issues on which to focus</span>: To begin, the ministry of health, health department, or other health administrative unit engaged with the stress test should decide which aspects of health systems and services to include, such as focusing on the preparedness of facilities and infrastructure, acute care and emergency department capacity, pharmacies, first responders, public health services, and non-governmental organizations, such as the Red Cross/Red Crescent society. These choices will inform decisions about which individuals should comprise the stress test team.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Form the stress test team</span>: Ideally, the climate change and health stress test team should include specialists (e.g., public health officials, doctors, nurses) knowledgeable about the health risks of climate change, projections of climate change for the geographic region of interest, health system policies and programs of relevance for climate change and health, policies, and programs in other sectors that could impact population health, local and national plans (e.g., those affecting urbanization), and the local demographics of particularly vulnerable groups. Team members could come from the ministry or department of health, healthcare delivery organizations, universities, non-governmental organizations, and others. As local context is critical, inclusion of participants with intimate knowledge of local health system disaster planning and, crucially, actual disaster experience, is key. Including someone from the local meteorological service would be very helpful to provide insights on the local or regional risks associated with specific types of extreme weather events. Every situation is different, therefore, the team should utilize the specifics of a given context, as well as aim to integrate with existing coordination mechanisms where possible. For example, many countries have a climate change and health technical working group that could be engaged in the process. The team should include the breadth and depth of expertise needed, without becoming too large to be effective. Jurisdictions with specific climate hazards of concern to health systems, for example, mental health impacts in rural, isolated, or northern communities, may require participation of specialists, such as psychologists or social support workers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determining the stress test timeframe is key, as the type, magnitude, and frequency of climate-related hazards, as well as the population structure, and issues such as land-use and insurance coverage will vary considerably, depending on the time horizon. Other stipulations, such as the extent of the disaster (which would affect the availability of aid) and impacts on other sectors (e.g., power generation, transport, etc.) should also be determined.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Conduct a stocktake and review/generate data and information</span>: In this step, the team gathers data and information to inform the stress test. Stocktaking identifies relevant data, studies, reports, or plans developed by the ministry of health and other organizations. Publications, documents, and reports should be sought that provide details on recent climate-related shocks and stresses, and the effectiveness of health systems in preparing for, and managing, associated morbidity and mortality. For example, in the Vancouver Coastal Health jurisdiction of British Columbia, Canada, a scoping report provided information on climate projections for the region, possible risks that threaten facilities, and recommendations for taking adaptation actions in order to inform efforts to prepare facilities for the impacts of climate change [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-15-02370">45</a>]. The stocktake and review should leverage efforts already undertaken, particularly results from health V&amp;A assessments and adaptation planning documents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples of relevant information include (1) trends in temperature, precipitation, and extreme events over recent decades; (2) national or subnational research on the health risks of climate change; (3) national or subnational research on sectors that affect population health, such as the possible impacts of climate change on water and food safety and security; (4) information about the health system (e.g., number and types of specific health workers, number of hospitals and services offered at each, frequency of stockouts, description of supply-chains, baseline health metrics, etc.); (5) information on the spatial distribution of vulnerable groups, particularly those that are likely to need additional assistance or ad hoc services in a disaster, such as those with electricity-dependent life-sustaining devices at home, those on hemodialysis, those on opioid replacement therapy, and pregnant women, among others; (6) information on health- and other insurance coverage, and on the capitalization of the health system, as well as standing plans for rescue support including, but not limited to, mutual aid agreements, emergency, and other sources of funding, and other needed support for disaster recovery; and (7) recent national and subnational climate change and health V&amp;A assessments. Additionally, it may be advantageous to collect other information on physical infrastructure (structure and vulnerabilities of the electricity grid, road networks, etc.) that may be vulnerable during extreme weather events and which affect health systems. 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-15-02370" href="#app1-ijerph-15-02370">Appendix A</a> suggests guiding questions to identify where impacts may occur today or in the future. Additional questions will arise based on specifics of the local context.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Depending on the hypothetical situations (scenarios) of interest, it could be helpful to collect additional data and/or conduct modeling to generate further details for the stress test. For example, if the interest is in extreme events, then it could be informative to model possible increases in the intensity of events in the tail of the distribution in mid-century. The modeling could also consider where and when urbanization could increase, population aging, and other factors that could affect vulnerability to the event.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although access to data and other resources will improve the stress test, in low-resource situations, it is possible to utilize realistic scenarios (e.g., based on events experienced in similar jurisdictions) in place of those tailored specifically to the jurisdiction in question. In this sense, stress testing both increases the accessibility of climate resilience analysis and may result in the buy-in necessary for senior decision-makers to allocate resources needed for a broader V&amp;A assessment or other forms of analysis.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Identify priority health system functions to be considered in the stress test</span>: The stress test team will identify a preliminary list of critical health system functions to consider in the stress test, including measures of effective function, such as minimum number of healthcare professionals, access to essential medical products (including supply chain needs), and financing needed. Health system functions of potential interest include how to manage changes in the magnitude and pattern of climate-sensitive health outcomes over the coming decades with additional climate change, such as increases in the frequency, intensity, and duration of extreme weather and climate events, and the spread of infectious diseases [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-15-02370">3</a>]. Informal interviews with ministry of health staff, researchers, and other experts may identify other parameters of potential interest. General metrics of health system competency (e.g., daily all-cause mortality rates, in-hospital mortality rates, and cause-specific morbidity and mortality rates for vulnerable populations) are also important to consider because they provide generalizable indicators that are not specific to particular hazards, and because they capture health effects on populations that are not as directly affected. The stocktake will help with the other steps; for example, information from recent national and local assessments will be useful in identifying priority health system functions for the stress test, considered from the perspective of potential changes in the components of risk: hazards, exposure, and vulnerability. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Develop desk-based hypothetical situations (scenarios) of shocks and stresses</span>: The climate and health stress test team should develop several possible hypothetical scenarios for consideration in the workshop. These can range from relatively simple (e.g., heatwave outside historic experience during which the power grid fails) to more complex scenarios, including, for example, interacting and cascading events (e.g., heatwave coupled with wildfires that significantly affect air quality and also affect agricultural productivity) and/or events that affect supply chains (e.g., flooding that limits the ability to bring in needed supplies of medicines, food, and water, or the ability of affected individuals to reach healthcare). The scenarios could be informed by events that occurred in the past or in other regions. Basing the premise of the scenario in past real-world events, particularly those that took place in similar countries and regions, may help increase engagement from local decision-makers. Scenarios should be tailored to the region of interest, accounting for local factors that could affect the magnitude and pattern of the hazard or response. However, they should also describe threats that are beyond historic experience to account for possible future climate change impacts. The scenarios should test the capacity of health systems to manage shocks and stresses projected with climate change in the coming decades, with lower probabilities but more severe consequences. Real-world events experienced in similar geographic settings and plausible, yet currently infrequent, events, may be used in cases where high-quality data and modelling capacity are low. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the selection of the aspects of health systems and services of interest in the stress test, the scenarios should incorporate relevant information on the status and location of critical infrastructure (e.g., the probability that the power grid could fail during a heatwave, putting additional people at risk) and other factors that will affect the ability of the health system to manage the situation (e.g., a disease outbreak that significantly increases emergency department visits, increases hospital admission rates, decreases discharge rates, or stresses critical care capacity). A short description of each should be developed for discussion during the climate change and health stress test workshop (stage 2).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Map stakeholders for inclusion in the stress test workshop</span>: Strong partnerships, social networks, and inclusiveness are key characteristics of resilience and are important facilitators of effective ad hoc disaster response in the health sector [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-15-02370">46</a>]. A climate change and health stress test is an opportunity to identify and strengthen connections among stakeholders. To be effective, the workshop should engage a broad range of stakeholders, from local to national governments and civil society. These stakeholders should include officials in charge of health system entities vulnerable to shocks and stresses, as well as individuals who have decision-making roles in developing and implementing resilience-building strategies, including for upstream drivers of population health. Other potential stakeholders include technical staff at the ministry of health; representatives of healthcare facilities and medical clinics; representatives from the mental health and long-term care sectors, pharmacists, health emergency managers, supply chain workers, public health officials, emergency responders, and others. Additionally, it is generally desirable to have representation from actors serving in national to local organizations and/or government initiatives (e.g., public utilities/service providers, planning agencies, public-private agencies providing household services, etc.); private sector officials (e.g., chambers of commerce, industry groups, etc.); NGOs and community groups; and schools, universities, and research institutes. For health authorities with many pressing priorities, it can be difficult to allocate the time and financial and human resources to undertake a stress test. Including a broad range of stakeholders based on strong social networks and partnerships can help address these challenges.
 </p>
</sec>
