<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5dot2-ijerph-15-02370" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2. Stage 2: Conduct the Climate Change and Health Stress Test</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stress test will present and discuss the scenarios, as well as any necessary background information to evaluate how well health systems and services could function during and after the scenario. If other modalities, such as modeling, are used, the findings from these efforts also should be discussed. These discussions should identify what additional resources, tools, and policies could prevent or ameliorate adverse consequences for health system functioning or population health. The discussions could also identify where collaborations could be strengthened, such as among health authorities at different levels of government and among various sectoral partners, for example, the ministry of health and electric and water utilities.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Together, the team conducting the stress test, the ministry/department of health, and other key stakeholders, should draft the agenda and presentations, as well as identify the draft list of participants. Including a relatively large number of participants in the workshop will facilitate information sharing and more diverse discussions. The ministry/department of health and other government partners can be helpful in disseminating invitations to key stakeholders. If particular key stakeholders are not able to attend, then the stress test team should meet with these individuals separately to gather their insights for the exercise.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stress test workshop length depends on the need to provide participants with detailed background and contextual information on climate change impacts on health and health systems and on the hypothetical scenarios. The goal is to assess the extent to which the assembled actors could manage real events based on the scenarios, and to identify what additional policies, capacity building, and resources would be needed to effectively handle these situations. This is an opportunity for diverse stakeholders to exchange views on risks that could constrain the health system from achieving its goals to promote and protect healthy populations. The discussions can provide insights on what additional information, resources, policies, programs etc. would be needed for the health system to be resilient to the impacts of climate change. For example, the stress test workshop may highlight opportunities for education on key issues of concern, such as the risks of heatwaves on mental wellness, or the long-term psychosocial treatment needs related to trauma from extreme weather events. 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app2-ijerph-15-02370" href="#app2-ijerph-15-02370">Appendix B</a> lists possible modules to include in stress test workshops, and 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app3-ijerph-15-02370" href="#app3-ijerph-15-02370">Appendix C</a> provides guiding questions to facilitate discussions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples of additional actions for health systems to manage shocks and stresses associated with climate change are presented in 
  <a ref-type="app" rid="app4-ijerph-15-02370" href="#app4-ijerph-15-02370">Appendix D</a>. There are several factors that participants should consider when recommending which actions to undertake, including:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Necessity—which actions are most critical;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Timing—when a particular facility, program or other health system function may be vulnerable to certain climate impacts and when particular actions should be taken in to prepare for and respond to the timing of the hazard and other preparation and response activities;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Capacity—whether current surge capacity levels and available expertise are sufficient to handle projected impacts, or whether these need to be increased;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Likely losses—expected increases in morbidity and mortality; facilities where adaptation is prohibitively expensive and should not be undertaken; areas where programs or polices will need to be reevaluated due to unavoidable impacts (e.g., health transportation and supply lines that rely on ice roads); and contingent additional losses if mutual aid is not available); and</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Costs—the economic, political, environmental, and social costs of taking actions to increase resilience, whether they are manageable and how they compare to the costs of inaction.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prioritizing actions and investments can be done through multi-criteria analyses, or risk-based prioritization. More specific examination of whether the costs of adaptation warrant investment in specific measures may use cost–benefit analyses or cost-effectiveness analyses [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-15-02370" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-15-02370">19</a>]. The approach used will often depend on the data, expertise, and timeframe available for the analysis and the needs of decision-makers. For example, cost-effectiveness analysis would require robust information on the expected effectiveness of the suite of adaptation options under consideration; this information may be limited, or not available. The recommendations can be categorized into urgent and immediate actions (e.g., capacity building, data collection, records management, social network development, etc.), medium- and longer-term actions (new program development, infrastructure modifications or re-siting, etc.), and measures to strengthen contingency planning for shocks and stresses, thereby reducing the vulnerability of the health system. The recommendations should address specific climate-sensitive health risks, and include measures to protect vulnerable communities, groups, or assets, in the context of low-carbon development.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stress test participants should attempt to collectively agree on the major findings from the climate change and health stress test, with respect to the ability of different elements of the health system to manage the hypothetical scenarios, as well as additional policies, programs, and actions that could increase their capacity to prepare for and manage the changes. Moreover, there should be discussion of who should follow-up on recommended actions and on next steps for using the results to inform policies to increase resilience to climate variability and change. Participants should also stipulate a timeframe to reassess planning efforts going forward.</p>
</sec>
