<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="app3-ijerph-15-02370" class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Appendix C. Guiding Questions for Discussions at a Climate Change and Health Stress Test Workshop</div>
 <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>What is the level of effectiveness of current control programs to manage the burden of disease? How likely could the programs adjust to manage changes in the geographic range, seasonality, and intensity of transmission of, for example, infectious diseases? Or, how quickly could delivery of health services and supply chains be established in case of an extreme weather and climate event outside of historic experience?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Are there monitoring and surveillance systems that can provide place-based and timely information? An example is collection and analysis of environmental data that could warn when flooding events are expected, along with data on socioeconomic conditions so that vulnerable regions and populations can be identified.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Are monitoring and surveillance data incorporated into strategic resource planning (financial, infrastructure, medical personnel and training), distribution chains, disaster preparedness, etc.? Does strategic planning consider climate change-related risks and their potential consequences?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Are memorandums of understanding in place with other ministries and departments to facilitate timely access to data and information?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Does experience suggest the level of social capital in the community? Are there activities underway in the community that could be extended to increase social capital?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Has there been an evaluation of climate-related risks to healthcare infrastructure, and of any challenges to maintaining services in cases of epidemics or extreme weather and climate events? If so, what were the implications of this evaluation?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Are there education and training programs that could easily incorporate the health risks of climate variability and change?</p>
  </div>
 </div>
</div>
