<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="app1-ijerph-15-02370" class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Appendix A. Guiding Questions for Stage 1</div>
 <div orientation="portrait" class="array">
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Current burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes </td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Are temperature and precipitation associated with the health outcome(s) or with the transmission cycle(s) of interest in the area of interest? How important are the associations to the current burdens of climate-sensitive health outcomes?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Is there evidence that infectious diseases have already changed their geographic range or seasonality of transmission?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Do the number of cases of health outcomes of interest increase or decrease during heatwaves, floods, droughts, and/or storm surges, or have these events affected the transmission cycle? How important is the change?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Are there trends for the hazards, suggesting how climate change could affect the burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes over the shorter term?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Which populations and regions are particularly vulnerable?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Future burden of climate-sensitive health risks </td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>How much might increasing temperatures and changing precipitation patterns affect the magnitude and pattern of future burdens of the health outcome(s) of interest? How important could this change be over the next few decades?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Could climate change alter the geographic range, seasonality, or intensity of transmission of Lyme disease, dengue, and other infectious and re-emerging diseases? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>How could changes in the patterns of extreme events (heatwaves, droughts, floods, extreme storms) affect the burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Based on projections, are health outcomes likely to become more or less sensitive to climate change over time? Could climate change facilitate the emergence of health outcomes that may need more attention? How could hotspots of health outcomes change with climate change?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental factors that could affect population health, including 
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Availability of safe water (quality and quantity)</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Food security</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Wildfires</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Coastal erosion</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Saltwater intrusion</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>To what extent do temperature, precipitation, other weather variables, and sea level rise affect access to environmental services? How important is the association?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>How could water supply and sanitation systems be affected by changes in precipitation or salinization?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>How could wildfires and coastal erosion, for example, affect access to environmental services or electricity networks?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>To what extent could changes in these environmental factors affect population vulnerability to the risks associated with climate change?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Social and economic context, including 
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Community services</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Livelihoods</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Social capital</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Economic resources</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Infrastructure</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>To what extent do temperature, precipitation, other weather variables, and sea level rise affect social and economic factors? How important is the association?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>How could climate change affect the future availability and level of community services? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>To what extent could changes in these socioeconomic factors affect population vulnerability to the other risks associated with climate change? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health systems, including factors such as 
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Ability to deliver services</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Access to healthcare facilities</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Supply chains, particularly during extreme weather and climate events</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>To what extent do temperature, precipitation, other weather variables, and sea level rise affect the ability of health systems to deliver services?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Have extreme weather and climate events affected access to healthcare systems? How important was the disruption?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Have extreme weather and climate events affected supply chains? How important was the disruption?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Are mechanisms in place to mobilize resources (financial and human) during and after extreme weather and climate events?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geography and climate</td>
    <td valign="middle" align="left" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Which regions could be affected by the climate-related hazard? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Where are the most vulnerable populations for the health outcome(s) of interest located?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Which ecosystems and other services are of importance? Over what time period?</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Are there other factors of concern?</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </div>
</div>
