<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Following the above hypothesis, the sediment loads predicted when using the Phase 1 rating curves together with measured monthly riverflows during Phases 2–4 were compared with the observed sediment loads during these Phases (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3b–d</xref> and Tables 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref> in Supplementary material). Essentially, any departure of the computed sediment loads from that observed is indicative of non-natural behavior. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3b</xref> shows that during Phase 2 (1980–1991), observed values at most stations exceeded the predicted sediment load along the main reach of the Pearl River basin, with an ultimate observed increase of 7% in fluvial sediment supply to the coast. This could be attributed to land use changes in the upper reaches due to Chinese economic reform policies which resulted in much of the area being cleared and utilized for agricultural production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>. During Phase 3 (1992–2006), however, the observed sediment load sharply decreases compared to the predicted sediment load (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3c</xref>), with the fluvial sediment supply to the coast decreasing by about 25% compared to Phase 1. The main cause for this decrease in sediment load at the middle and lower reaches of the river is the construction of the Yangtan mega dam in the upper reach (indicated by YD in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2c</xref>). During Phase 4 (2007–2013) the sediment load decreases further compared to predicted sediment load (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3d</xref>), resulting in a massive 71% decrease in fluvial sediment supply to the coast compared to Phase 1. This is attributed to the placement of Longtan mega dam (indicated by LD in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2d</xref>) upstream of the Yangtan dam, trapping approximately 99% of the sediment input from the upper tributaries of the river
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
