<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bacterial diversity by pH category</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared the observed richness and Shannon diversity index by pH range (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">5A</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">B</a>) using a Monte-Carlo test to assess differences. Alpha diversity was significantly lower in acidic samples than in acidoneutral and alkaline soils (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Table S3</a>, Supporting Information).
 </p>
 <div id="fig5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Alpha diversity differences in the total communities by pH category. 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> Richness by observed OTUs. 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> Shannon index.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fiz128fig5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of community composition, we differentiated the abundant community, composed of only 135 OTUs, from the total community composed of 48 147 OTUs and observed the changes in relative abundance by pH range. In the total community, Acidobacteria, Armatimonadetes, Planctomycetes and Verrucomicrobia decreased with increasing pH. On the other hand, Bacteroidetes, Chloroflexi and Gemmatimonadetes increased in alkaline soils; Proteobacteria remained stable throughout. In the abundant community, Acidobacteria, Bacteroidetes and Gemmatimonadetes increased with increasing pH while Actinobacteria, Planctomycetes and Verrucomicrobia remained stable (Fig.   
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig6" href="#fig6">6</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig6" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Relative abundance of the abundant and total communities by pH range classified at the phylum level.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fiz128fig6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
