<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil samples were collected across the Arctic region between April 2017 and September 2017, and the global positioning system (GPS) coordinates of each site were recorded with a portable GPS (Fig.   
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig1" href="#fig1">1</a>). All sites were generally remote with limited human presence; however, in Iceland and Norway where tourist activities are frequent, we aimed to sample at least 500 m away from human-related activities. At each location, three to five soil samples were collected within 100 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> under the most common vegetation, for a total of 200 independent Arctic samples across 43 sites, with the aim to cover the broadest geographical area possible. Despite the extent, it should be noted that large areas of Canada and Russia remain uncharacterized and under-represented, highlighting areas where sampling should be prioritized in the future. Approximately 150 g of soil per sample was collected from the top 15 cm, avoiding plant roots and rocks and using an ethanol-cleaned shovel and Whirl-Pak bags (Nasco, WI, USA). Remaining plant roots and rocks were removed manually in a class II microbiological safety cabinet; samples were homogenized by manual mixing and frozen at −20°C before transportation to the United Kingdom. Samples were conserved at –20°C until analyzed.
 </p>
 <div id="fig1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Map of sampling sites within the Arctic Region, as characterized by the Arctic circle (black line), the 10°C isotherm (red) and the tree line boundary (green). 200 individual soil samples at 43 different sites were collected for this study, all within at least one of the definitions of the Arctic region.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fiz128fig1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
