<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial and environmental factors influencing bacterial communities</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distance–decay curves were used to evaluate the influence of spatial factors on bacterial community structure. Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2A</a> illustrates the increase in community dissimilarity with increasing geographic distance (linear regression: 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.108, 
  <span class="italic">P &lt;</span> 2.2 × 10
  <span class="italic">
   <span class="sup">−</span>
  </span>
  <span class="sup">16</span>). The best-fitted power model (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.221, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.005) suggested the presence of spatial autocorrelation, also qualified as dispersal limitation, within the first 500 m. For a more accurate estimate of dispersal limitation, we plotted the same graph within 0 and 500 m (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2B</a>) and observed spatial autocorrelation approximately up to 20 m.
 </p>
 <div id="fig2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Distance–decay curves with the linear regression (red), the best-fitted power model (green). 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> Community dissimilarity of the total bacterial community by geographic distance in km. 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> Zoom into Fig. 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">2A</a> from 0 to 500 m to assess the spatial autocorrelation distance.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fiz128fig2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the influence of environmental factors on the bacterial community structure, we used the adonis function with 999 permutations. Results indicated that pH explained 18.7% of the variance in bacterial community composition overall (Table 
  <a rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" href="#tbl1">1</a>). In comparison, conductivity, moisture and TOC explained almost 10% of the variance altogether. The measured environmental parameters explained 29% of the variance in the bacterial subcommunity, leaving 71% unexplained.
 </p>
 <div id="tbl1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The relative importance of environmental factors on bacterial communities, calculated by adonis.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Total</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">R</span>
      </sub>2
     </th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pr(
      <span class="italic">&gt;</span>F)
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.187</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001***</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conductivity</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001***</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moisture</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.027</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001***</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">TOC</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001***</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Residuals</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.717</td>
     <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To quantify the influence of edaphic properties and spatial factors, we conducted variation partitioning on the bacterial community. We built spatial vectors using distance-based Moran's Eigenvector Maps (dbMEM) on 
  <span class="italic">x</span>,
  <span class="italic">y</span> geographic coordinates. Three vectors (MEMs) were produced; after forward selection, two significant MEMs were identified for the total community and used in further analyses. The variation partitioning analysis differentiated the effect of environmental factors, linear trend and spatial vectors on Bray–Curtis dissimilarity (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">3</a>). Results indicated that the environmental factors (X1 = [a]+[d]+[g]+[f]) explained 30.7% of the variance in the community. These results are equivalent to the finding of the adonis test (Table 
  <a rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" href="#tbl1">1</a>), confirming the success of the variation partitioning analysis. Nonspatially structured environmental variables (fraction [a]) explained 15% of the variation while spatial factors only (fractions [b], [e] and [c]) explained ∼10% of the variation. Of the fraction X1 (environmental factors), 15% represented spatially structured environmental variables, also called induced spatial dependence, where the spatial structure of these environmental variables induced a similar spatial structure in the response data (detailed results in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Table S1</a>, Supporting Information). In total, 63.3% of the total bacterial community dissimilarity could not be explained by environmental and spatial factors after 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> adjustment.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Venn diagram illustrating the results of the variation partitioning analysis and indicating the amount of variation in bacterial community explained by environmental variables and spatial factors including the linear trend. Detailed results are available in 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Table S1</a> (Supporting Information).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fiz128fig3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
