<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previously, Sleep and Zahnle (
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>) modeled the evolution of the geological carbon cycle over Earth history and reported the Hadean and Archean mean surface temperatures below 0 °C, unless atmospheric methane abundances were very high. In contrast, we find that Archean temperatures were likely temperate, regardless of methane abundances. This disparity can be ascribed to the differing treatments of seafloor weathering. Sleep and Zahnle (
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>) did not include ocean chemistry in their model (they effectively fix pH), and were thus forced to parameterize seafloor weathering using a power-law pCO
  <sub>2</sub> dependence with a fitted exponent. This parameterization overestimates the role of Archean seafloor weathering. Experiments with basalt dissolution reveal a weak pH dependence and a moderate temperature dependence, but no direct pCO
  <sub>2</sub> dependence (see discussion in ref. 
  <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The change from a CO
  <sub>2</sub>-dependent parameterization to a temperature-dependent parameterization means the seafloor weathering feedback better stabilizes climate against increasing luminosity. For a purely temperature-dependent weathering feedback, decreasing luminosity does not change climate, as the weathering flux must remain constant to maintain carbon cycle balance. Instead, CO
  <sub>2</sub> adjusts upwards to maintain the same temperature at lower insolation. In contrast, for a purely CO
  <sub>2</sub>-dependent weathering feedback, a decrease in solar luminosity will result in a temperature decrease (see also 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix B</span>
  </span>). In short, the pH-dependent and temperature-dependent seafloor weathering parameterization we apply stabilizes climate and prevents a globally glaciated early Earth. This result is broadly consistent with a single time point at 3.8 Ga that calculated equilibrium surface temperatures using a GCM and geological carbon cycle model (
  <a rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" href="#r13">13</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The only way to produce Archean climates below 0 °C in our model is to assume the Archean outgassing flux was 1–5× lower than the modern flux (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S12
  </span>). However, dramatically lowered Archean outgassing fluxes contradict known outgassing proxies and probably require both a stagnant lid tectonic regime and a mantle more reduced than zircon data suggest, which lowers the portion of outgassed CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix C</span>
  </span>). Moreover, even when outgassing is low, frozen climates are not guaranteed (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S12
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our model gives a monotonic evolution of ocean pH from 6.3–7.7 in the Archean (95% confidence), to 6.5–8.1 (95% confidence) in the Proterozoic, and increasing to 8.2 in the modern surface ocean. This history is broadly consistent with that of Halevy and Bachan (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Figs. 3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">4</a>). Halevy and Bachan (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>) tracked Na, Cl, Mg, and K exchanges with continental and oceanic crust, and related these fluxes to the thermal evolution of the Earth. Minor constituents such as HS, NH
  <sub>3</sub>, Fe
  <span class="sup">2+</span>, and SO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2-</span> were also considered. However, they prescribe many features of the carbon cycle rather than apply a self-consistent model as we have done here. Specifically, they imposed pCO
  <sub>2</sub> to ensure near-modern temperatures throughout Earth history. Consequently, the explicit temperature dependence of both seafloor and continental weathering were omitted. Additionally, subduction and outgassing were assumed to be directly proportional, a limited range of heat flow histories were adopted, and continental silicate weathering was described using an overall pCO
  <sub>2</sub> power-law dependence with no allowance for changing land fraction or biogenic enhancement weathering. Thus, the uncertainty envelopes for the early Earth ocean pH are underestimated in ref. 
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a> as can be seen by their uncertainty diminishing further back in time. Good agreement with the results of ref. 
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a> confirms that the details of ocean chemistry are of secondary importance to pH evolution, and that the monotonic evolution of pH is instead driven by solar luminosity evolution, buffered by enhanced continental and seafloor weathering under high pCO
  <sub>2</sub> conditions. The two models also agree because the carbon cycle buffers to near-modern temperatures, allowing the constant temperature assumption of ref. 
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>, but there is no way of knowing the effectiveness of the buffer without a self-consistent model of the carbon cycle.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One caveat for our results is that the ocean chemistry is incomplete. Specifically, Ca abundances in the ocean and pore space are controlled entirely by alkalinity fluxes from continental and seafloor weathering. In reality, Ca abundances are modulated by other processes such as the hydrothermal exchange of Ca and Mg in the seafloor, dolomitization, and clay formation (
  <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>). To explore whether neglecting these processes would affect our results we conducted sensitivity tests with a large ensemble of Ca evolutions (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix C</span>
  </span>). High Archean Ca abundances might be expected to produce more acidic oceans because carbonate abundances are lower for the same saturation state. However, this effect is buffered by decreases in Ca and CO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> activity coefficients (complexing), and so model outputs look very similar to our nominal model for a broad range of Ca abundance trajectories (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S9
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our nominal climate model, we did not include the effects of changing atmospheric pressure or albedo changes. These effects are likely to be modest compared with the other sources of uncertainty in our model. Lower surface albedo from a reduced Archean land fraction can contribute at most 5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> of radiative forcing (
  <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>), which would cause only a few degrees of warming. Halving Archean total pressure—as has been suggested by paleopressure proxies (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>)—would cool the Earth by ∼5 K because of the loss of pressure broadening, thereby offsetting the lower land fraction (
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>). Changes in cloud cover could, in principle, induce larger warming, but the required conditions for &gt;10 K warming are highly speculative (
  <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>). In any case, the effects of pressure changes and albedo changes are unlikely to affect our conclusions because the temperature changes they induce will be compensated by pCO
  <sub>2</sub> variations to balance the carbon cycle. Sensitivity analyses where massive amounts of Archean warming are imposed (+30 K) still result in temperate surface temperatures because of this pCO
  <sub>2</sub> compensation (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S10
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although our model outputs are broadly consistent with paleosol proxies and glacial constraints, some disagreement occurs with selected seafloor weathering proxies. Proxies for seafloor carbonate precipitation were estimated by using the average carbonate abundances in Archean oceanic crust, scaled by the model spreading rate at that time multiplied by an assumed carbonatization depth (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix D</span>
  </span>). Our modeled seafloor carbonate precipitation fluxes agree with that of Nakamura and Kato (
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>) and Shibuya et al. (
  <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>), but undershoot crustal carbonate abundances reported by Shibuya et al. (
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>) and Kitajima et al. (
  <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>). It is difficult to construct a balanced carbon cycle model with seafloor weathering fluxes in excess of 100 Tmol C/y as these latter two studies imply, and so the discrepancy may be because those oceanic crust samples are not representative of global carbonatization flux, or because some of the carbonate is secondary. The only way to approach the carbonate abundances reported by Shibuya et al. (
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>) and Kitajima et al. (
  <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>) is to impose very high Archean outgassing (e.g., up to 60× the modern flux; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S11
  </span>), but even then the fit is marginal. If high Archean crustal carbonate estimates were truly primary, then Archean outgassing would have been very high, and so Earth’s internal heat flow would have decreased dramatically over Earth’s history, contrary to Korenaga (
  <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conclude that current best knowledge of Earth’s geologic carbon cycle precludes a hot Archean. Our results are insensitive to assumptions about ocean chemistry, internal evolution, and weathering parameterizations, so a hot early Earth would require some fundamental error in current understanding of the carbon cycle. Increasing the biotic enhancement of weathering by several orders of magnitude as proposed by Schwartzman (
  <a rid="r60" ref-type="bibr" href="#r60">60</a>) does not produce a hot Archean because this is mathematically equivalent to zeroing out the continental weathering flux (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>). In this case the temperature-dependent seafloor weathering feedback buffers the climate of the Earth to moderate temperatures (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1721296115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S14
  </span>). Dramatic temperature increases (or decreases) due to albedo changes also do not change our conclusions due to the buffering effect of the carbon cycle (see above). If both continental and seafloor weathering become supply limited (e.g., refs. 
  <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a> and 
  <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>), then temperatures could easily exceed 50 °C. However, in this case the carbon cycle would be out of balance, leading to excessive pCO
  <sub>2</sub> accumulation within a few hundred million years unless buffered by some other, unknown feedback.
 </p>
</sec>
