<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate is changing rapidly [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>], and the regional distribution of many plant and animal taxa has begun to shift spatially in response to the changing environment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Much research has focused in recent years on the ecological impacts of climate change on species or communities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>], and although changes in the distribution of species are likely the mirror of individual responses to climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>], studies linking fine-scale individual behaviour with broad-scale climatic trends are slow to follow (but see, e.g., [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]). Studying individual responses to climate may help understand how species will react, and potentially adapt to climate change; this knowledge would be of paramount scientific, conservation, and management value [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-latitude environments are disproportionately affected by climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Arctic and subarctic species now cope with warmer temperatures, altered precipitation patterns, and more frequent extreme weather events [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Numerous studies have demonstrated that Arctic perennial sea ice is declining rapidly [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], affecting the ecology and demography of pagophilic (i.e., ice-dependent) species such as the polar bear (
  <span class="italic">Ursus maritimus</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]), Pacific walrus (
  <span class="italic">Odobenus rosmarus divergens</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]), and hooded seal (
  <span class="italic">Cystophora cristata</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]). Accumulating evidence also suggests that the phenology of freshwater-ice formation and ablation in northern regions is changing (see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>] and references therein). For example, Magnuson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>] analyzed time series of ice extents on water bodies of the Northern Hemisphere and found that lakes and rivers had increasingly earlier breakup and later freezing dates during the 1846–1995 period. These seasonal processes may influence non-pagophilic terrestrial species that use ice on inland water bodies to move across their range or colonize new areas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>] by impeding their movements [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>], altering the timing of their migrations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>], or increasing their risks of drowning [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We studied the responses of migratory caribou (
  <span class="italic">Rangifer tarandus caribou</span>) to trends in the availability of ice on lakes and rivers in an Arctic/subarctic region to assess potential mechanisms linking fine-scale individual behaviour to broad-scale climatic conditions. Predicting changes in caribou migration routes in response to climate change would aid conservation efforts for the species (notably regarding planning of human developments [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]) as well as ensure long-term sustainability of the Aboriginal hunt [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Caribou perform one of the most impressive terrestrial long-distance migrations in the world [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. In Northern Québec (Canada), caribou travel distances up to 1 000 km from their calving grounds in the Ungava Peninsula to their wintering areas in the boreal forest. Along the way, they encounter many lakes and rivers, which are highly abundant in the region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. The potential consequences of crossing water bodies for caribou could depend on the availability of ice. Caribou are often observed swimming across open water bodies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>], but this type of locomotion is much less efficient and more energetically costly than walking [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. Frozen water bodies are plane, wind-swept surfaces with packed snow and increased visibility that make them ideal substrates to move rapidly during travel. On the other hand, frozen lakes are entirely devoid of vegetation, and represent large open areas that may facilitate detection by predators [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] and hunters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. Thus, caribou encountering large water bodies may have to trade off energy maintenance (i.e., by crossing) with foraging opportunities (i.e., by going around), as well as mortality risk (including risks of drowning [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our objectives were four-fold. First, we analyzed contemporary (2000–2014) and historical (1947–1985) thawing and freezing trends of lakes and rivers in the range of the Rivière-aux-Feuilles (RAF) caribou herd in Northern Québec (Canada). We predicted that these local trends would reflect results obtained by Magnuson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>] at much larger spatiotemporal scales. Second, we assessed the responses of caribou to ice and water availability by studying their space use and movements on and around lakes and rivers during 8 years (2007–2014). This was done at a fine spatiotemporal scale using GPS-collared animals and regularly updated (i.e., every 8 days) 500-m resolution ice maps. We predicted that caribou would select ice during their movements to travel more rapidly and directly, and to reduce the energetic costs associated with swimming [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. We also predicted that caribou would circumvent water bodies more frequently when ice was unavailable [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Third, we assessed the relationship between fine-scale, intra-annual variability in caribou behaviour and broad-scale, inter-annual changes in ice phenology. We predicted that caribou would adjust their behaviour (e.g., avoid water more strongly) according to trends in breakup and freeze dates observed during the study. Finally, we projected the contemporary movements of caribou within a gradient of future ice phenology scenarios to determine the potential consequences of climate change on the movements of caribou during the next 25 – 50 years. We predicted that future climatic conditions could force caribou to circumvent unfrozen water bodies more often, resulting in an increase in the total distance travelled by caribou to reach wintering and calving areas.
 </p>
</sec>
