<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change and ice phenology</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Declines in sea- [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] and freshwater-ice [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>] have begun to affect the distribution and behaviour of arctic wildlife [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Global surface temperatures have increased by approximately 0.12 °C (0.08 – 0.14 °C CI 90 %) per decade over the last &gt;50 years (with Arctic warming going at least twice as fast [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]), and ice breakup and freeze dates on lakes and rivers in northern regions have changed correspondingly [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Temperatures are predicted to continue increasing in the future, and depending upon climate scenarios (see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]), the average air temperature could rise 1.5 °C to 4.0 °C by the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century (with even more rapid changes in arctic/sub-arctic regions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]). These increases in the rate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>] (see also [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>] for comparable results on plant phenology) and magnitude [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>] of changes in arctic environments suggest that freshwater ice availability in Northern Québec will likely decrease in the foreseeable future. In fact, based on various projections across northern North America [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>], as much as 36 % of ice crossings performed by caribou during the early spring and fall migrations would not have been possible if icing phenology had been comparable to conditions anticipated for the 2041 – 2070 horizon.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contrary to Magnuson et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>], we did not detect any significant icing trend on the largest water bodies used by caribou in Northern Québec (2000–2014) and Lake Nichicun (1947–1985). This study was based on a different methodology and used data collected over much broader spatial (i.e., Northern Hemisphere) and temporal (i.e., 19
  <span class="sup">th</span> century onwards) scales. In comparison, our compilation of 15 years of MODIS data may have been insufficient to detect a significant trend. Broad scale predictive models usually outperform finer climatic models because of their capacity to capture a larger range of variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Other reports on local freshwater ice conditions have also demonstrated the difficulty of studying ice phenology at fine scales [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Latifovic and Pouliot [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>] found that, out of 36 lakes monitored across Canada from 1950 to 2004, 33 had earlier breakup and 24 had later freezing dates, but only 45 % and 42 % of these trends were statistically significant, respectively. The lack of additional long-term data on ice availability in our study area prevented us from performing more precise analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
