<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and caribou herd</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The RAF caribou herd ranged over &gt;630 000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> across Northern Québec, Canada (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Females gave birth in the Arctic tundra of the Ungava Peninsula (61°N, 74°W), generally between early and mid-June. In October–December, caribou undertook a long migration across the taiga and into the northern fringe of the boreal forest, where they fed on arboreal and terrestrial lichens (mostly 
  <span class="italic">Cladonia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cetraria</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Usnea</span>) found in open black spruce (
  <span class="italic">Picea mariana</span>) stands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. In April, they left their wintering ranges and initiated a migration back to the calving grounds. Across this entire journey, they coped with severe climatic conditions typical of arctic and subarctic regions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. In the southern part of the caribou range, a series of hydroelectric infrastructures were built during Hydro-Québec’s James Bay Project in the 1970s and 1980s. Many structures were built on La Grande River, along which several natural lakes were converted into some of the largest artificial reservoirs in the region (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Study area in Northern Québec showing the range of the Rivière-aux-Feuilles caribou herd. We delineated the range using a 100 % minimum convex polygon encompassing caribou locations from 2007 to 2014. The largest water bodies used to study caribou responses to ice and water (as well as Lake Nichicun, see Additional file 
     <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>) appear in blue. All other water bodies in the province appear in light grey. Inserts show the location of our study area (
     <span class="italic">top-left</span>) and the steps performed by caribou during this study (
     <span class="italic">bottom-left</span>). Overlaid over observed steps (
     <span class="italic">green lines</span>) are the approximate trajectories of the fall migrations (
     <span class="italic">red arrow</span>), winter displacements (
     <span class="italic">blue arrow</span>), and spring migrations (
     <span class="italic">black arrow</span>) performed by caribou
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40462_2016_79_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
