<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While the scientific consensus has strengthened, public opinion remains seriously divided, without a clear trend [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. Repeated surveys report annual-scale variations possibly related to developments such as release of the 2007 IPCC report, the 2008 economic crisis, “climategate” attacks on scientists in 2009, or a snowy northeastern US winter in 2011 [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Decadal-scale surveys provide essential perspective, but must employ questions with wording that has changed over the years, or else was frozen at a time when the discourse was different. Whereas recent scientific statements emphasize the term “climate change,” referencing regional differences and shifts in precipitation, storms or extreme events, the legacy survey questions often ask about “global warming” instead. Non-scientists sometimes misinterpret this term to mean that every place should be constantly warming, which seems easily refuted by pointing out a place that is cooling. Moreover, there has been publicity about a “pause” or slowdown in the rate of global air temperature rise, leading to unscientific claims that global warming had stopped [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The term “global warming” by itself apparently can elicit more conservative opposition than the term “climate change” on surveys [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. A potentially greater problem with wording is that some of the longest-running survey questions do not specify human causation, which today (rather than the mere fact of change) forms the main point of public contention [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. The reality of climate change has been publicly acknowledged even by political leaders who dismiss human causation as a hoax [
 <xref rid="pone.0138208.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. These complications in public discourse make it harder to interpret responses to survey questions designed long ago.
</p>
