<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An Atlantic Niño, characterized by warm sea surface temperature (SST) anomalies in the equatorial east Atlantic, typically peaks in boreal summer and is the dominant mode of interannual variability in the equatorial Atlantic (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>). Dynamics of an Atlantic Niño are somewhat similar to those of a Pacific El Niño, involving Bjerknes positive feedback. That is, initial warm SST anomalies in the equatorial eastern Atlantic lead to weaker trade winds, driving an eastward propagating equatorial oceanic downwelling Kelvin wave and a deeper thermocline, which, in turn, causes further warming in a coupled oceanic-atmospheric process (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>). An Atlantic Niño promotes the occurrence of a Pacific La Niña in the ensuring winter (
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>). Specifically, the associated anomalous heating enhances local convections (fig. S1), inducing an intensified Walker circulation with an ascending branch over the Atlantic and a descending branch over the central Pacific during boreal summer (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">11</italic>
 </xref>). The latter causes equatorial easterly anomalies, triggering Bjerknes positive feedback in the equatorial Pacific, and the development of a La Niña event (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>). The opposite operates for an Atlantic Niña to induce an El Niño.
</p>
