<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A database of future daily weather data is available for the whole of Europe, specifically designed to be used for crop modelling [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. In short, these data are based on three downscaled and bias-corrected regional climate model implementations of the IPCC A1B emission scenario, which is a middle of road scenario describing a world with rapid economic growth and a mix of fossil and non-fossil energy sources, as created within the ENSEMBLES project [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. The weather generator ClimGen [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] has been applied to produce 30 simulated years of weather for each climate model, for the time horizons 2000, 2020 and 2030. These future weather data are bias-corrected using the same weather database as our forecasting model baseline [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. Duveiller et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] term the three climate model implementations DMI-HIRHAM5-ECHAM5 [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], ETHZ-CLM-HadCM3Q0 [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] and METO-HC-HadRM3Q0-HadCM3Q0 [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], which are respectively referred to as DMI, ETHZ and METO for short in this paper. Duveiller et al. chose these models because they are based on widely used global circulation models and show maximum diversity in output weather variables. In general, DMI and METO are the coldest and warmest regarding surface air temperature, respectively, ETHZ falls in between but shows different precipitation patterns [
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. We uses the 2030 time horizon for all three climate models for our scenario analysis. For each climate model, 30 simulated years representing 2030 were used, meaning 90 years of potential future European weather in 2030. The data are available on a 25 x 25 km grid. A data summary is presented in 
 <xref rid="pone.0218956.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>.
</p>
