<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="pcx141-T1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">Table 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Key definitions</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" class="table">
  <thead align="left" class="thead">
   <tr class="tr">
    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">Term</th>
    <th rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">Definition</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody align="left" class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Greenhouse gases (GHGs)</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">These are gases (e.g. water vapor, carbon dioxide, methane) in the atmosphere that absorb and emit radiation warming Earth’s surface to a temperature above what it would be without the atmosphere.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Climate change adaptation</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">In the context of climate change adaptation means taking appropriate actions (e.g. move the planting dates earlier or introducing drought tolerant varieties) to prevent or minimize the damage the adverse effects of climate change can cause, or taking advantage of opportunities that may arise (e.g. expanding cropping areas of certain crops).</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Climate change mitigation</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">In the context of climate change mitigation refers to efforts to reduce or prevent emission of greenhouse gases. Mitigation can mean using new technologies and renewable energies, making older equipment more energy efficient, or changing management practices (e.g. minimize soil cultivation) or consumer behavior.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Representative concentration pathways (RCPs)</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">These are four greenhouse gas concentration trajectories adopted by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2014. They describe four plausible climate futures, all of which are considered possible depending on how much greenhouse gases are emitted in the years to come. RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6, and RCP8.5, are named after a possible range of radiative forcing values (the difference between the incoming radiation absorbed by the Earth and the energy radiated back to space) in the year 2100 relative to pre-industrial values (+2.6, +4.5, +6.0, and +8.5 W/m2, respectively)</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Computable general equilibrium (CGE)</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">These models are a class of economic models that use actual economic data to estimate how an economy might react to changes in policy, technology or other external factors.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Scopus</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">This is the world’s largest abstract and citation database of peer-reviewed research literature with over 22,000 titles from more than 5,000 international publishers.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Fuzzy logic</td>
    <td rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">This is a form of multi-value logic in which the truth values of variables may be any real number between 0 and 1. It is employed to handle the concept of partial truth, where the truth value may range between completely true and completely false.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
