<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To study a wide range of potential future environmental conditions a total of six climate scenarios were analyzed, combining three climate trajectories derived from climate models with two future scenarios of peak wind speed. The three climate change scenarios were based on different combinations of global and regional circulation models under A1B forcing, namely CNRM‐RM4.5 driven by ARPEGE (Radu et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), MPI‐REMO (Jacob 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>), and ICTP‐RegCM3, both driven by ECHAM5 (Pal et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Previous analyses showed that the temperature and precipitation changes resulting from the A1B scenario storyline lie between those expected from RCP4.5 and RCP6.0 for our study area (Thom et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017a</xref>). For mean annual temperature, the three scenarios project an increase of +3.2° to +3.3°C for the period 2080–2100 relative to the climate of 1950–2000. For the same reference period, annual precipitation sum changes by between −84 and +160 mm in the studied climate scenarios. Climate was assumed to stabilize at the level of 2080–2100 for the years simulated past 2100. Climate scenario data were statistically downscaled using climate observations provided by the Central Institute of Meteorology and Geodynamics Vienna (cf. Thom et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017b</xref>). To address the considerable remaining uncertainties regarding local future wind climate (Lindner et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), we studied two wind scenarios for each of the three model‐derived climate trajectories. The first scenario was based on historically observed wind data, assuming that future peak wind speeds and return intervals resembled those of the recent past. The second scenario follows recent findings indicating that future peak wind speed could increase moderately in Central Europe (Rockel and Woth 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>), assuming a 10% increase in peak wind speeds across all wind events. An in‐depth description of the disturbance scenarios and processes can be found in Seidl et al. (
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018a</xref>).
</p>
