<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The importance of an increasing focus on patient safety in healthcare has been recognised [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. However, whilst the majority of patient contacts occur in primary care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>], there has been a far greater focus on patient safety in hospital settings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>], arguably due to a perception of primary care as a relatively lower-risk endeavour [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. However, both patient [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>] and practice factors [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>] have contributed to a growing complexity of clinical practice for general practitioners (GPs) which, combined with the sheer volume of patient contact, increases the potential for patient safety incidents (PSIs) in primary care. This is particularly concerning as GPs have reported several barriers to monitoring patient safety, such as limited and unreliable data on serious incidents, time to review practice-level data, and lack of examples of serious harm or ‘never’ events that are applicable to primary care settings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recognising the limited data on patient safety in primary care, the World Health Organisation has noted the pressing need to study and address patient safety in this setting [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. In secondary care settings, targeted strategies have been implemented [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>], with varying degrees of supporting evidence. However, a systematic review [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>] of interventions to improve safety culture in primary care identified only two published interventional studies. Although both studies reported positive outcomes, methodological issues precluded the derivation of conclusive recommendations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Scottish Patient Safety Programme in Primary Care (SPSP-PC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>] is one of the first comprehensive and coordinated attempts to improve patient safety in primary care. This programme has been implemented in 90% of Scottish general practices, with 83% reporting that it enabled them to make changes within their practice, resulting in safer, higher quality patient care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. GP feedback on the programme’s acceptability, feasibility, and utility has been predominantly positive [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. However, its impact has not yet been evaluated independently of its developers, or assessed using a strong experimental design. Given the dearth of information on safety interventions in primary care, we therefore aimed to inform the design of a definitive randomised controlled trial of a primary care patient safety intervention.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We report the feasibility of conducting a randomised controlled trial of an intervention, developed previously by SPSP-PC, within primary care settings in two different healthcare systems; the Republic of Ireland (RoI) and Northern Ireland (NI). Following recommendations for good practice when designing pilot and feasibility studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>], we aimed to evaluate rates of recruitment and retention of practices, response rates to questionnaires, completion of outcome measures, and participants’ perceptions of the intervention and effects of the intervention on safety climate.
 </p>
</sec>
