<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec23" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews</div>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nine members of the practice teams were interviewed across the four intervention practices, including: three principal GPs, three non-principal GPs, one practice nurse, and two administrators. Two interviews were carried out by telephone, and seven were conducted face-to-face. No invitees declined to be interviewed but not all who agreed were available at times convenient to the researcher and recruitment ceased when data saturation was considered to have been achieved. Interviews lasted approximately ten minutes. Three themes emerged from the analysis of interview data, with supporting quotes anonymised by the interviewee’s role (managerial/ non-managerial: M/ NM) and participant number.</p>
 <sec id="Sec24" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Benefits from the intervention</div>
  <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several interviewees considered that the intervention was helpful in raising awareness of safety issues, promoting learning and 
   <span class="italic">“beneficial for your own practice…and for your own patients”</span> (NM1). One commented that the intervention “
   <span class="italic">would cover areas that I suppose we mightn’t, you know, be aware of”</span> (M1)
   <span class="italic">,</span> and noted that it “
   <span class="italic">highlighted things to us that we mightn’t have realised at all were issues”</span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SC survey was beneficial in providing a ‘voice’ for more junior and non-managerial staff. Interviewees recognised that 
   <span class="italic">“it’s hard to raise concerns on a personal basis…it’s good to do this sort of thing anonymously”</span> (NM6) and commented on the tailored practice-level feedback: 
   <span class="italic">“it was good to see how you compared to other practices as well to use it as a benchmark”</span> (NM3). Group discussions identified different approaches within practices, of primary care team members, to decision-making and patient management, that were previously unrecognised. Revelations of “w
   <span class="italic">here unnecessary work was being done and where gaps were being left”</span> (NM4) were beneficial to organisational planning.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes and improvements in practice</div>
  <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One interviewee reported how the intervention had indicated that 
   <span class="italic">‘changes should be made…….but that takes effort and time’</span> (NM4)
   <span class="italic">.</span> However, this perception of inaction was a deviant view: other interviewees, including others from the same practice, reported changes in practices’ processes and management. For example, 
   <span class="italic">“note taking got a bit better after house calls”</span> (NM1), changes were made to protocols; “
   <span class="italic">we were all actually using different protocols kind of to change the Warfarin dosage…we standardised that and we have it in now in our system”</span> (NM3), 
   <span class="italic">“the prophylactic antibiotics given for UTI… are now changed to nitrofurantoin – because guidelines had changed”</span> (NM6). The intervention encouraged clinical meetings in one practice and in another, there was a plan to 
   <span class="italic">“try to make discussions at those more inclusive”</span> (NM5)
   <span class="italic">.</span>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec26" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acceptability and recommendations</div>
  <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most interviewees welcomed the intervention; one noted 
   <span class="italic">“I definitely think it’s worth it”</span> (NM2), although a commonly perceived barrier was lack of time; 
   <span class="italic">“It was time intensive- with current workloads and demands on time it couldn’t be given a priority”</span> (NM5)
   <span class="italic">,</span> and that 
   <span class="italic">“many practices do not have the resources</span>” (M3).
  </p>
  <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The general consensus was that the intervention was worth investigating in a larger trial and that evidence of its effectiveness would promote its use in routine practice. Comments revealed perceptions that the SC questionnaire 
   <span class="italic">“asked same basic questions in different ways”</span> (NM4) but this was welcomed as it allowed opportunity to consider different situations within their responses. Also, comments indicated some uncertainty in identifying PSIs: group discussion was valued in developing an agreed definition. Interviewees offered recommendations, such as, 
   <span class="italic">“… the [TRM] tool needs a few tweaks- it’s a good way of assessing how things go but thought should be given to giving it more rigour”</span> (NM6) and, regarding the time required, 
   <span class="italic">“obviously that has to be reimbursed”</span> (NM3).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
