<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">DNA metabarcoding using high‐throughput sequencing enables the identification of dietary species using DNA extracted from faecal samples more accurately than traditional visual and microscopic observation of faecal samples (Kartzinel et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This technique has been used to identify herbivore gut contents, revealing cryptic functional diversity and niche partitioning (Kress, García‐Robledo, Uriarte, &amp; Erickson, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Plastid genes such as 
 <italic class="italic">rbc</italic>L (Group et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) and nuclear ribosomal internal transcribed spacer (ITS; Hollingsworth, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) are commonly used for plant metabarcoding (Hollingsworth, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). We aimed to analyse faecal pellets using metabarcoding to identify the plants in the diet of the Royle's pika and examine the effects of talus characteristics, topography and plant richness; abundance; and seasonal dynamics (pre‐ and postmonsoon) on diet, across five sites in the western Himalaya, India. Food availability (plant species’ presence and abundance; Huntly, Smith, &amp; Ivins, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1986</xref>; Dearing, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>; Wilkening et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Bhattacharyya et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014a</xref>; Bhattacharyya &amp; Ray, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), habitat topography (elevation, slope, aspect; Walker, Halfpenny, Walker, &amp; Wessman, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>; Deems, Birkeland, &amp; Hansen, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Wilkening et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Rodhouse et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Gurung et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and predation risk (rock cover, crevice depth, distance to the nearest area of talus; Calkins, Beever, Boykin, Frey, &amp; Andersen, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Bhattacharyya et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014a</xref>,
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">b</xref>; Castillo, Epps, Davis, &amp; Cushman, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Bhattacharyya et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) significantly impact the foraging ecology of the Royle's pika and potentially influence access to nutritive plants, and thereby affect individual fitness (Bhattacharyya, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). For talus‐dwelling 
 <italic class="italic">Ochotona</italic> spp., talus size (area) and connectivity between talus are known to influence the habitat occupancy (Franken &amp; Hik, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). In Royle's pikas, a high proportion of rock cover in talus habitat provides refuge from predation risk, which in turn increases their habitat occupancy and abundance (Bhattacharyya et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Topographical features determine the distribution and abundance of alpine plants (Bruun et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The prehistoric distribution of small mammals (Ochotonidae), highly adapted to arctic or alpine environment, was closely associated with preferred C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> food plant diet which is high in protein and moisture content (Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Whilst the interplay between plants and herbivores is a key determinant of community structure (see Dolezal et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Wisz et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), climate‐induced expansion of C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> plants is believed to have resulted in extinction and range contraction in pikas (Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Furthermore, in highly seasonal montane habitats, dietary constraints in herbivores tend to be strongly linked to quality of forage available. In the Himalayan region, both plant quality and available biomass may act as constraints for pikas. Seasonal dynamics in diet selection can reflect dietary adaptations (plasticity) in a seasonal alpine habitat. Our Royle's pika diet analysis will provide insights into the plant genera selected during foraging and test the following hypotheses:
</p>
