<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amplification by the Bjerknes Feedback</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is not well understood why the Pacific warms preferentially in response to increased TSI (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). Previous studies have noted an ENSO-like pattern and suggested a dynamically excited mechanism involving a damped-resonant ENSO response triggered by direct TSI surface heating (
  <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>). However, the weak westerly anomalies found in AMIP-ZM suggest an alternative mechanism and here we propose that a Bjerknes feedback further weakens the PWC at Smax.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigate this hypothesis in a conceptual framework using a low-order atmosphere–ocean model of the Pacific that has been extensively used to study ENSO dynamics (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>). The model solves for SST and thermocline depth anomalies in two boxes, representing the east and west equatorial Pacific, by taking into account the Bjerknes feedback that drives wind stress anomalies, which in turn cause equatorial upwelling in the eastern Pacific and zonal advection (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
  </span>). Effects of the SC are introduced as an 11-y sinusoidal modulation of the wind stress of 1% amplitude, roughly corresponding to the 10% reduction in surface easterlies simulated in AMIP-ZM. The model shows that the imposed westerly anomaly reduces the thermocline tilt between the West and East Pacific at Smax, resulting in eastward advection of anomalously warm water and positive SST anomalies in the East Pacific (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S11
  </span>). The west–east SST gradient is thus weakened and hence the Bjerknes feedback reinforces the imposed westerly anomalies. The transition from Smax to Smin weakens and eventually reverses the wind anomalies to easterlies at Smin.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results of this low-order ENSO model can only frame a theoretical background for understanding the observed PWC weakening given that the simulated response amplitude depends on the assumed coupling parameters. Nevertheless, the low-order model predicts a weakening of the equatorial Pacific thermocline tilt at Smax, and thus a lifted thermocline in the western Pacific that brings cold water to the subsurface. We find further evidence that the two-box model can be considered as a credible analog of the observed SC response by examining equatorial subsurface ocean temperature responses in the EN4 objective analysis for the period 1950–2013 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>). MLR identifies negative temperature anomalies, indicating a shallower thermocline in the western Pacific at +1 y lag (−0.5 K per 1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> TSI at 130 m, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.3) and significant positive anomalies indicating a deeper thermocline in the eastern Pacific (&gt;1 K, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05; 120°–160°W at 130-m depth). This means a reduced thermocline tilt at Smax as suggested by the low-order model. This observational evidence is supported by the SOLAR ensemble, which simulates cold water in the western Pacific subsurface, but does not show a stronger warming in the subsurface over the central and eastern sector (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>). This negligible change in the eastern Pacific thermocline likely explains the generally weaker SST warming in the equatorial Pacific at Smax (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">I</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>SC regression coefficients of ocean temperature in the equatorial Pacific for (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) EN4.2.0 (1950–2013) and (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) SOLAR. Hatched areas indicate chance probability 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1. Units in K per 1-W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span> increase in TSI. Signals refer to +1-y time lag.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1815060116fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The low-order model thus highlights the potential for a Bjerknes amplification of the weak westerly wind anomalies initially generated by the SC influence on global hydrology. In addition, the relaxation of the trade winds at Smax is likely to weaken evaporative cooling, which further weakens the surface winds. This wind–evaporation–SST feedback (
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>), not accounted for in the low-order model, could provide a source of additional warming in the West Pacific, as indicated by the pattern of Pacific SST anomalies in the Kaplan dataset and the SOLAR ensemble (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1 
   <span class="italic">C</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
