<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary and Discussion</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies of the response to centennial increases in TSI have suggested a contrasting response, with reduced rainfall in the Pacific and stronger east–west SST gradients (
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). However, this response is not supported by a recent multimodel comparison of the tropical impacts of a step-change doubling of CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration versus a 2% increase in TSI (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>). In those simulations, both forcings produced strikingly similar patterns of increased precipitation over the central Pacific and a relaxed east–west SST gradient, despite the fact that TSI predominately affects the surface, whereas GHGs perturb the radiative balance of the troposphere. In fact, the globally averaged precipitation is expected to increase at higher rates for the same surface warming under TSI than GHG forcing (
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>). Likewise, we find no evidence for divergent patterns in the Pacific response given that the detected patterns of increased rainfall, relaxed SST gradient, positive ΔSLP anomalies, and a weakened PWC in response to SC resemble modeled responses to 2% TSI and doubling CO
  <sub>2</sub>, despite subtle differences in the timescale and the magnitude of the forcing (2% TSI roughly corresponds to 20× the SC amplitude).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By highlighting the importance of global hydrology in mediating SC responses in the tropical Pacific, our findings add confidence in the modeled predictions for a weakened PWC, driven by similar hydrological changes in response to GHG forcing. We are not suggesting, however, that observed SC signatures can be used as an analog for quantifying future PWC responses to GHGs. This is because we identify ΔSLP changes of about 300 Pa/K (24–28 Pa per 1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> TSI associated with about 0.08 K per 1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) between solar maximum and minimum, which are considerably larger than the observed century-long ΔSLP trends (50–100 Pa/K scaled to the global-mean SST warming) (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>, 
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>). Reasons for reduced sensitivity in the case of GHG forcing are likely to be found in the pattern of SST response in the Pacific, which is ill constrained in observations and/or cancellation from opposing mechanisms that may not be as effective on the 11-y SC timescale. For example, a long-term adjustment of the thermocline to GHG forcing has been found to reduce the effectiveness of the Bjerknes feedback (
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>), while our analysis, instead, highlights the importance of this feedback in reinforcing wind and SST anomalies and ultimately the PWC reduction. In summary, we propose a bottom-up pathway by which the SC influence in global hydrology induces weak westerly surface wind anomalies which are then amplified by the Bjerknes ocean–atmosphere feedback (and possibly also a wind–evaporation–SST feedback), leading to the further reduction and eastward shift of the PWC, positive SSTs, and more rainfall in the equatorial Pacific. This study suggests that SC forcing is an appreciable source of decadal variability in the Indo-Pacific and further studies are required to assess the potential to improve decadal predictability in this region.
 </p>
</sec>
