<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weakening of the Walker Circulation</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first isolate spatially coherent patterns of annual-averaged tropical (30°S–30°N) SLP anomalies in the Indian and Pacific basins. Although the HadSLP2r dataset (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>) spans the whole 20th century, we focus on the second half of the 20th century (1950–2013), for improved data quality, at the expense of a reduced sample length. The spatial pattern of the solar SLP regression coefficients (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>) at lag +1 y has positive anomalies over the maritime continent and negative anomalies in the central and eastern Pacific, the latter demonstrating a chance probability of 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1 according to the Cochrane–Orcutt method. This pattern, which indicates an overall relaxation of the climatological zonal SLP gradient, remains robust even over the whole period 1900–2013 or under different configurations of the MLR model (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>) and is present in individual seasons (
  <a rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" href="#r13">13</a>). The ΔSLP difference between the equatorial (5°S–5°N) Indian/West Pacific (160°–80°W) and East Pacific (80°–160°E) (boxes in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>), which serves as a proxy of the PWC strength (
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>), has a positive loading (24–28 Pa for a typical SC) both over 1900–2013 (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1) and 1950–2013 (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S2
  </span>). This means that the climatological ΔSLP gradient slackens by about 13% from Smin to Smax, a response about an order of magnitude weaker than the reduction during typical El Niño events.
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" fig-type="featured" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(
    <span class="italic">Top Row</span>) SC regression coefficients of (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) SLP with 10-m surface winds imposed as arrows, (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) precipitation, and (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) SSTs averaged over 5°S–5°N. The SLP surface winds and precipitation patterns are shown at +1 y time lag; SC signals in SSTs are shown as a Hovmøller plot of lead/lagged (±5 y, positive lag indicates a response that lags the SC). Units are Pa, ms
    <span class="sup">−1</span>, mm/d, and K per 1-W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span> increase in TSI, respectively. SLP data from HadSLP2r, surface wind data from WASwind, precipitation data from GPCC, SSTs from Kaplan, all datasets from 1950 onward. Hatched areas indicate chance probability 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1. Following rows indicate the corresponding signals from the ensemble average of the AMIP (
    <span class="italic">D</span>–
    <span class="italic">F</span>), SOLAR(
    <span class="italic">G</span>–
    <span class="italic">I</span>), and AMIP-ZM (
    <span class="italic">J</span>–
    <span class="italic">L</span>) simulations.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra1" xlink:href="pnas.1815060116fig01" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive ΔSLP anomalies imply weakened surface easterlies and this is evident in the wave- and anemometer-based sea surface wind (WASWind) surface wind observations from 1950 to 2011 (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>), which show westerly wind anomalies of 0.7–1.2 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span> over the western and central Pacific (arrows in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>), with a Pacific-basin–wide (120°E–70°W, 5°S–5°N) mean reduction of ∼0.1 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.3). To study the vertical structure of the wind anomalies and in the absence of dense direct observations, we analyze equatorial zonal winds in a multireanalysis composite [mean of NOAA-CIRES 20th century (20CR), ERA 20th century (ERA20), NCEP/NCAR reanalysis (NCEP)] over the common period 1950–2010, but we note that similar signatures are found over the full 20th century (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S3
  </span>). Despite some differences among the reanalyses, a statistically significant reduction of climatological equatorial easterlies is evident in the central Pacific, penetrating high into the troposphere up to ∼400 hPa, with anomalies exceeding 1 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span> at 800 hPa (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>). The dipole of positive/negative wind anomalies straddling the climatological westerlies in the upper troposphere (e.g., 200 hPa, 180°–60°W) indicates an eastward displacement of the ascending branch of the PWC toward the central Pacific.
 </p>
 <div id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>SC regression coefficients of equatorial zonal winds for (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) the multireanalysis mean of 20CR, ERA20, and NCEP, (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) AMIP ensemble mean, (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) SOLAR ensemble mean, and (
    <span class="italic">D</span>) AMIP-ZM ensemble mean. Hatched areas indicate chance significance 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1. Contour lines show the zonal wind climatology. Units in ms
    <span class="sup">−1</span> per 1-W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span> increase in TSI. Signals refer to +1-y time lag. (
    <span class="italic">E</span> and 
    <span class="italic">F</span>) MSSA filtered equatorial zonal winds (ms
    <span class="sup">−1</span>) in the multireanalysis mean composite (1950–2010) and SOLAR, respectively, averaged over 800 hPa and 140°E–160°W (marked in 
    <span class="italic">A</span> and 
    <span class="italic">C</span>). TSI variability (gray, normalized) is superimposed for reference.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra2" xlink:href="pnas.1815060116fig02" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To validate these MLR results, we analyze time series of zonal wind anomalies averaged over the equatorial western and central Pacific troposphere (800 hPa, 140°E–160°W, black line in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>) using a multichannel singular spectrum analysis approach (MSSA) that identifies quasiperiodic oscillations (
  <a rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" href="#r19">19</a>). The MSSA (nine channels with 15-y window) isolates an 11.9-y quasiperiodic oscillation that tracks TSI variations throughout the analyzed period with a correlation coefficient of 0.74 peaking at 1–2-y lag (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). The amplitude of the detected decadal oscillation in this region exceeds 1 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, consistent with the MLR signal, with prevalent westerly anomalies in Smax reversing to easterly anomalies during Smin years.
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparison of SC regression coefficients (percentage changes) of global-mean precipitation (circles) and WVC (squares) against the respective global-mean surface temperature change. Units in percent and K per 1-W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span> increase in TSI, respectively. Open circles and squares mark individual ensemble members of the SOLAR, AMIP, and AMIP-ZM simulations. All signals refer to +1-y time lag. Gray lines indicate sensitivities to SC inferred in the CMIP5 20th century simulations (
    <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1815060116fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A weaker and eastward-shifted PWC at Smax results in an eastward migration of atmospheric convection and precipitation maxima toward the central Pacific as evident in the Global Precipitation Climatology Centre (GPCC) precipitation dataset (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>) over the period 1950–2013 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). Despite the limited spatial coverage of GPCC in the Pacific, the detected pattern is robust and is supported by the reanalyses and the independent GPCP v.2.3 global precipitation dataset (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S4
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed signals in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Figs. 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a> refer to 1 y after Smax (lag +1 y), when the strongest ΔSLP anomalies are detected in HadSLP2r and the reanalyses (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5
  </span>). This time lag is similar to that identified in previous studies (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>, 
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>) and indeed our MLR analysis of the Kaplan SSTs over the period 1950–2013 (
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>) detects a significant SST warming of more than 0.4 K over the equatorial Pacific that maximizes at 1-y time lag (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). The spatial pattern of these SST anomalies is characterized by a stronger loading over the central Pacific and overall warming over the Indian Ocean, as shown in earlier MLR analyses (
  <a rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" href="#r13">13</a>, 
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" href="#r20">20</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In line with other studies, we propose that the observed SLP, wind, and precipitation anomalies are all associated with this SST warming. To highlight the bottom-up contribution of SSTs, we perform a six-member ensemble of an atmosphere-only global climate model for 1950–2013 (33 SCs) forced only at the surface boundary by time-varying SST and sea-ice concentration observations (AMIP ensemble, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>), while deliberately keeping the solar irradiance and all other forcings constant. The SLP regression coefficients show good agreement with the HadSLP2r at lag +1 y, and significant positive/negative SLP anomalies are simulated over the Indian Ocean/West Pacific and the East Pacific, respectively, resulting in a positive ensemble mean ΔSLP of +41 Pa at Smax (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S2 and S5
  </span>). Westerly surface wind anomalies (&gt;1 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) are simulated between 150° and 170°W that extend up to 400 hPa into the equatorial troposphere in all individual AMIP runs, although the ensemble mean westerly anomalies are narrower than in reanalyses with an overall stronger magnitude (1.5 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span> at 800 hPa), likely explained by differences in the extent and position of the climatological PWC (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S6
  </span>). Consistent with precipitation observations, the upward branch of the PWC shifts eastward bringing significantly more rainfall (&gt;2.5 mm d
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) toward the central Pacific (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the AMIP ensemble underlines the role of SST anomalies, this is insufficient evidence for the role of SC forcing on the PWC. Although the null hypothesis, that the observed responses simply reflect internally generated decadal variability, can be rejected in statistical terms with probability &lt;0.1, the MLR analysis alone cannot establish causal linkages between SC forcing and warmer SSTs/weakened PWC per se. In fact, the detected patterns in tropical PWC, SSTs, and precipitation share common features with modes associated with internal Pacific variability (
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>), implying a possible signal contamination. To demonstrate a physical linkage to SC forcing, we perform a four-member, 100-y ensemble (∼40 SCs) using a coupled atmosphere–ocean model forced only by repeating the solar cycle 22 (1986–1996) variation in solar spectral irradiance (SOLAR ensemble, 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s5" href="#s5">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased TSI at Smax in the SOLAR results in a widespread warming over the equatorial Pacific, with regression coefficients of up to +0.4 K that maximize at a lag of 1–2 y, in good agreement with the observations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">I</span>
  </a>). The equatorial SLP responds to the positive SST anomalies by increasing over the Indian Ocean/West Pacific and reducing in the East Pacific and the strongest SLP signal is also found at 1–2 y lag (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">G</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5
  </span>). The ensemble mean ΔSLP change of +38 Pa per 1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> increase in TSI is consistent with the observed change of about +24 Pa per 1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S2
  </span>) and indicates a slower PWC. This is confirmed by the westerly surface wind anomalies between 150° and 170°W (0.5 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) that extend throughout the troposphere (0.7 ms
  <span class="sup">−1</span> at 800 hPa) in the western Pacific (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). SOLAR reproduces the pattern of observed zonal wind anomalies over the equatorial Pacific but the model simulates broader easterly anomalies over the Indian Ocean (30°–90°E), associated with overall broader simulated SLP and SST patterns. This is related to a common model bias in simulating tropical Pacific feedbacks, which also affects the SLP, precipitation, and SST responses to ENSO variability on interannual timescales (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S7
  </span>) and is present in many other coupled atmosphere–ocean models (
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). The spread of wind anomalies among individual ensemble members in SOLAR is low and all consistently show a weakened PWC with reduced easterlies in the western Pacific and a dipole of negative/positive anomalies in the upper troposphere (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S8
  </span>). MSSA filtering of the ensemble mean SOLAR zonal winds at 800 hPa over the western and central Pacific identifies a quasiperiodic (∼10.3-y) fluctuation in phase with the specified TSI variability (∼10.5-y period) over 100 model years with a correlation coefficient 0.6 at lag +1 y (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a>). An eastward shift of the upward branch of the PWC in SOLAR brings more rainfall toward the central Pacific (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">H</span>
  </a>), with an amplitude and pattern comparable to the observations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An eastward shift of the PWC following Smax has also been simulated in previous studies (
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>), but as an additional measure to validate our model responses, we identify a similar pattern of westerly wind anomalies at Smax in the Community Earth System Model (CESM) Large Ensemble Project simulations that include all historical forcings (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1815060116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S9
  </span>). In summary, the SOLAR simulations reject the null hypothesis that the PWC response is due to internal decadal variability and instead provide supporting evidence that the observed weakening of the PWC is a genuine response to the increased TSI at solar maximum.
 </p>
</sec>
