<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of tick parasitism</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds that died did not have particularly high tick loads, except for one bird. This suggests that 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> infestations are not associated with (short-term) survival. However, all birds suffered each time from acute blood depletions caused by feeding ticks resulting in reduced haematocrit levels - independent of previous tick exposures
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>. This supports the hypothesis of a lack of resistance to ticks in this songbird species
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. Birds succeeded to compensate, and even over-compensated for the erythrocyte loss. This increase was stronger when the previous tick burdens were higher (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). The latter could be explained by a density-dependent stimulation of host erythropoiesis by molecules secreted by ticks
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a> or via erythrocyte decreases
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>. Interestingly, the leukocyte counts did not change with tick loads. In vertebrate host species that acquire resistance to ticks, these measures increase when exposed
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>. But in our study species, tick infestation success remained high
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>, indicating that the ticks (still) succeeded in circumventing and/or suppressing the birds’ haemostatic processes, inflammatory responses, and the immune counterattacks for preventing blood loss
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">9</a>. A similar observation in which birds tolerate repeated tick exposures, without developing resistance, has been observed in 
  <span class="italic">Turdus migratorius</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the energy losses linked to the tick’s repeated erythrocyte drainage, and the bird’s compensatory processes, the general body condition did not decrease. Instead, in most of the birds, the body condition increased throughout the experiment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>) which was possibly facilitated by the 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food conditions. Even though we performed our experiment in a series of consecutive blocks that started within a short time window (20 days), we cannot fully exclude that seasonal effects play a role here too. The observed increase may also relate to the gain in body mass for the regeneration of feathers (i.e. the post-juvenile moult)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>. Similarly, seasonal changes in agranulocytes have been reported for other wild bird species, which has been interpreted as an indication of a shift toward lymphocyte-based immunity
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. Such temporal or developmental processes have, therefore, to be kept in mind when interpreting the variation in part of the acute response to tick infestation (e.g. ESR, 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t2" href="#t2">Table 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But our experimental manipulation only explores the consequences of interrupted recurrent infestations, while infestations may follow each other more rapidly or even overlap under natural conditions. Thus our results are the outcome of one possible scenario, and it requires additional studies to investigate changes in tick virulence throughout a broader range of scenarios.</p>
</sec>
