<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study is the first to experimentally investigate both cummulative and acute health effects of a parasitic vector and its vector-transmitted pathogens in a wild bird species. Our experiment mimics the natural situation, whereby songbirds are recurrently exposed to 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes</span> ticks and their endemic 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> strains. We focused on the juvenile post-fledging stage, which is the time when tick-borne diseases are more likely to be established for the first time. This is in contrast to most previous studies which investigated the occurrence of tick infestations and 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infections at the time of autumn and spring migration
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">10</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>. This life history stage is of particular interest, due to a low acquired resistance, but also because of the high propensity to disperse and establish new territories
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a> that may lead to the spatial expansion of tick populations and their transmitted pathogens.
 </p>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of tick parasitism</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds that died did not have particularly high tick loads, except for one bird. This suggests that 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> infestations are not associated with (short-term) survival. However, all birds suffered each time from acute blood depletions caused by feeding ticks resulting in reduced haematocrit levels - independent of previous tick exposures
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>. This supports the hypothesis of a lack of resistance to ticks in this songbird species
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. Birds succeeded to compensate, and even over-compensated for the erythrocyte loss. This increase was stronger when the previous tick burdens were higher (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). The latter could be explained by a density-dependent stimulation of host erythropoiesis by molecules secreted by ticks
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a> or via erythrocyte decreases
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>. Interestingly, the leukocyte counts did not change with tick loads. In vertebrate host species that acquire resistance to ticks, these measures increase when exposed
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>. But in our study species, tick infestation success remained high
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>, indicating that the ticks (still) succeeded in circumventing and/or suppressing the birds’ haemostatic processes, inflammatory responses, and the immune counterattacks for preventing blood loss
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">9</a>. A similar observation in which birds tolerate repeated tick exposures, without developing resistance, has been observed in 
   <span class="italic">Turdus migratorius</span>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the energy losses linked to the tick’s repeated erythrocyte drainage, and the bird’s compensatory processes, the general body condition did not decrease. Instead, in most of the birds, the body condition increased throughout the experiment (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>) which was possibly facilitated by the 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food conditions. Even though we performed our experiment in a series of consecutive blocks that started within a short time window (20 days), we cannot fully exclude that seasonal effects play a role here too. The observed increase may also relate to the gain in body mass for the regeneration of feathers (i.e. the post-juvenile moult)
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>. Similarly, seasonal changes in agranulocytes have been reported for other wild bird species, which has been interpreted as an indication of a shift toward lymphocyte-based immunity
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. Such temporal or developmental processes have, therefore, to be kept in mind when interpreting the variation in part of the acute response to tick infestation (e.g. ESR, 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="t2" href="#t2">Table 2</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But our experimental manipulation only explores the consequences of interrupted recurrent infestations, while infestations may follow each other more rapidly or even overlap under natural conditions. Thus our results are the outcome of one possible scenario, and it requires additional studies to investigate changes in tick virulence throughout a broader range of scenarios.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection and their interaction with tick parasitism
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the above mentioned seasonal changes in among others body condition, we found that this increase correlated with the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection rate. This is highly interesting, since such an increase contrasts with the substantial nutritional and energetic costs that are required to trigger and maintain an inflammatory response
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>. Birds may possibly anticipate the costs of an activation of the immune system due to ongoing, non-cleared 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infections. From the pathogen perspective, 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes could proliferate more successfully in those birds with a stronger body mass increase and it is conceivable that they may even induce such metabolic processes (cf. 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> stimulating fat decompositions in 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>). When considering the effects of a 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection on the songbird’s immune system, we found an interactive effect on the NOx levels between 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection and the tick loads during previous infestations. NOx has signaling functions in the cascade of an immune response and may also act as a direct non-specific cytotoxin
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>. Here, NOx levels decreased with tick infestation levels, but this change was counteracted by the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection rate (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>). The decrease of NOx with tick loads can most likely be explained by the immuno-suppressive effects of molecules secreted by the tick saliva
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">40</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a>. This may ultimately also facilitate the proliferation of vector-borne diseases
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>. A stimulation of NOx production by 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infections as shown here, has also been observed in mammals
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>, where the signal function of NOx plays a significant role in the processes that aim at eliminating 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes via macrophages
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">45</a>. Interestingly, the acute NOx response against the final tick exposure was lower when the previous 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection rate (and hence NOx level) was already high (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>). This association suggests a physiological upper limit in the immune reaction, possibly due to a high immune-pathological cost. It could however also indicate that those birds that had already elevated NOx levels because of an ongoing 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> infection, were more effective in eradicating additionally introduced bacteria of infestation 3, and hence show a smaller NOx increase. The outcome may also suggest an acquired immune response against 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span>, which would probably be associated with the downregulation of effectors such as NOx. Identifying the specific immunological pathways in birds against tick-
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> exposures requires further research. The NOx association in great tits indicates that competent reservoirs, which are expected to carry infections without showing signs of disease
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">46</a>, may still present measurable symptoms of infection. Nevertheless, the effects of the bacteria on health and mortality in great tits seem to be low, which is in line with findings in other infected native
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">10</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">16</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">48</a> and domesticated birds
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">49</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">50</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for tick exposures and 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> transmissions
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pathogen infections may alter host physiology and behaviour in a way that positively influences transmission
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">51</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">53</a>, and compensatory processes such as those observed in this study may belong to this category. They probably increase the nutritional needs, hence foraging efforts, that ultimately enhance the encounter rates with uninfected ticks, hereby increasing the transmission and reproduction of the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes. This effect may become reinforced if the higher demand pushes the juveniles to forage in sub-optimal habitat, the lower vegetation strata, entailing a higher tick infestation risk. Indeed, brood-rearing great tits had more severe tick burdens when raising larger broods with higher food requirements
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>. On the other hand, the higher haematocrit levels (reflecting elevated capacity of oxygen consumption) and body mass (reflecting higher energy reserves), both enable hosts to be more active, have larger home ranges and possibly to investigate a greater proportion of the space within their home range, again increasing the chances of encountering ticks
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">54</a>
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">55</a>. Studying whether and to what extent the observed physiological effects alter the bird’s susceptibility to future tick infestations seems, therefore, to be a promising line for future research.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study contributes to our understanding of the virulence of the parasitic actors in a common tick-pathogen system in a native resident songbird reservoir. The outcome can be regarded as an indication of tolerance rather than resistance to the vector and its vector-borne disease, with tolerance being defined as mechanisms reducing the impact of the parasite on the host rather than preventing the exploitation by and proliferation of the parasites
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">56</a>. Repeated parasite exposures led to an overcompensation in health measures, which in the end may benefit the fitness of both ticks and 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes. Furthermore, repeated tick exposures not only increase the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> transmission occasions, but while attached to the bird, ticks also suppress the bird’s immune response, potentially enhancing the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> proliferations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, taken together juvenile great tits act as potent 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> reservoirs during the period of post-fledging dispersal, with subtle clinical symptoms of infections. This probably facilitates subsequent transmission, and will have a significant impact on the spatial distribution of 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> and its vector. As a next step, it needs to be shown whether similar effects can be observed for adult birds with maturated immune systems and other species. Furthermore, infestations may often overlap or may cover longer time periods. The consequences of these patterns have, as yet, to be studied.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
