<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for tick exposures and 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> transmissions
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pathogen infections may alter host physiology and behaviour in a way that positively influences transmission
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">51</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">52</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">53</a>, and compensatory processes such as those observed in this study may belong to this category. They probably increase the nutritional needs, hence foraging efforts, that ultimately enhance the encounter rates with uninfected ticks, hereby increasing the transmission and reproduction of the 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes. This effect may become reinforced if the higher demand pushes the juveniles to forage in sub-optimal habitat, the lower vegetation strata, entailing a higher tick infestation risk. Indeed, brood-rearing great tits had more severe tick burdens when raising larger broods with higher food requirements
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>. On the other hand, the higher haematocrit levels (reflecting elevated capacity of oxygen consumption) and body mass (reflecting higher energy reserves), both enable hosts to be more active, have larger home ranges and possibly to investigate a greater proportion of the space within their home range, again increasing the chances of encountering ticks
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">54</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">55</a>. Studying whether and to what extent the observed physiological effects alter the bird’s susceptibility to future tick infestations seems, therefore, to be a promising line for future research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study contributes to our understanding of the virulence of the parasitic actors in a common tick-pathogen system in a native resident songbird reservoir. The outcome can be regarded as an indication of tolerance rather than resistance to the vector and its vector-borne disease, with tolerance being defined as mechanisms reducing the impact of the parasite on the host rather than preventing the exploitation by and proliferation of the parasites
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">56</a>. Repeated parasite exposures led to an overcompensation in health measures, which in the end may benefit the fitness of both ticks and 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> spirochetes. Furthermore, repeated tick exposures not only increase the 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> transmission occasions, but while attached to the bird, ticks also suppress the bird’s immune response, potentially enhancing the 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> proliferations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus, taken together juvenile great tits act as potent 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> reservoirs during the period of post-fledging dispersal, with subtle clinical symptoms of infections. This probably facilitates subsequent transmission, and will have a significant impact on the spatial distribution of 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> and its vector. As a next step, it needs to be shown whether similar effects can be observed for adult birds with maturated immune systems and other species. Furthermore, infestations may often overlap or may cover longer time periods. The consequences of these patterns have, as yet, to be studied.
 </p>
</sec>
