<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of tree phenotype</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate whether tree phenotypic traits were good predictors of variation in gall abundance, GLMMs were used to model counts of individual gall types with 
  <span class="italic">DBH</span> (growth), 
  <span class="italic">Form</span> (tree health) or 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span> (spring phenology) as fixed effects. While the influences of tree growth and health on gall abundance are expected to be linear, the local adaptation hypothesis for herbivores predicts that the influence of phenology will be curvilinear, with lower gall abundance on provenances that show budburst either before or after local oaks. The fixed effect 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span> was therefore fitted as both untransformed and squared terms. To account for potential differences in abundance levels between the two study years, a factor 
  <span class="italic">year</span> was fitted as a fixed effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each gall type, counts per shoot were initially modelled with 
  <span class="italic">year</span> and either 
  <span class="italic">Form</span>, 
  <span class="italic">DBH</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span> or both 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> as fixed effects. The severity of co-linearity between these variables was assessed by their variance inflation factors (VIFs) using the 
  <span class="sc">r</span> package 
  <span class="italic">HH</span> version 2.3-23 (Heiberger 
  <a rid="b38" ref-type="bibr" href="#b38">2013</a>). To assess the importance of interactions between tree phenotypic traits, a model containing the fixed main effects 
  <span class="italic">Form</span>, 
  <span class="italic">DBH</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Budburst</span>, and their three pairwise interactions was fitted for each gall type. All models were fitted in the MCMCglmm package with the random effect structures and prior specifications described above. The probability that the posterior distribution of the fixed effect coefficients did not include zero (pMCMC) was used to assess the predictive capacity of the fixed effects.
 </p>
</sec>
