<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Influences of oak provenance on the gallwasp guild, and incorporation of provenance covariance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results show that oak provenances vary significantly in phenotypic traits likely to influence associated herbivores and that this in turn is associated with significant variation in the population density (abundance per oak shoot) of multiple gallwasp species. We show that the form of these relationships is robust across models that assume very different patterns of variance–covariance among oak provenances, from identity models assuming total independence to models that estimate covariance based on population genetic and provenance origin data. Our results indicate that models that treat provenances as statistically independent entities, which we know not to be true, consistently underestimate provenance effects on gall densities relative to models in which covariance is specified based on a measure of genetic differentiation (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub> or 
  <span class="italic">GeoF</span>
  <sub>ST</sub>). If these models accurately describe provenance co-variance, then the influence of tree provenance on gall abundance is substantially greater (38–95%) than would be inferred by assuming provenances to be statistically independent. While pairwise 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub> and related measures are consistently significantly larger than 0 (Tables S2.1 and S2.3 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2" href="#sd2">Data S2</a>), their absolute values are small, providing little resolution of the relationship of genetic differentiation and geographic distance (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2" href="#sd2">Data S2</a> for a comprehensive discussion). It is therefore difficult to estimate a ‘true’ value for the impact of provenance and its explanatory power given the nonindependence of populations (Felsenstein 
  <a rid="b200" ref-type="bibr" href="#b200">2002</a>; Stone et al. 
  <a rid="b76" ref-type="bibr" href="#b76">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strong provenance effects we show are consistent with the growing body of community genetics work linking host plant genotypic variation to associated trophic levels (Wimp et al. 
  <a rid="b92" ref-type="bibr" href="#b92">2005</a>; Bangert and Whitham 
  <a rid="b7" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7">2007</a>). A key challenge in this field is to understand the importance of host genetic effects for herbivore communities relative to other ecological factors (Hersch-Green et al. 
  <a rid="b39" ref-type="bibr" href="#b39">2011</a>). Working near the northern limit of pedunculate oak (
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>) in Finland, Tack et al. (
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>) found spatial effects to be more important than tree genotypic effects in structuring a community of herbivorous insects that included several gallwasps. In reciprocal transplant experiments at local and regional scales, Tack et al. (
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>) found no effect of tree genotype for any of the three gall types in their study (asexual and sexual generations of 
  <span class="italic">N. quercusbaccarum</span> are shared with our study). The contrast between this and the strong host plant provenance effects present at the Petite Charnie trial is likely to reflect contrasting levels of adaptive genetic and phenotypic diversity of the oaks in each study. Although Finnish oak populations show substantial intraspecific genetic diversity (Vakkari et al. 
  <a rid="b80" ref-type="bibr" href="#b80">2006</a>), they show substantially less genetic diversity (and we expect also phenotypic diversity) than the much wider geographic array of provenances present at La Petite Charnie (Petit et al. 
  <a rid="b61" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61">2002</a>). Our provenance trial study involves a much greater array of genetic diversity than would be expected from a single natural population, a feature shared with the studies of genetically diverse hybrid populations (e.g., Dungey et al. 
  <a rid="b22" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22">2000</a>) that often show strong plant genotype effects on associated herbivores (Tack et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). Generally, the importance of host genetic effects relative to other factors is likely to correlate positively with the adaptive genetic diversity within a tree population present at a site, and we would expect this to be increased in situations where climate matching or other forms of assisted migration are implemented.
 </p>
</sec>
