<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oak provenance effects on gall abundance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage of variance in gall abundance per shoot explained by differences between provenances (expressed as the mean variance component, ranging between 0% and 100%) varied substantially between the statistical models used. In identity models of the 20 provenance dataset (which assume provenances to be fully independent statistically), the percentage of variance in gall abundance explained by provenance ranged from 3% (in sexual generation 
  <span class="italic">Neuroterus albipes</span>) to 33% (in asexual generation 
  <span class="italic">Neuroterus quercusbaccarum</span>) and was &gt;10% for seven of the 14 gall types (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). Because provenances are related, the identity model is unlikely to be appropriate. All models incorporating provenance covariance gave higher estimates of the variance component for provenance effects (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1" href="#sd1">Data S2</a> for comparison of results across the alternative datasets and models). Incorporation of provenance covariance using the 1−
  <span class="italic">GeoF</span>
  <sub>ST</sub> covariance matrix for the same 20 provenance dataset attributes between 38% (sexual generation 
  <span class="italic">N. albipes</span> and 95% (asexual generation 
  <span class="italic">N. quercusbaccarum</span>) of variance in gall abundance to provenance effects (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). The identity models should thus be viewed as providing artificially low estimates of the variation in gall abundance attributable to differences between provenances (Table S2.2, Figure S2.1 in Data S2). On this basis, host tree provenance is an important predictor of the abundance of many gallers, explaining at least 10%, and as much as 95% of the variation in abundance of seven of the 14 gall types tested. Without more knowledge of the form of variance–covariance relationship, it is not possible to give a correct estimate. Importantly for what follows, analysis of fixed effects was not influenced by our choice of variance–covariance model.
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The proportion of variation in gall abundance attributed to the effect of provenance for the 20-provenance dataset that either do not (black circles) account for population nonindependence (i.e., identity models) or incorporate a 1−
    <span class="italic">GeoF</span>
    <sub>ST</sub> variance–covariance matrix (open circles). Vertical bars represent 95% confidence intervals for each mean.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="eva0008-0972-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
