<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicting the impact of climate-matched planting on associated herbivores</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate matching necessarily requires introduction of phenotypically divergent tree populations. In Europe, climate models predict warmer summers and winters (Giorgi and Coppola 
  <a rid="b29" ref-type="bibr" href="#b29">2009</a>; Jenkins et al. 
  <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">2009</a>), and climate matching will thus always involve introducing more southerly provenances that show earlier budburst (Ducousso et al. 
  <a rid="b21" ref-type="bibr" href="#b21">1996</a>; Broadmeadow et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2005</a>). Under low and high emissions scenarios for 2050, Broadmeadow et al. (
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2005</a>) identified climate-matched sites for five UK locations that were 0–2° and 5–12° further south, respectively (Broadmeadow et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2005</a>). Our results (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2C</a>) suggest that while the small latitudinal shifts required under a low emission scenario would probably have little impact on oak phenology, the shifts of &gt;10° of latitude required under a high emission scenario could lead to major phenological differences between native and climate-matched trees, and significantly dissimilar gallwasp assemblages.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The widespread existence of latitude-dependent photoperiod cues in plant phenology (Aitken et al. 
  <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">2008</a>) suggests that the phenological contrasts between climate-matched and native oak populations will be shared by other plant species. The extent to which any such differences influence associated herbivores is likely to vary according to specific plant–herbivore interactions, reflecting available herbivore phenotypic plasticity and adaptive genetic diversity. We hypothesized that impacts of phenological mismatch will be greatest for interactions in which herbivore fitness is strongly correlated with successful exploitation of a narrow phenological ‘window of opportunity’ (Durant et al. 
  <a rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23">2007</a>; Van Asch and Visser 
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2007</a>; Forkner et al. 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">2008</a>; Netherer and Schopf 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">2010</a>). This includes many insects that feed on newly flushed leaves (Van Asch and Visser 
  <a rid="b81" ref-type="bibr" href="#b81">2007</a>; Forkner et al. 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">2008</a>). However, we found no evidence of such a window for gallwasps: while they prefer to oviposit (or survive better on) young tissues, they show no strong preference for host trees at a single phenological stage. As discussed above, impacts on herbivores with multivoltine or multihost lifecycles may be complex.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationships we found between host plant vigour and herbivore abundance are relevant to two stages in a climate matching strategy: the expected poor performance under current climates of introduced provenances matched to predicted future conditions, and the expected decline in the performance of native provenances as climates move away from any locally adapted range. The slope of the relationship between environmental variables and vigour for a specific provenance will dictate not only the impact on associated trophic levels, but also whether climate matching with that provenance is feasible at all. The challenge for forest managers is to identify a climate-matched provenance that is able to survive as a sapling and young tree before the conditions justifying its selection have been reached and become established before native provenances fail. Climate matching is a recently developed strategy and its success at maintaining forest productivity is untested (Broadmeadow et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2005</a>). Current guidelines in UK forestry advocate mixed planting of both matched and local provenances, which increases local resource heterogeneity for herbivores (Hubert and Cottrell 
  <a rid="b41" ref-type="bibr" href="#b41">2007</a>), and creates conditions that accelerate both environmental selection on host trees (Lefevre et al. 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">2014</a>) and host plant-mediated selection on associated organisms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assisted migration is increasingly seen as a viable strategy for commercial and conservation settings (Broadmeadow et al. 
  <a rid="b14" ref-type="bibr" href="#b14">2005</a>; Stone 
  <a rid="b73" ref-type="bibr" href="#b73">2010</a>; Dawson et al. 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">2011</a>). Issues cited as slowing down the implementation of climate matching as an adaptive forestry strategy include lack of operating procedures, uncertainties over which climate models to use in matching algorithms and risks associated with moving plants outside their current ranges (Williams and Dumroese 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">2013</a>). Theoretical studies nevertheless suggest that such adaptive-, rather than resilience-targeted strategies may be the best way to safeguard forest systems (Buma and Wessman 
  <a rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15">2013</a>; Lefevre et al. 
  <a rid="b47" ref-type="bibr" href="#b47">2014</a>). We would add that the community impacts of assisted migration need to be carefully considered, particularly so for foundation species such as forest trees. This requires better understanding of the relative contributions of host plant genotype and other ecological factors to the tree phenotypes exposed to herbivores (Tack et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). Geographical patterns of local adaptation and tree phenotypic variation have only been mapped in a tiny minority of species (Savolainen et al. 
  <a rid="b66" ref-type="bibr" href="#b66">2007</a>; Robakowski et al. 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2012</a>; Sork et al. 
  <a rid="b71" ref-type="bibr" href="#b71">2013</a>), and studies that target multiple provenance trial locations are required to separate genetic and environmental contributions to provenance phenotypes (Tack et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). While our study was based on a single trial, the oak phenotypic traits we analysed have been shown to be highly heritable in the sampled provenances (Sinclair 
  <a rid="b900" ref-type="bibr" href="#b900">2012</a>), so we expect the provenance effects we found to contain a significant genetic component. Given strong environmental effects on plant traits including phenology, repetition of the work in an array of trials spanning different environments is clearly desirable. Understanding herbivore numerical and adaptive responses then in turn requires understanding the impacts of both plant phenotypes and other ecological processes, including the mortality inflicted on herbivores by their natural enemies (Bidart-Bouzat and Imeh-Nathaniel 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">2008</a>; Thomson et al. 
  <a rid="b79" ref-type="bibr" href="#b79">2010</a>; Van Asch et al. 
  <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2012</a>; Rasmann et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2014</a>). Much more needs to be done before forest managers can take informed decisions concerning likely impacts of climate matching on forest-associated biodiversity.
 </p>
</sec>
