<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A great deal of the academic literature that addresses climate-migration is based on traditional migration theory, which puts forward that drivers of migration can be broken into five broad categories. These include factors that promote out-migration (including the environment, political instability, conflict, lack of economic opportunity, 
 <italic class="italic">etc.</italic>); factors that draw in-migrants (including economic opportunity, demand for resources, political stability, 
 <italic class="italic">etc.</italic>); “network” factors, which facilitate or hinder the move between the two places (including family ties, ease of transport, legality of migration, 
 <italic class="italic">etc.</italic>); national policies that hinder or encourage movement; and the personal goals or motivations of the migrant [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Fundamental to the theory of climate-migration is the postulate that changes in the environment can serve as a potential contextual driver that will encourage individuals to leave their homes as environmental stresses make living in one place no longer feasible or desirable [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. However, these factors and their interactions are highly complex, poorly understood, and context specific. Because of the variety of different reasons for migration, it is often difficult to isolate any one driver as necessary or sufficient. For example, land degradation might negatively impact economic opportunity and influence out-migration—in this case, is the driver the environment, or is it lack of economic opportunity? This is one of the key complexities in climate-migration research. A fairly complex model was developed for the 2011 UK Foresight report (2011) that describes how environmental drivers can (along with many other factors) lead to migration [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. This graphic is reproduced below (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-13-00443-f002" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>) in order to illustrate the challenge of determining the relative role of any one of these factors. 
</p>
