<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The purpose of 4FRI is to reestablish forest structure to improve forest health and the resiliency of forests to climate change, fire and other disturbances (U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Other studies have found that large‐scale forest restoration projects are likely to have co‐benefits that include maintaining biodiversity (Hurteau et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), improving water supply (Robles et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), improving insect resistance (Fettig et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, Kolb et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), and increasing soil function (Sánchez Meador et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). This study illustrates that large‐scale forest restorations are also likely to have potential co‐benefits of increased carbon storage, but climate change could diminish the effects of restoration if higher predicted temperatures are realized. We conclude that the 4FRI project will increase potential carbon stores in ponderosa pine forests by reducing tree mortality from severe wildfires and sustaining productivity under adverse climatic conditions. Our results also suggest that carbon increases can result from initial thinning followed by maintenance fires. Prescribed fire is less expensive and easier to implement than thinning and can provide benefits not achieved with thinning alone (North et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>, Hood et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and both are required to achieve the desired results. 4FRI is only one of 16 western U.S. landscapes in which the CFLR program has funded accelerated restoration of dry forests across 1.1 million ha (U.S. Department of Agriculture, Forest Service 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0064" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). However, the scale of the fire risk is much larger: of the estimated 25 million ha of frequent‐fire conifer forests on federal lands in the western United States (Ager et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), fire regimes have been significantly altered and restoration is needed on more than 11 million ha (Menakis et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). All 11 million ha are likely not suitable for mechanical thinning. However, even if only one‐half are suitable and accelerated restoration in those landscapes has similar effects on the carbon cycle as 4FRI, substantial increases in carbon sequestration and stabilization at the sub‐continental scale could be realized. While accelerated forest restoration on its own is unlikely to be a sufficient long‐term response to climate change, carbon stabilization from accelerated restoration would buy time to retain forest cover, understand climate effects and develop management strategies that reduce the loss of forest cover from climate‐induced impacts. Short of enhancing the current CFLR program or developing new programs that address the urgent need to accelerate restoration, this study and others project potentially dramatic changes in forest carbon pools and forest cover in the Western United States.
</p>
