<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="jame20562-sec-0015" class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">Kooperman acknowledges funding from an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship grant (AGS‐1349579). Pritchard acknowledges funding from the NSF grant (AGS‐1419518) and DOE Early Career and SciDac programs grants (DE‐SC0012152 and DE‐SC0012548). Part of this material is based upon work supported by the U.S. DOE Office of Science, Office of Biological and Environmental Research, Climate and Environmental Sciences Division, Regional and Global Climate Modeling Program under award DE‐AC02–05CH11231. CAM development is led by NCAR and supported by the NSF and DOE. SPCAM development was led by CMMAP (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cmmap.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cmmap.org</ext-link>) and funded by the NSF (ATM‐0425247). Current versions of CAM and SPCAM are available for download through the NCAR subversion code repository (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www2.cesm.ucar.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www2.cesm.ucar.edu</ext-link>). The horizontal resolution and perturbed parameter ensemble experiments are based on CAM5 in CESM version 1.2.2. The CCSM4 and SPCCSM4 experiments are based on CCSM version 4.0 (repo tag ccsm4_0_beta45); for access to this earlier version of SPCCSM4 contact Cristiana Stan (
  <email class="email">cstan@gmu.edu</email>). CCSM4 was run at the DOE NCCS/ORNL (DE‐AC05‐00OR22725); SPCCSM4 was run at the DOE NERSC (DE‐AC02–05CH11231), and supported by the DOE RGCM (SC0006722); and CAM5 was run at the DOE NERSC (DE‐AC02–05CH11231). The CCSM4 output (variables: pr and prc, time frequency: daily, experiment: RCP8.5) is available through the CMIP5 archives on the ESG (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/availability.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5/availability.html</ext-link>). The daily SPCCSM4 output is available upon request from Cristiana Stan (monthly SPCCSM4 output is available on the ESG). The CAM5 output (variables PRECT, PRECC, and PRECL, time frequency: daily) from the horizontal‐resolution experiments is available on the NERSC Portal (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://portal.nersc.gov/project/m1949/iliad/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://portal.nersc.gov/project/m1949/iliad/</ext-link>); and the CAM5 output from the perturbed parameter ensemble experiments will also be made available on the NERSC Portal when the full set of simulations are complete and are currently available upon request from Ben Timmermans (
  <email class="email">bwtimmermans@lbl.gov</email>). The GPCP 1DD and TRMM 3B42 data are provided by the NASA GSFC, which develops 1DD as a contribution to GEWEX GPCP and 3B42 as a contribution to TRMM. The GPCP 1DD and TRMM 3B42 data are available from NASA GSFC RSD (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="ftp" xlink:href="ftp://rsd.gsfc.nasa.gov/pub/1dd-v1.2/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ftp://rsd.gsfc.nasa.gov/pub/1dd-v1.2/</ext-link>) and Mirador (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mirador.gsfc.nasa.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://mirador.gsfc.nasa.gov</ext-link>), respectively. The authors thank Cristiana Stan and Li Xu for additional SPCCSM4 output. The authors also thank two anonymous reviewers and the editors of helpful feedback and suggestions.
 </p>
</ack>
