<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">Mathematically, bifurcations in time-independent and periodically forced systems are equivalent
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. However, transitions that are triggered by changes in periodic forcing have not been explicitly included in the concept of climate tipping points which usually build on the simple paradigm of stable equilibria (and their loss of stability at a tipping point)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. This stands in contrast to the fact that the climate system is interspersed with a number of internal and external oscillations that may cause such transitions on a vast range of time scales. This seems plausible because hardly any oscillation remains the same over time. For example, the seasonal cycle of solar insolation varies due to the Earth’s precession, which in turn is modulated by eccentricity. Similarly, the diurnal insolation cycle depends on the seasons, the Earth’s orbital parameters and its rotation rate. Moreover, modes of internal climate variability often have a distinct range of frequencies, and affect ecosystems and other components of the climate system. Besides these naturally occurring phenomena, the human interference with the climate system is another reason why such oscillations might change. For example, a human impact on the amplitude and frequency of ENSO can be expected
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Even the amplitude and timing of the annual cycle can change in many variables when the balance of climate feedbacks shifts under increased greenhouse gas concentrations, for example associated with changes in Arctic cloud cover, or the loss of sea ice
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref> gives a non-exhaustive overview of (quasi-) periodic oscillations and the nonlinear systems they affect. The possibility of tipping points induced by quasi-periodic drivers emerges from a large body of literature on these systems, but is hardly discussed in such process-based studies or in review articles on tipping points.
</p>
