<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par59" class="p">In the longwave part of the cloud-free global energy balance diagram in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>, the surface fluxes consist of the downward longwave clear-sky radiation of 314 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> (Sect. 
 <xref rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" class="xref">5.3</xref>), and the upward longwave clear-sky surface radiation of 398 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>. This latter flux remains essentially the same as in the all-sky diagram (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig" class="xref">14</xref> left), since in the clear-sky we keep the surface and atmospheric properties identical to the all-sky except for the clouds as pointed out earlier, and the emission in the clear-sky thus comes from the surface with the same temperature as the all-sky. For a discussion of the justification of the 398 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> for the all/clear-sky longwave surface upward radiation the reader is referred to Wild et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2015</xref>). To be precise, there would still be a slight difference between the clear-sky and all-sky surface upward longwave radiation even under otherwise identical surface and atmospheric conditions. This is due to the fact the surface upward longwave flux contains not only the longwave emission from the Earth’s surface, but added to this also a small contribution of the upward reflected fraction of downward longwave radiation. This reflection is neglected when the Earth’s surface is assumed to be a perfect blackbody in the longwave, which then absorbs all incident longwave radiation. In reality the Earth’s surface is globally indeed fairly close to a blackbody in the longwave, yet not perfectly, allowing for a few percent of the downward longwave fluxes to be reflected at the surface. However, since the all-sky and clear-sky downward longwave fluxes overall differ globally by only about 28 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref> and following Section below), the difference in the surface reflected longwave flux under clear- and all-sky conditions is less than 1 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>. This slight difference is thus neglected in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig14" ref-type="fig" class="xref">14</xref>, which display identical surface upward longwave fluxes under clear-sky and all-sky conditions. With a surface upward and downward clear-sky longwave radiation of 398 and 314 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>, this results in a best estimate for the surface net longwave clear-sky radiation of − 84 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>. This allows then also the estimation of the atmospheric clear-sky longwave net radiation (longwave atmospheric clear-sky divergence) at − 183 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>, calculated as a residual between the clear-sky outgoing and surface net longwave radiation of − 267 and − 84 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>, respectively. The corresponding value for the atmospheric clear-sky longwave net radiation as derived in CERES-EBAF according to Kato et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2013</xref>) amounts to − 182 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>. Thus, as with the shortwave clear-sky atmospheric absorption, also our estimates for its longwave counterpart closely agree with the corresponding independent CERES-EBAF estimates.
</p>
