<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The objective function of the optimization process is to minimize global agricultural production costs. Because the demand is inelastic, the main decision on how to allocate land for cropping activities is based on production costs and interregional restrictions on trade. In the MAgPIE model, four different types of costs are defined: factor requirements, technological change, land conversion, and transport costs. Factor requirements costs are defined per ton of produced crop type and differentiated between rainfed and irrigated production systems. They represent costs of capital, labor, and intermediate inputs (such as fertilizers and other chemicals) and are implemented on the regional scale using the cost-of-firm Global Trade Analysis Project (GTAP) data (
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">46</italic>
 </xref>). Crop production can be increased in a region by investing in yield-increasing technological change (
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">47</italic>
 </xref>) or by extension of agricultural production into other nonagricultural areas suitable for plant cultivation (figs. S8 and S9). Land conversion from forest and natural vegetation into arable land comes at region-specific costs. Transport costs are calculated from the GTAP database and assure paying for a quantity of goods transported to the market in a unit of time needed to cover the distance. All MAgPIE regions fulfill part of their demand by domestic production, which is founded on regional self-sufficiency ratios. If domestic production does not cover regional demand, goods are imported from regions with excess production. Export shares and self-sufficiency ratios are calculated from the FAOSTAT database (
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">48</italic>
 </xref>) for the initial year (1995). Trade between regions can be liberalized in future time periods by relaxing the trade barrier, and thus allowing for a certain share of goods freely traded, on the basis of regional comparative advantage. In every time step, trade is balanced at the global level (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
