<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The increase in concern about climate change over recent decades has led to the emergence of evidence supporting a relationship between climate and the incidence of diarrhea (
 <xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c33" ref-type="bibr">Pachauri et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c38" ref-type="bibr">Shuman 2010</xref>). In Japan, norovirus and rotavirus are two of the main causes of diarrhea in children (
 <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Thongprachum et al. 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="c40" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Norovirus is a predominant winter virus, showing a marked peak in November and December with continual detection through the month of May. In contrast, rotavirus is most common in February and March (
 <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Thongprachum et al. 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="c40" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). Additionally, several studies conducted in Japan have reported that the overall prevalence of norovirus and rotavirus infection is 13.2–40.7% and 5.0–42.2%, respectively, with the number of detected cases increasing with each winter in Japan (
 <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Thongprachum et al. 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="c40" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>). A recent systematic review and meta-analysis showed a positive association between ambient temperature and all-cause diarrhea and bacterial diarrhea, but no association with viral diarrhea (
 <xref rid="c5" ref-type="bibr">Carlton et al. 2016</xref>). A large-scale modeling study that assessed projections of climate change-related rises in diarrhea based on 5 empirical studies and 19 climate models suggested that climate change will bring increases in the risk of diarrhea. However, this study also found uncertainties related to projections of diarrhea due to climate change (
 <xref rid="c21" ref-type="bibr">Kolstad and Johansson 2011</xref>). Moreover, a systematic analysis of data from the Global Burden of Disease Study removed climate change as a global health risk factor due to insufficient empirical evidence for climate–diarrhea relationships (
 <xref rid="c25" ref-type="bibr">Lim et al. 2012</xref>). These findings suggest that climate change may raise heat-related diarrhea incidence, while concomitantly reducing cold-related diarrhea incidence. Although several studies have reported climate-related mortality due to diarrhea (
 <xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr">World Health Organization 2014</xref>), to our knowledge, no studies have estimated future projections of climate change-related excess morbidity due to diarrhea according to climate change scenarios. Furthermore, the degree to which the anticipated reduction in cold-related diarrhea incidence can counter the rise in heat-related diarrhea incidence remains to be determined. Therefore, a more comprehensive understanding by modeling future projections of climate change-related diarrhea might help to facilitate the development of climate change mitigation and adaptation strategies and public health policies.
</p>
