<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Artificial nest experiment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Artificial shorebird nests comprised four Japanese Quail (
  <span class="italic">Coturnix japonica</span>) eggs supplied by CRO Quail Farms Inc., which were placed in a divot in the ground. Quail eggs mimic the size and colouration of 
  <span class="italic">Calidris</span> shorebird eggs. Survival of artificial and real shorebird nests may differ because of the ability of shorebirds to conceal nests or use distraction displays [
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref040">40</a>], but nevertheless, they have proven to be an effective measure of relative predation risk in several Arctic predation risk experiments [
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref041">41</a>]. Our intent with the experiment was therefore to identify 
  <span class="italic">relative</span> temporal and spatial patterns of risk associated with fluctuations in predator-prey abundance and activity indices rather than absolute levels of predation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the experiment, we placed artificial nests in a stratified-random design, with samples evenly distributed among the six dominant habitat types (Dry Heath, Scrub Willow, Sedge Meadow, Moss Carpet, Intertidal, Gravel Ridge; see [
  <a rid="pone.0221727.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref014">14</a>] for descriptions) within the study plots (Within, Near, Far, Coats Island). We marked the location of each artificial nest with a handheld GPS unit and a tongue depressor stuck in the ground within 10m of the nest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each year, we deployed and monitored artificial nests during two trials each lasting nine days. We considered artificial nests depredated if at least one egg was taken and successful if the clutch remained intact over the nine-day experiment. Artificial nest experiments were conducted from 28 June– 19 July in 2015, and 28 June– 17 July in 2016. This timing corresponds with the mid- to late-incubation periods for shorebirds breeding at these sites.</p>
</sec>
