<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <sec id="sec010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal trends in predator-prey indices and risk of predation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To identify temporal trends in predator-prey abundance and activity indices at East Bay Mainland we regressed each predator-prey index against time. We also used a general linear model to test for effects of yearly goose indices on gull, jaeger, and fox indices using linear and quadratic fits as well as lemming presence (high or low relative to long-term trends) and an interaction between both.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We related observational predator-prey abundance and activity indices to risk of predation of real shorebird nests over the 13 years (2004–2016) of monitoring at East Bay Mainland that we collected all predator-prey indices, using generalized mixed effects models with a binomial distribution and a logit-link function. Due to the interrelated nature of predator-prey systems, we hypothesised 
   <span class="italic">a priori</span> that the relationships between predictors would be complex. Consequently, we modeled unanticipated interactions through a best-subsets model building approach using the R package MuMIn [
   <a rid="pone.0221727.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref042">42</a>]. We considered yearly lemming abundance (Lemm) as high or low, compared to the average (0.25) of long-term trends because of the relatively large variation at the site. Observational abundance and activity indices for arctic fox (Fox), jaeger (Jaeger), and gull (Gull) were included as continuous covariates, and the response variable of shorebird nest predation varied between 0% (survived) and 100% (depredated). We tested models that incorporated combinations of individual and additive effects of each predator/prey species as well as interactions between each predator species and lemming abundance. To account for any unexplained non-predator-prey related indices that may co-vary with time we also tested a model with a single variable of Year. We included shorebird species as a random effect in each model, recognizing the consistent differences in nest survival among species e.g., [
   <a rid="pone.0221727.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref031">31</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0221727.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref043">43</a>]. Following [
   <a rid="pone.0221727.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0221727.ref044">44</a>] we ranked models using Akaike’s information criterion (AIC) and considered models within two AICc of the top model as informative. We also examined the confidence intervals of predictor variables in the top model to determine whether they included zero.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial experiment using camera predator-prey indices</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a general linear model to determine the effect of distance from the goose colony on camera predator indices (response) with plot distance (Within, Near, Far, Coats), predator species (fox, gull, or jaeger), and year (2015 and 2016), and interactions between the three variables as predictors. For the results from the artificial nest experiment we used a generalized linear mixed effects model with a binomial distribution to identify the influence of plot distance from goose colony, year (2015 and 2016), and an interaction between the two on the probability of predation of an artificial nest during the nine-day experiment. In this model we also included trial as a random effect. All statistical analyses were performed in R Version 3.3.1 (R Core Team 2017).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
