<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our main objectives were to determine whether indices of predator abundance and activity responded to temporal and spatial variation in light goose and lemming abundance, and whether these changes affected the predation rates of shorebird nests. To identify temporal changes in the abundance and activity of predators and their prey, we generated group-specific indices (see below) from daily observations (hereafter observational predator-prey indices) at East Bay Mainland from 2000–2016 (We did not collect long-term observational indices at our other study sites). We then used shorebird nest survival at East Bay Mainland from 2004–2016 to relate predator-prey abundance and activity indices to risk of predation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To identify spatial trends in predator abundance and activity, in 2015 and 2016 we generated predator indices using time-lapse cameras (hereafter camera predator indices) placed within the four study plots established at increasing distances from the goose colony. Measuring the spatial patterns in shorebird nest predation was challenging, in that too few shorebird nests were found Within and Near the goose colony for statistical analyses; presumably because of reduced nesting densities and nest survival in these heavily goose-affected areas. Therefore, in 2015 and 2016, we placed artificial nests within each of the four study plots to relate predation risk to spatial variation in camera predator indices. The Animal Care Committee of Environment and Climate Change Canada approved our procedures, and permits were granted from Federal and Territorial Governments (e.g., NUN-SCI-14-05, WL2016-053). No animals were handled during this study and there were no ethical concerns regarding animal welfare. All research was conducted on territorial land and within the East Bay Migratory Birds Sanctuary under permit NUN-MBS-14-05 granted by Environment and Climate Change Canada.</p>
</sec>
