<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A dynamic, multispecies, occupancy model (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>) was used to explicitly model the persistence and colonization dynamics that occurred between the historic and modern time periods. Survey data were assumed to be the result of imperfect observation of the true incidence of a species at a site. Occupancy dynamics were modeled as a first-order Markovian process (i.e., incidence of a species in the modern period was assumed to depend on the incidence state of the historic period). Covariates were included as a linear combination of effects with a logit-link transformation for each of the four probabilities estimated by the model [detection (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>), historic occupancy (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="i5" class="math">
   <mi class="mi">ψ</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>), local persistence (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="i6" class="math">
   <mi class="mi">ϕ</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>), and local colonization (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="i7" class="math">
   <mi class="mi">γ</mi>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>)]. The species-specific intercept and coefficient values were governed by normal distributions, which were in turn drawn from community-level hyperdistributions. The hyperdistributions for the intercept terms and the mean of the coefficients were assigned vague priors. We fit the model with a weakly informative prior applied to the variance of the coefficient hyperdistributions, which behaves as a type of regularization (
 <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>). Regularization limits the effects of collinearity in the covariates and prevents overfitting, allowing us to evaluate a global model of community response (
 <xref rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>). For full model and prior specification, see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1805123115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>
 </ext-link>.
</p>
