<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">The global change in probability of exceeding the historically unprecedented event at three levels of forcing.</title>
  <p class="p">Global-scale cumulative distribution functions (CDFs) are calculated from all bootstrapped return interval ratios at all observationally available grid points for each level of anthropogenic forcing (see Materials and Methods). The horizontal axis is the change in probability calculated as the return interval ratio between the natural and anthropogenic forcing. For example, a ratio of 5 means that, in the anthropogenic forcing, the probability of exceeding the most extreme historically observed value is five times the probability in the world without human influence. The vertical axis is the cumulative fraction of all ratios calculated at all available grid points that are less than or equal to a given ratio. Insets show 1 minus the value on the vertical axis, which gives the fraction of ratios that are greater than a given ratio. For example, if a given CDF curve intersects 5 on the horizontal axis and 0.75 on the vertical axis, then 75% of all calculated return interval ratios are less than or equal to 5, and the inset will show that 25% of all calculated ratios are greater than 5. The dark gray vertical line in each panel shows where the return interval ratio between the natural and anthropogenic forcing is equal to 1, meaning that the probability of exceeding the most extreme historically observed value is equivalent in the natural and anthropogenic forcing. The three levels of anthropogenic forcing are the 1986–2005 period of the Historical simulations (~1500 GT CO
   <sub class="sub">2</sub> emitted and ~1°C of global warming above the pre-industrial), the 2016–2035 period of the RCP8.5 simulations (~2500 GT CO
   <sub class="sub">2</sub> and ~1° to 2°C), and the 2036–2055 period of the RCP8.5 simulations (~3500 GT CO
   <sub class="sub">2</sub> and ~2° to 3°C).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="aao3354-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
