<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results presented in this paper demonstrated the variations in climatic suitability and planting regionalization for the potato in northern China from 1965 to 2014. Over the past 50 years, the comprehensive climatic suitability index during the potato growth season in the study area fluctuated but showed a slight increase overall. This increase would be beneficial to potato production in the vast area of northern China. Specifically, the temperature suitability index and the precipitation suitability index both decreased with at rates of 0.002 and 0.008 every ten years, respectively, and the reduction in the precipitation suitability index (0.006) was greater than that in the temperature suitability index (0.018). However, the light suitability index and comprehensive climatic suitability index exhibited increasing trends, at rates of 0.014 and 0.002 every ten years, respectively. Moreover, the increase in light suitability index (0.035) was greater than that in comprehensive climatic suitability index(0.004) over the past 50 years. For the spatial distribution, the average suitability indexes of temperature, precipitation and comprehensive climate all showed gradually declining trends from the eastern region to the western region, expanding westward and southward from 1965 to 2014. For the growth period, the comprehensive climatic suitability index increased during the sowing-emergence stage. However, it decreased during the emergence-flowering stage and the flowering-maturity stage, which would directly affect the quality and yield of potato, particularly because the flowering-maturity stage was associated with potato tuber enlargement and starch accumulation. The effects of climate change on potato planting regionalization in northern China over the past 50 years were evident. It was particularly noted that climate change was more beneficial to potato cultivation in northeast China, where highly suitable areas had obviously expanded. However, the planting of potatoes was the most negatively affected in northwest China, where middle suitable areas had receded.</p>
