<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The CENTURY model was originally developed for the U.S. Great Plains grassland ecosystem [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] and has been successfully adapted to simulate carbon fluxes under climate change across a wide latitudinal gradient, from tropical to temperate to high-latitude ecosystems [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. A detailed description of the CENTURY model has been presented by [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The observed data for parameterization of the CENTURY model included the nutrient contents in vegetation and soil that were derived from the Haibei research station of the Chinese Ecosystem Research Network (CERN), Chinese Academy of Sciencies. The performance of the CENTURY model on the Tibetan Plateau grassland has been evaluated by the observed net ecosystem exchange (NEE), ecosystem respiration (Re), gross primary production (GPP) (2003 ~ 2005) obtained from the Haibei flux tower observations and aboveground biomass (AGC) (2000 ~ 2012) obtained from the field sampling at Haibei research station [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. In addition, the Re was further separated into autotrophic respiration (Ra) and heterotrophic respiration (Rh) according to the study of [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>], and the net primary production (NPP) was then obtained by subtracting Ra from GPP. The site-level verification from our previous study showed that the parameterized CENTURY model was able to capture the carbon fluxes of alpine grassland (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> &gt; 0.80, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). The simulated monthly AGC exhibited a good agreement with the observed data with the slope close to 1, and the intercept and the root mean square error (RMSE) were less than 25 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup>. Compared to the eddy-covariance flux data, the simulated monthly NPP and Rh were comparable to the observation with slopes equal to 0.77 and 1.10, and the estimated errors of RMSE were 29.06 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> and 13.24 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup>, respectively. The simulated NEE was also agreed well with the field observation (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.88, RMSE = 17.94), while the seasonal amplitude of the simulated NEE was slightly higher than that from the flux tower data with a slope of 0.64) [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. We acknowledged that the model parameterization was dependent on data from Haibei station, which might cause a certain degree of uncertainty. This was due largely to the fact that most of the existed observations on the Plateau were not long-term experiments and lacked necessary information for model calibration. We used NEE observations at Damxung meadow site on Tibetan Plateau to validate the calibrated CENTURY. The simulated NEE at Damxung agreed well with the observational fluxes (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215261.s002" class="xref">S2 Fig</xref>, R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.52, p&lt;0.01). Furthermore, we validated the results with the Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) NPP products (MOD17A3) during 2000–2014 on the regional scale (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215261.s003" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref>). And the simulated NPP by CENTURY model showed a similar trend with MODIS derived NPP. At the regional scale, our previous historical simulated results were comparable to other studies, with a mean NPP and NEP of 259 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> and 10 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> from 1981 to 2010, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], which was within the range of 120 ~ 340 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> and 8 ~ 24 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> reported by [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215261.s004" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). The spin up procedure for the CENTURY model simulation followed the published literature [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>].
</p>
