<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Carl Linnaeus pioneered the study of phenology when he outlined methods for investigating associations between flowering and climate in the 1700s (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Linnaeus, 1751</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Von Linné, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Puppi, 2007</xref>). Around 1850, Charles Morren introduced the term “phenology” to describe his observational studies of yearly flowering (
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morren, 1853</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Demarée &amp; Rutishauser, 2009</xref>). Early field studies of plant phenology have been thoroughly reviewed by 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Schaik, Terborgh &amp; Wright (1993)</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fenner (1998)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Forrest &amp; Miller-rushing (2010)</xref>. Long-term observations in field studies have provided a valuable resource for analyzing phenological responses to recent climate change (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Walther et al., 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Parmesan &amp; Yohe, 2003</xref>). A growing need for historical data that allows for the exploration of ecological implications of climate change prompted researchers to look to herbarium specimens. A few phenology studies such as 
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Borchert (1996)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rivera &amp; Borchert (2001)</xref> used herbarium specimens to study flowering periodicity, but not in the context of climate change. The first study to use herbarium specimens to understand phenological responses to climate change was published in 2004 by 
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Primack et al. (2004)</xref>. 
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Primack et al. (2004)</xref> analyzed 372 specimen records (1885–2002) and found flowering had advanced approximately eight days over the last century. Between 2004 and 2017, more than 30 studies were published using herbarium specimens to examine changes in phenology in response to climate change.
</p>
