<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As Grant et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) stressed with the threat of emerging infectious diseases, effective conservation and management in the face of climatic uncertainty require a proactive framework to reduce risk of future catastrophic storm impacts to vulnerable populations of imperiled species. In its 4th Assessment Report, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change classified adaptation strategies as those consisting of 
 <italic class="italic">protective</italic> actions (those that increase robustness by building species and/or habitat resilience to disturbance events), 
 <italic class="italic">accommodating</italic> options (those that increase flexibility), and 
 <italic class="italic">retreat</italic> options (those that enhance adaptability) (Nicholls et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). For amphibians in coastal wetlands, appropriate protective actions may include (a) minimizing or eliminating landscape features that are conduits for future inundation by plugging ditches and installing water control structures; (b) restoring habitat and maintaining its suitability using prescribed fire and other tools; and (c) engineering protective structures such as sea walls, flood levees, dikes, culverts, and impoundments for flood abatement (Enwright et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Noble et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Examples of accommodating actions include (a) enhancing population resilience (e.g., increasing genetic diversity), (b) increasing connectivity among populations, and (c) acquiring land to allow future managed translocations. Although building resilience is fundamental to future conservation of populations in coastal environments, more active planning and management will likely be needed to protect the most vulnerable coastal environments (Fisk, Haines, &amp; Toki, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Meeting this need may require implementing a range of retreat measures, including assisted migration or managed translocation, establishment of ecological corridors, and ex situ conservation (Fisk et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Noble et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
