<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We observed pika activity at eight sites in GNP from 15 to 24 July, 2009. We chose sites that had relatively high pika densities across a broad range of elevations and slope aspects. We conducted twelve separate 3‐h observations per site during the following intervals: morning (05:15–08:15), midday (13:00–16:00), and evening (19:00–22:00). We conducted observations over a 10‐day span to reduce the effect of seasonality; pikas are more active in late summer when caching food (Smith and Weston 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>). Morning observations commenced ~45 min prior to sunrise and evening observations concluded ~30 min after sunset. We observed pika activity passively from a high vantage point, because pikas pay little attention to quiet observers (Conner 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1983</xref>). Trained observers continuously scanned the talus using the naked eye or 7 × 35 binoculars, and recorded the time of all visual and audible evidence of pika activity. Observers worked in pairs, but recorded data from nonoverlapping areas (~40 m radius) of the same talus patch, assigning pikas temporary ID numbers and sketching maps of their whereabouts to distinguish the activity of individuals (sensu Barash 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1973</xref>). A single pika call or sighting was considered a “unique event”. Additional calls or sightings of the same individual within 30 sec were recorded, but not considered new unique events. In this way, we categorized brief flourishes of activity as single events. We identified the type of observed behavior under the following nonmutually exclusive categories: haying (collecting or carrying vegetation in the mouth), foraging (directly consuming vegetation), moving fast, moving slow, and vigilant (stationary). We assumed that imperfect detection of pikas played a relatively small role in data collection, because pikas are highly detectable (85–95%) and relatively easy to identify for a stationary observer (Beever et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Moyer‐Horner et al. 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
