<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used multiple regression to associate minimum above‐talus temperature (
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>) and two site‐level variables (elevation, 
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>; slope aspect, 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>) with aggregate above‐talus pika activity observations to understand whether field observations were generally congruent with predictions from our biophysical model. We only modeled pika activity with minimum above‐talus temperature because of moderate to high collinearity with other temperature measurements (0.55 &lt; 
 <italic class="italic">r </italic>&lt;
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.99) and because minimum above‐talus temperature best explained variability in pika activity in preliminary analysis (see Table S2). There was no strong collinearity detected among the remaining predictor variables (
 <italic class="italic">r </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.06–0.26). We developed a set of 10 a priori hypotheses relating minimum above‐talus temperature, elevation, and slope aspect to observed pika activity (see Table S3) and evaluated relative empirical support for these hypotheses using AIC
 <sub class="sub">C</sub> (Burnham and Anderson 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). We derived parameter estimates that accounted for model selection uncertainty by performing model averaging among models with &gt;10% AIC weight and without uninformative parameters (Burnham and Anderson 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Arnold 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). We log‐transformed the response variable (per capita pika sightings) to approximate a normal distribution (Ives 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Log‐linear forms of 
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> a</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">t</italic> outperformed linear and quadratic forms in preliminary analysis (see Fig. S1); therefore, we used log‐linear forms of our predictor variables in the final analysis. We fit models and performed model selection using the package ‘AICcmodavg’ (Mazerolle 
 <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) in R version 3.1.1 (R Core Development Team).
</p>
