<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">The second assumption is a straightforwardly normative one—I assume that certain individuals have moral obligations to perform particular actions (or omissions) on grounds that these actions are in some way relevant to the eventual realization of climate harms. This is without question a substantive assumption, since even if one grants that individuals contribute 
 <italic class="italic">causally</italic> to the realization of climate harms, this does not alone settle the normative question about whether we have individual obligations not to. Indeed, Sinnott-Armstrong has argued that there is no plausible moral principle from which it follows that individuals (as opposed to, say, nations) have moral obligations to diminish their carbon footprints (2010) and Johnson has argued that climate change has the structure of a tragedy of the commons and that in that context individuals lack moral obligations to curb their emissions (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2003</xref>).
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3" class="xref">3</xref> Others have argued that individuals do in fact have such obligations. Broome defends the claim that individuals have “duties of justice” to minimize our carbon footprint and to engage in political actions that might result in policy changes that mitigate emissions (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2012</xref>). Cripps argues that we have individual moral obligations to form collectives that are capable of addressing climate change on a larger scale (2013).
 <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn4" class="xref">4</xref> Finally Jamieson (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2007</xref>) and Sandberg (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">2011</xref>) have each argued that individuals should inculcate “green virtues”, which would involve character traits that dispose one to minimize emissions. Along the lines suggested by Hursthouse (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">1998</xref>), one could straightforwardly derive claims about the wrongness of certain individual actions from these virtues. It is obviously beyond my scope to adjudicate this debate, and for the purposes of exploring the question of whether individuals are blameworthy for their easily avoidable emissions, their failure to form collectives that would be able to realise large-scale emissions reductions, or their failure to inculcate green virtues, I will assume that the relevant individual moral obligations have some normative foundation.
</p>
