<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The Svalbard tundra is characterized by a simple food web, with few species. The wild Svalbard reindeer is the only mammalian herbivore, besides a small local population of sibling voles 
 <italic>Microtus levis</italic> (Ims &amp; Ehrich, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The reindeer are largely solitary and virtually free from predation, although rare attacks by polar bears (
 <italic>Ursus maritimus</italic>) on sick or weak reindeer have been observed (Derocher, Wiig, &amp; Bangjord, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). Thus, direct density dependence and large annual variations in weather conditions—notably the amount of ROS, but also the length and warmth of the summer—shape the reindeer's body condition and vital rates (Albon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Solberg et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Stien et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). This, in turn, causes large fluctuations in population abundances from year to year (Albon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Kohler &amp; Aanes, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Solberg et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). There is some evidence of spatial population synchrony (Aanes et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>), most likely explained by spatially autocorrelated fluctuations in weather rather than dispersal, which is strongly restricted by natural barriers such as open sea, glaciers and steep mountains. Genetic analyses also indicate significant population differentiation across very small distances (Côté et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), largely confirming the observation that Svalbard reindeer are resident within annual home ranges of only a few km
 <sup>2</sup> (Tyler &amp; Øritsland, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">1989</xref>). Overall, individuals do not move between neighbouring populations, except under special circumstances, such as following overgrazing or extreme ROS events (Hansen, Aanes, &amp; Sæther, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Loe et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). Combined with the strong climatic signals observed in vital rates (Albon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), the characteristics of this study system provide a rare opportunity to investigate the impacts of climate‐induced environmental change on the population dynamics and trends of a high‐Arctic ungulate, both locally and at a meta‐population scale.
</p>
