<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to set the stage globally and identify the current state of, and gaps in, knowledge to guide future research in this novel arena. Although this is a global review, the issue requires localised research. Therefore, we advocate for a portfolio of case studies with which to inform policy at the local level, while providing broader insights, aiming to:</p>
 <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Identify and map linkages between areas where MNF currently occurs/is expanding and potential driving influences such as prevalence and characteristics of net distribution, estimates of net ‘availability’ and net ‘leakage’, resource management capacity, broad fishery types and gear availability/accessibility. This will require a broad cross-disciplinary approach including data and knowledge sharing.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Empirically assess ecological impacts across the scale of MN use. Studies need to qualify and quantify the direct impacts faced in terms of overexploitation and interactions of indirect impacts such as habitat damage. Predictive modelling coupled with empirical studies would allow us to understand how this might impact fisheries more broadly.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Understand specific drivers of MNF for different user groups at a local level, being mindful of varying vulnerability and the potential for indirect drivers of MNF within coupled socio-ecological systems, particularly emerging market forces.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Determine the level to which MNF has become entrenched as a livelihood and/or subsistence activity within communities and user groups, and therefore the potential difficulties of reducing MNF.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Investigate how MN distribution efforts interact with MNF e.g. is growth in MNF correlated with specific net characteristics; do free vs. subsidised policies have an impact on MNF levels and if so why; does temporal spacing between re-distributions impact MNF and if so why; what effect might net retrieval schemes have?</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Conduct assessments of localised institutional capacity for management, both formal and informal, with a focus on inclusion of vulnerable groups.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Collate and assess examples of interventions which have addressed the drivers of MNF, not merely reduced incidence, such as education and awareness programs, livelihood interventions, integrated gear management efforts.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All of these research strands need to be pulled together to inform a fully collaborative interdisciplinary approach to the issue. The perception data presented here indicate that the drivers of MNF are complex and may be influenced by policy change in both fisheries management and healthcare interventions. Therefore we hope that this research can act as a catalyst for collaboration between the health, fisheries management and conservation sectors. MNF is global, expanding and complex. Whilst strides are made to eradicate malaria, mitigation of unwanted and unforeseen consequences to natural resource sustainability must be of priority to avoid additional harm to developing nations’ fishing communities and indeed potentially negative feedbacks on human health. Additionally, it will be important not to lose sight of the ecosystems and biodiversity at stake, making MNF a conservation issue. Biodiversity conservation strives for a ‘do no harm’ approach to interventions, increasingly seeking to marry development and conservation towards mutual sustainability goals. We would advocate for similar principles being adhered to in antimalarial efforts and in an interdisciplinary approach to this problem, seeking collaborations toward outcomes that minimise social and environmental impacts in pursuit of malaria control.</p>
</sec>
