<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gear characterisation, deployment and users</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of respondents reported that deployment took place on foot (60%, n = 115), but with canoe use also featuring prominently (29%), particularly in W&amp;C Africa. MNF from sail and motorised boats was also reported across all three regions (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191519.s007" href="#pone.0191519.s007">S7 Fig</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four predominant MNF methods were identified from the literature, and clarified further by our survey: Single-net use, with nets largely unaltered and operated by individuals or pairs, dominated across all regions (53%, n = 105), followed by multiple nets sewn together for use by small groups of fishers (34%), then use as a cod end of larger seine nets (10%) and finally just three reports of insecticide fishing, the details of which remain unconfirmed but where in one case additional DDT is thrown in to the water along with the MNs. Numerous other methods were described by survey respondents, including a number of trap designs, ‘scoop’ or ‘dip’ nets, and the use of static ‘set’ nets used to funnel fish, sometimes with photographic evidence (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191519.s007" href="#pone.0191519.s007">S7 Fig</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reported frequency of engagement in MNF varied significantly across demographic groups, with women most commonly reported as engaging in MNF ‘often’, and men, children and the elderly most commonly reported as engaging in MNF ‘sometimes’ (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191519.s005" href="#pone.0191519.s005">S5 Fig</a>, X-squared = 38.94, df = 6, Cramer’s V = 0.27, p = &lt;0.001). Thirty-five percent of observations reported those engaging in MNF locally to be experienced fishers, 43% part time and 21% inexperienced fishers.
 </p>
</sec>
