<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for management</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results support the suggestion that MNF is a highly accessible fishing activity which doesn’t require the skill, knowledge, vessels, opportunity costs or capital investment necessary for other fishing gears. Looking at motivations from a ‘push’ or ‘pull’ perspective, the perceived drivers cited by observers are dominated by pull factors; positive reasons why one would choose to MN fish, and underlying this was the predominant push factor of poverty. The real variation in drivers, important to intervention design, may lie in the user groups. For those users already classified as ‘vulnerable’ or ‘marginalised’, MNF offers an opportunity to reduce this vulnerability. In many traditional artisanal fisheries women play a vital supporting role in processing and sales of fish, and are also involved in gleaning [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref026">26</a>]. However, in many places women are still considered a marginalised and vulnerable group because of cultural norms that limit their access to fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref027">27</a>]. MNF represents a more efficient method for traditional gleaning that could generate higher returns. Our data also suggest that the experience levels of fishers are variable and that occupational multiplicity is common amongst those engaging in MNF. This may be particularly important for traditional farmers and natural resource users driven off their land by climate change or changing land uses and resettlements [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref028">28</a>]. For example, the Giriama in coastal Kenya were settled in Mida Creek as a result of resettlement and took up MNF [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref008">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If MNF becomes increasingly attractive economically, either due to other fisheries declining or development of new markets, this could increase male engagement in cases where MNF is currently deemed ‘women’s work’ (e.g. seaweed farming in Tanzania, at first undertaken predominantly by women, was later dominated by men once its commercial value was deemed sufficient [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref029">29</a>]). Market-based factors such as the ever-growing reach and size of the Chinese Traditional Medicine and animal/aquaculture feed markets may drive these changes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents’ perceptions of reasons not to engage in MNF most commonly alluded to fishers' perceptions of the unsustainability of the practice. These perceptions are of course from people external to the fishery; in reality this motivation is likely to vary widely between user groups depending on an interaction between people’s perceptions, ecological understanding and the degree with which they engage/rely on the wider fishery. Awareness of the health benefits from correct use of MNs is second-most cited and there are examples in the literature of increased awareness-raising impacting levels of alternative MN use [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref030">30</a>]. These efforts are likely to be impacted by overall availability of nets. For example Bush et al., (2016) found that in Mida Creek, Kenya there was unlikely to be a trade-off between malaria prevention and MNF as nets were so readily available.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was not an empirical investigation into the sustainability of MNF. We therefore do not present conclusions on the ecological impacts of MNF, but our findings do give useful preliminary insights to guide future research. The observations of catch composition and juvenile capture do lend us some critical first insights that may support and oppose current concerns, but certainly illustrate the need for further investigation. The diversity of marine MNF catch is likely to be due to the utilisation of habitats such as seagrass beds and mangroves for MNF, which are important nursery grounds for both pelagic and reef-associated species [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref007">7</a>]. The range of families and functional/trophic groups reportedly caught in MNs in the marine environment is of concern for selective fishing management regimes. Some species and/or life history stages targeted are those for which there was limited former demand (e.g. juvenile 
  <span class="italic">Gerres oyena</span>), potentially expanding fishing impacts, but also providing a potentially valuable new resource. Fish also often occupy multiple niches at different life stages. Exploitation of a species at an increasing number of these life stages could be disruptive at the ecosystem level, or may conversely contribute to a more balanced harvest-type scenario with increased overall yields if managed appropriately.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reports of high juvenile capture rates are also of concern in both marine and freshwater environments where conventional management is a goal. Although it is impossible to verify the specific biological knowledge of every respondent, enough respondents were able to identify fish to family or species level, and verify juvenile capture at this scale to warrant investigation. Within the literature this is the biggest concern pertaining to MNF due to the undermining of size-selective management [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref005">5</a>], and the potential for growth and/or recruitment overfishing of stocks that are relied upon by other user groups. However, size-selective management, as well as being generally inappropriate and prohibitively difficult to implement in artisanal scenarios, is no longer the predominant accepted management discourse. Particularly where food security is the biggest concern and where wet weight of protein may be prioritised over rents, balanced harvest is increasingly thought of as a more pragmatic approach to management [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref031">31</a>] and to achieving new goals of ecosystem-based management [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref010">10</a>]. It is worth considering, therefore, the critical importance of understanding the user groups for MNF and their vulnerability alongside empirical assessments of their impacts on a fishery. Strong arguments exist for an underestimated importance of the harvesting of small bodied fish in subsistence communities [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref019">19</a>]. MNF investigations should not disregard a potential synergy with ecosystem-based management goals and benefits posited by balanced harvest theory including increased protein provision and positive contributions to nutrition through micro-nutrients, particularly for children [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref032">32</a>]. Small mesh nets may play an important role in optimising yields (albeit of potentially low-economic value catch by western standards) in a balanced harvest scenario which, coupled with the accessibility of MNF, could contribute in a significant way to social equity and overall food security. Though this consideration of social equity is deeply complicated by the health element of the MNF issue, the distribution of nets for anti-malarial purposes hinging importantly on collective compliance, it will nevertheless be critical to development of effective management interventions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">External to the debate over the direct impacts of MNF on the target fishery resource, however, reports of habitat damage are worrying in fragile habitats such as seagrasses where regular seining and trampling may have long term impacts. Also of concern are emerging market-based drivers, such as the Chinese Traditional Medicine and animal feed examples which are new to some of these areas, wherein external influences are introduced and environmentally and economically destructive behaviours encouraged.</p>
</sec>
