<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Online survey</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An online survey was made available in English and French between 4/6/15 and 14/8/15 using the Qualtrics Survey Software [
  <a rid="pone.0191519.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191519.ref020">20</a>]. Information regarding MNF was requested from anyone living or working within any area of malarial risk, either coastally or close to bodies of water used for fishing at any scale, with a focus on obtaining responses from relevant stakeholders in the fisheries management, public health, conservation and development sectors. By sampling these groups we deemed that relevant and detailed responses would be more likely, detail would be more reliable based on respondent experience and the survey would benefit from snowball distribution to relevant networks. Additionally, we deemed the online survey method to be the fastest and most cost-effective way of obtaining responses. Although this method excludes those without internet access and can suffer limitations in scope and uptake, this sampling strategy and target audience was used to attempt to maximise access (both in terms of internet connection and language), generate good quality data and rapidly glean a global perspective on an issue which is rarely a primary focus of any of these sectors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Qualifying questions on, for example, time the respondent has spent at the location, organisational affiliation and associated role were used to gauge levels of confidence in observations. Two survey options were available: for individuals whose experience was predominantly fisheries/conservation/ecology focused, and for those whose experience was predominantly development/health focused. The latter omitted questions for which a higher level of ecological knowledge was necessary. We requested observations of MNF at the ‘
  <span class="italic">village level</span>’ or equivalent but also accepted were ‘
  <span class="italic">areas of coastline</span>, 
  <span class="italic">river</span>, 
  <span class="italic">lake</span>, 
  <span class="italic">fishing location or region’</span> if later geographically defined. Respondents could provide more than one observation by completing the survey for each location where they had first-hand, personal knowledge of MNF. We solicited both negative and positive observations of MNF in order to reduce positive bias. We included duplicate observations at given locations if additional information significant to the study objectives was provided.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We promoted this survey to relevant respondents through the authors' own networks, relevant mailing lists, newsletters, conference delegate lists and direct targeting of relevant individuals and subsequent networks through internet searches. Social media outlets Facebook and Twitter were utilised extensively with all authors’ affiliated organisations participating and expanding the reach. Every effort was made to ensure geographical representation and to limit potential bias from factors such as prevalence of NGO activity in an area. Whilst negative observations are not conclusive evidence of absence, some confidence is afforded by the general visibility of MNF as an activity. Where deemed necessary and feasible, we contacted respondents directly for additional detail, reports, papers and photographic evidence.</p>
</sec>
