<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40">Fourth, researchers should continue to invest efforts in interventions targeting direct triggers of behaviour change, such as social comparison messages and choice architecture (nudges). Although such interventions have their own set of challenges (e.g., unknown collateral effects of downward social comparisons, or ethical concerns with consent and autonomy in nudge interventions), our results indicate these are the most effective interventions. For instance, choice architecture relies on people preferring the path of least resistance, such as having to walk less to the recycling bin or not giving a second look at the air conditioning temperature. This approach could be implemented in less explored areas. For instance, utilities companies could implement a default (opt-out) payment for renewable energy (e.g. refs. 
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>). Moreover, the layout of cafeterias, restaurants and supermarkets could be rearranged to display animal products in less accessible areas. This is a strategy commonly used in health promotion to reduce consumption of sugary foods, but seldom used to fight climate change. Given the pressing need to change the consumption patterns of millions of individuals and households, interventions should target proximal drivers of behaviour change— over and above the longstanding goal of changing hearts and minds. This is recommended because, conversely, traditional policy instruments such as public service announcements, statistics, consumption feedback, and energy labels, were found to be the least effective ways to produce behavioural change. The assumption about the positive role of information seems to die hard, despite consistent evidence of its low impact. Whereas this is an unsurprising result to behavioural scientists
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> and some results have pointed in this direction
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>, there is a considerable gap between what is known in behavioural science and what is proposed and implemented by policy-makers. These strategies continue to dominate the proposed solutions in the latest Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Special Report with respect to demand-side behaviour changes
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>, and the recently published randomised field trials persist on the idea of testing information-based strategies to promote mitigation behaviours (
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">Supplementary References</xref>
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>
 </sup>). Information-based strategies are employed under the assumption that, when provided with facts and figures, people will adjust their behaviour and monitor their actions that produce carbon emissions
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>
 </sup>. Such assumptions are challenged by our results, estimating the probability that information can produce positive changes in 3.4%. This is a result of paramount significance considering the central role these strategies are expected to play in the fight against global warming
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>
 </sup>. Nonetheless, there is still the need to evaluate the conditions under which the effect of information strategies may be boosted, for instance when combined with financial incentives, or when delivered by trustworthy sources and easily available at the point of decision
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>
 </sup>. Whereas information has little impact to motivate unmotivated individuals, information may be crucial to guide behaviour once people are fuelled by complementary, more motivating strategies.
</p>
