<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One native and non-native species were selected for additional study to explore whether UV screening varied with elevation and prevailing levels of solar radiation. For this study, we sampled the native shrub, 
 <italic class="italic">Vaccinium reticulatum</italic>, and the non-native forb, 
 <italic class="italic">Verbascum thapsus</italic>, across the entire elevational range of both species (762–3352 masl for 
 <italic class="italic">V. reticulatum</italic>; 100–3962 masl for 
 <italic class="italic">V. thapsus</italic>) during June. We chose these species because they could often be found growing in close proximity throughout much of this elevation gradient, which was essential for sampling purposes (measurements were conducted in the dark as indicated below). Sampling locations were located on the south slope of Mauna Kea along a transect that generally corresponded to that used by 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nullet and Juvik (1997)</xref> in a study characterizing elevation changes in UV-B, photosynthetically active radiation (PAR; 400–700 nm), and total shortwave (SW) radiation (300–3000 nm). In their study, 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nullet and Juvik (1997)</xref> measured UV-B using a broadband sensor (Robertson-Berger Model 501A Biometer) that provided a measure of biologically effective UV-B (UV-B
 <sub class="sub">ERY</sub>) weighted according to the human erythemal action spectrum. PAR was measured with a LiCor Model LI190SB quantum sensor and SW radiation was measured with an Eppley PSP pyranometer. 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nullet and Juvik (1997)</xref> collected radiation data at 10 elevations ranging from sea level (0 m) to 4230 masl on Mauna Kea near midday under clear skies in June and then they adjusted their data to correspond to a solar zenith angle of 10°. At each of their sampling elevations, these investigators reported values of UV-B
 <sub class="sub">ERY</sub>, PAR, and SW relative to those at the Mauna Kea summit. We used polynomial regression models [second-order for UV-B and fourth-order for PAR and SW (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.98–0.99); SAS JMP] to establish relationships between elevation and these three measures of relative solar irradiance. We then used these regression models to calculate relative clear sky UV-B
 <sub class="sub">ERY</sub>, PAR, and SW for the sampling elevations used in our study. Least square regression and correlation (multivariate) analyses in JMP were used to examine relationships between T
 <sub class="sub">UV A</sub>, elevation, and solar radiation. For these regression models we tested linear and polynomial models (second, third, and fourth order) and selected the model that explained the largest amount of variation in the data (i.e., the highest value of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>).
</p>
