<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Causes of decline</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several authors have attributed the primary cause of decline for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">angasi</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">glomerata</span> reefs to overexploitation largely through dredge harvesting during the mid to late 19
  <span class="sup">th</span> century [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref037">37</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref039">39</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref080">80</a>]. Dredging was analogous to mining, breaking off pieces of reef and removing all size-classes of oysters [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref050">50</a>]. Dredging directly removed adult shellfish, and thereby reducing the spawning stock, and also removed, broke up, or buried shell culch material inhibiting spat settlement. Oyster populations were severely reduced in New South Wales estuaries during the 1850s-1870s through a process referred to as skinning, where a schooner would be berthed at an oyster bank at low tide and workers raked together the live oysters to supply lime kilns in Sydney and Newcastle [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref050">50</a>]. Reducing the number and extent of oyster reefs or beds within a reef system also likely reduced the resilience of the remaining isolated patches against local impacts such as disease and predation [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref039">39</a>]. Increased sediment loads into coastal waters resulting from land use changes could also have contributed to reef burial or covered shell cultch further inhibiting settlement [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref039">39</a>]. The removal or burying of hard substrate likely led to complete ecosystem change or phase shift from shellfish ecosystems to soft sediment ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref081">81</a>] and collapse of the harvest fishery [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref073">73</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Invasive animals and new diseases may have also contributed to shellfish ecosystem decline or were at least symptomatic of declining water quality and disturbance. One oyster dredging company undertook a large restocking exercise of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">angasi</span> (source unknown but possibly New Zealand) in Western Port Bay, Victoria in 1861 [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref050">50</a>]. Subsequently, all stocked reefs and surrounding natural reefs died mysteriously in 1862, possibly through the introduction of a new disease (e.g. the parasite 
  <span class="italic">Bonamia</span> sp.). Ogburn et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref050">50</a>] attributed the collapse of subtidal oyster reefs in eastern Australia to the proliferation of spinoid polychaete mud worms in the 1880s, again possibly introduced from New Zealand with live 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">glomerata</span> transport.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other causes including declining water quality [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref045">45</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref078">78</a>] which can precipitate disease [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref050">50</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref078">78</a>] are also considered to have contributed to shellfish ecosystem decline or inhibited natural recovery. Many estuaries along the east coast of Australia have been strongly affected by acidification caused by the disturbance of acid-sulphate soils brought about by land use changes and development. Affected water has elevated concentrations of metals and lowered pH, which can lower oyster survival and growth rates [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref082">82</a>]. Global patterns of increasing ocean acidification may challenge the recovery of shellfish ecosystems in some locations in the future [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref083">83</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref085">85</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
