<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Towards the recovery of Australia’s shellfish ecosystems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The historical exploitation of shellfish ecosystems was an important economic driver for early colonial Australia employing hundreds of people directly in the fishery, shellfish transportation and vessel construction and maintenance. Early fisheries agencies recognised the decline in shellfish harvests and implemented changes in policy and management to reduce overfishing, which included spatial closures, zoning, restoration and, eventually, turning to early forms of aquaculture. In recent times, however, governments and coastal managers have done little to address the protection or restoration of shellfish ecosystems which has, in part, been attributed to the 
  <span class="italic">shifting baseline syndrome</span> (sensu, Pauly [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref092">92</a>]), as a large proportion of the loss occurred in the late 1800s and early 1900s, outside the living memory of most coastal users and managers today [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref037">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fortunately, Australia is well equipped to reverse the decline of shellfish ecosystems with a number of existing management and policy tools available to help protect and restore shellfish ecosystems. At the national level mangrove, saltmarsh, seagrass and kelp forest systems are likely to have suffered less loss compared to shellfish ecosystems yet are afforded greater protection under several Commonwealth and State Government conservation legislation (e.g. Commonwealth Government 
  <span class="italic">Environment Protection and Biodiversity Conservation Act</span> 1999, New South Wales 
  <span class="italic">Threatened Species Conservation Act</span> 1995 and the Queensland 
  <span class="italic">Fisheries Act</span> 1994). Considering the extent in decline of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">angasi</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">glomerata</span> ecosystems and their current limited distribution and continuing threats to their survival [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref093">93</a>] the ecological communities associated with both species would likely qualify for listing under relevant federal and state legislation. Both 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">angasi</span> and 
  <span class="italic">S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">glomerata</span> reefs are also likely to qualify for listing under the IUCN Red List of Ecosystems (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://iucnrle.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://iucnrle.org/</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Australia is a signatory to the Ramsar Convention (which lists shellfish ecosystems as a Ramsar wetland ecosystem type- see Kasoar et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref038">38</a>]) and various migratory shorebird international agreements and has one of the largest networks of marine protected areas [
  <a rid="pone.0190914.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref094">94</a>], all of which could be used effectively to encourage the development of local and national recovery plans and protect what’s remaining. However, in order to help enact protection policy and recovery plans, further information on the ecology, function and biodiversity of shellfish ecosystems should be acquired, information that we identified in our literature review as being under-studied.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We therefore recommend the expansion of research into the current distribution, ecology and function of Australia’s shellfish ecosystems in order to inform appropriate levels of conservation, protection and best practice restoration, prioritise resource allocation, as well as strengthen the case for long-term public and private investment in their future management.</p>
</sec>
