<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To assess the Green River District's relative vulnerability to each hazard, we compiled environmental exposure, human health outcome, population vulnerability, and environmental vulnerability indicators drawn from the literature review for each hazard. 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="tab1" class="xref"> Table 1</xref> illustrates that while a number of key indicators were available on the National EPHT Network portal (most notably, environmental exposure indicators) external sources were required to perform a comprehensive assessment at the local level. For example, a number of studies have established a correlation between extreme heat events and heat-related morbidity and/or mortality by comparing the dates of extreme heat events with the dates of heat-related morbidity and mortality data [
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>–
 <xref rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. While the National EPHT portal provides heat-related mortality data for Kentucky during summer months from 1999 to 2014, it does not provide data at the county level. Furthermore, the datasets are annualized to protect privacy [
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. However, county-level temperature data from 2000 to 2012 (also obtained from the National EPHT portal) shows geographic variation across the district [
 <xref rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. This variation is likely even more pronounced across the commonwealth. In order to compare morbidity and mortality data with the actual dates meeting the definition of an extreme heat event, we gathered heat exposure data from the Kentucky Climate Center and heat-related morbidity and mortality data from the Kentucky Department for Public Health. The Kentucky Injury Prevention and Research Center at the University of Kentucky retrieved the health data from the Kentucky Inpatient Hospitalization and Outpatient Services Claims Files at the Kentucky Cabinet for Health and Family Services, Office of Health Policy, and from the Kentucky Death Certificates Files at the Kentucky Department for Public Health, Cabinet for Health and Family Services. It received Institutional Review Board approval from the Kentucky Cabinet for Health and Family Services.
</p>
