<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bottom temperature interannual variability</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Low-frequency variation in melt rate is being driven by intrinsic ocean variability. EOF analysis of bottom temperature anomaly shows that 32% of variability is explained in the shallower, coastal region (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a, b</a>), and has a multimodal spectrum with power in the interannual time band (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>). Shelf break exchange (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d, e</a>) explains 15% of variability and temperature anomaly EOF1 has multimodal power in the interannual band (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4f</a>). The intra-annual in-band variance in bottom temperature anomaly peaks along the ice front, explaining up to 71% of total variability (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4g</a>), while 1–5 year modes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4h</a>) produce 40–60% of total variability over the continental shelf. The 5–10 year mode (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4i</a>) explains 20–30% of total variability on the continental shelf, while the multidecadal mode (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4j</a>) explains 20% of total variance deeper than ~500 m. Bottom temperature variability is generally aligned along bathymetric features, indicating that ocean–bathymetry interactions are a significant source of variability.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Intrinsic variability in bottom temperature. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Bottom temperature anomaly EOF mode 1 and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> PC 1. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Spectral variance (power spectrum times frequency) for bottom temperature PC 1. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> EOF mode 2 and 
     <span class="bold">e</span> PC 2. 
     <span class="bold">f</span> Spectral variance for bottom temperature PC 2. SSA in-band variance is shown for time bands 
     <span class="bold">g</span> 0–1 years, 
     <span class="bold">h</span> 1–5 years, 
     <span class="bold">i</span> 5–10 years and 
     <span class="bold">j</span> 10–30 years, with min–max explained variance shown. Thin contours show bathymetry of 500, 1500, 2000, 2500 m. Orange line in 
     <span class="bold">b</span> and 
     <span class="bold">e</span> is smoothed with a 1.5-yr filter, while grey line is raw data. Colour bars in 
     <span class="bold">g</span>–
     <span class="bold">j</span> are scaled to the min/max variance range, as given as percentages in the lower left hand corner of each panel
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5618_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e681" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
