<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model details</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the response of basal melting to intrinsic ocean variability, we ran numerical ocean model simulations of the TIS over a period of 150 years. The ocean model is based on the Regional Ocean Modelling System (ROMS)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span> framework, with modifications to allow thermodynamic interaction between the ocean and a steady-state ice shelf
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span>. The model domain extends 25.5° in longitude (104.5° E–130° E) and 8° in latitude (60° S–68° S), with a longitudinal resolution 1/15° and latitudinal resolution of 1/30° (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). Ice/ocean thermodynamics are parameterised using the three-equation formulation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
   </span>. More details of the model setup are given in Gwyther et al.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span> The model bathymetry is based on RTopo
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span>, which provides the deep ocean and continental shelf bathymetry. RTopo does not included realistic bathymetry for TIS so we blended it with a TIS cavity bathymetry inverted from airborne gravity measurements that also includes a hypothesised trough connecting the continental shelf to an eastward extension of the TIS cavity
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span>. This modelling study includes direct ocean access to the eastern extension of the TIS cavity, which satellite altimetry missions indicate hosts a surface lowering signal distinct from the deeper TIS grounding zone
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. Ice draft was determined with airborne radar sounding measurements acquired by the ICECAP (International Collaborative Exploration of the Cryosphere through Aerogeophysical Profiling) consortium.
  </p>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first simulation has surface wind forcing from COREv1 which corresponds to repeating normal-year (1995) momentum fluxes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>. Surface heat and salt fluxes are taken from the 1995 record of sea ice formation from Special Sensor Microwave Imager (SSM/I) satellite observations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. This year is chosen as it represents a normal climate year, and unlike CORE forcing, SSM/I observations better capture the timing, magnitude and spatial extent of sea ice and polynya formation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. Lateral forcing consisted of downscaled results from a general circulation model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>, which itself was forced with repeated normal-year COREv1
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span> forcing. The lateral boundary conditions are applied interannually, so as to capture intrinsic oceanic variability in Southern Ocean properties (Supplementary Figs. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a> and 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>), in particular, the 20-year South Pacific Intrinsic Mode
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>, but no other modes of variability (e.g. coupled land–ice–ocean-atmosphere processes such as climate modes). If a repeated normal-year forcing were applied to the lateral boundary conditions, then slow oceanic modes would not be excited and in effect, the ocean variability spectrum would be truncated. Here we are concerned with variability in melt rate rather than the mean value, and so the choice of lateral boundary conditions is valid, despite the reduced mean melt rates. The mean value is low due to cooler conditions in the Southern Ocean, a common model bias in ocean GCMs forced with COREv1 conditions.
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second run (COREv2) of 120 years was forced with two periods of 1949–2007 interannual climate forcing. Surface wind forcing is from the COREv2 1949–2007 air–sea flux data set
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>, while surface heat and salt fluxes are composed of the climatology of surface heat and salt fluxes from SSM/I observations for 1995
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span> but scaled by the E − P (evaporation minus precipitation) fields for 1949–2007 from COREv2. These data sets are combined in this way to provide long-term estimates of polynya activity and sea ice formation, which are not obtainable from a data set of comparable length. The lateral boundary forcing is analogous to that in the first simulation, but now the global ocean circulation model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span> is itself forced with the COREv2 1949–2007 interannually varying air–sea fluxes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>. As a result, the lateral boundary forcing is representative of the oceanic response to the large-scale atmospheric climate variability including the complete forcing spectrum with all natural, intrinsic, internal (e.g. climate modes) and anthropogenic forcing components. The first period of 60 years is considered spin-up.
  </p>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A sensitivity study investigating whether intrinsic variability in melt rate originates locally or is imported through the boundary conditions was conducted (see Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). In this run, we force with the same normal-year atmospheric conditions as previously. However, we have changed the lateral boundary conditions to remove the interannual intrinsic variability, replacing them with a repeated seasonal cycle calculated as the climatology of the previously-used interannual COREv1 intrinsic variability forcing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>. These new boundary conditions, where we removed any interannual variability, enable an estimate of the variability intrinsic to the ROMS domain.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis techniques</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all analyses, the first 30 years of time series of melt and bottom temperature, which contain the model spin-up signal, are excluded. The resulting time series are detrended with a linear fit.</p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Signal-to-noise ratio is calculated as the ratio of variances 
   <span class="italic">σ</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>, calculated as
   <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">1</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${\mathrm{SNR}} = \frac{{\sigma _{{\mathrm{COREv}}2}^2}}{{\sigma _{{\mathrm{COREv}}1}^2}},$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">SNR</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msubsup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">σ</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">COREv</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msubsup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">σ</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">COREv</span>
          <span class="mn">1</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">,</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5618_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>where 
   <div id="IEq1" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sigma _{{\mathrm{COREv}}2}^2$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M4" class="math">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">σ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">COREv</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41467_2018_5618_Article_IEq1.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> is the square of the standard deviation of the melt rate anomaly for the interannually varying run with COREv2 forcing, while 
   <div id="IEq2" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M5" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\sigma _{{\mathrm{COREv}}1}^2$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M6" class="math">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">σ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">COREv</span>
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41467_2018_5618_Article_IEq2.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> is the square of the standard deviation of the melt rate anomaly for the intrinsic variability-only run with COREv1 forcing.
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cross correlations of MCDW depth and volume flux with melt rate were calculated and a lag of 0 months is found to be optimal. As analysis is computed on monthly averages, a short lag or lead of less than 1 month is possible.</p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical orthogonal function (EOF) analysis is used to decompose a time series into orthogonal spatial patterns (EOFs) along with the associated time series or principal components (PCs) and the variance explained by each mode
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. While EOF analysis can provide useful decomposition of data, it has limitations such as domain dependence. While the leading mode(s) may often be physical, successively higher order modes, which explain less of the remaining variance, are unphysical as a consequence of the mode orthonormalisation.
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consequently, we employ singular spectral analysis (SSA) to express the original time series as a linear combination of components derived from singular value decomposition of the (time) lagged covariance matrix with maximum lag 
   <span class="italic">M</span>. The resulting modes together sum to the original time series, while the slowest varying mode represents the non-linear trend with (time) variability of the order of the chosen embedding dimension 
   <span class="italic">M</span> or longer. The decomposition is data driven (based on smaller, lagged portions of the original time series) and does not require projection on predefined basis functions, as required for example with Fourier transform methods. SSA readily provides non-linear smoothing of the original time series with the degree of smoothing controlled by 
   <span class="italic">M</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>. The SSA in-band variance shows the percentage of total variance present in the chosen time band bounded by predefined embedding dimension values, i.e. 0–1, 1–5, 5–10 and 10–30 years as in Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3j–m</a> and 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>g–j.
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plots made with assistance from the Antarctic Mapping Tools for MATLAB toolbox
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span> and cmocean
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span> colourmaps.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model output that supports the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author on request.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
