<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intrinsic variability in melt rate</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The area-averaged melt rate of the TIS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) contains significant low-frequency variability, with a range of 4.5–6 m yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>) and power in the ~3–7 yr time band (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Intrinsic variability in basal melting. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Average melt rate (5.0 m yr
     <span class="sup">−1</span> with standard deviation of 0.5 m yr
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> area-averaged melt rate for the Totten Ice Shelf. The first 30 years is considered model spin-up and is excluded from analysis. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Spectral variance (power spectrum times frequency) for the melt rate anomaly, constructed by removing the climatology. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Melt rate EOF mode 1 and 
     <span class="bold">e</span> PC 1. 
     <span class="bold">f</span> Spectral variance for melt EOF mode 1. 
     <span class="bold">g</span> Melt EOF mode 2 and 
     <span class="bold">h</span> PC 2. 
     <span class="bold">i</span> Spectral variance for melt EOF mode 2. 
     <span class="bold">j</span>–
     <span class="bold">m</span> SSA in-band % explained variance in melt rate, with band duration (years) and min–max variance shown. Inset in 
     <span class="bold">a</span> shows location. Orange line in 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">h</span> is smoothed with a 1.5-yr filter, while grey line is raw data. Colour bars in 
     <span class="bold">j</span>–
     <span class="bold">m</span> are scaled to the min/max variance range, as given as percentages on the left side of each panel
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5618_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e536" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To identify and characterise modes of variation, we applied two different methodologies commonly used for analysing climate data (see Methods). Empirical orthogonal function (EOF) analysis identifies spatially invariant patterns in the data and accompanying time series that maximise variance. This was used to reduce the dimensionality and to decompose spatial and temporal variation into the EOF spatial modes, temporal principal components (PCs) and the variance explained by each mode. We restrict our analysis to modes explaining &gt;5% of the variance (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> for first 6 modes). The data has been linearly detrended and the climatological mean removed prior to analysis.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EOF analysis of melt rate anomaly suggests that most variability (57% of variance) is explained by mode 1 (EOF1; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>) which shows wide-scale coherent fluctuations in basal melting, similar to the time-mean spatial pattern in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>. EOF mode 2 (EOF2; 8% of variance) captures enhanced shallow or deep melting, and results from water flowing either along the ice shelf front or below the ice shelf (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3g</a>). Interannual fluctuations in average melt rate are represented strongly in the first PC of the EOF analysis (compare Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a> to Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), which contains ~3-, 5-, ~7-year and multidecadal modes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3f</a>). The second PC (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3h</a>) contains mostly intra-annual variability (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3i</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the EOF analysis captures spatial patterns of covariability it does not necessarily separate physical modes over different timescales. To achieve this, we apply singular spectrum analysis (SSA)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, which identifies spatially coherent regions of variance for a chosen time band, to analyse the leading PCs of melt rate and extract secular behaviour present at intra-annual (&lt;1 year), interannual (1–5 and 5–10 years) and multidecadal (10–30 year) time bands (see Methods).
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The in-band SSA variance shows the percentage of total variance at each location within defined time bands (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3j–m</a>). Intra-annual modes explain ~40–50% of total variance, and closer to 90% of total variance near to the ice front (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3j</a>). These intra-annual modes result from the seasonal cycle in sea ice production and winds. As this study focusses on interannual variability, these &lt;1-year modes will not be further discussed. Modes with a period of 1–5 years explain on average ~23% (maximum of 44% in certain locations) of the total variance in basal melting (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3k</a>), while ~7% (maximum of 21%) of the total variance is explained by modes that occur over 5–10 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3l</a>). Multidecadal modes in basal melting are present but explain on average ~6% (maximum of 24%) of the total variance (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3m</a>). Histograms of in-band SSA variance for the chosen time bands are shown in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
