<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our experiments show that mortality rates were higher when simulating heat waves compared with control conditions. This result was expected (Andrew, Hart, Jung, Hemmings, &amp; Terblanche, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Rukke, Aak, &amp; Edgar, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Tewksbury, Huey, &amp; Deutsch, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and may be caused by, e.g., denaturation of proteins, disruption of membrane structure and function, interactions with oxygen supply, and dehydration impairing evaporative cooling (Chown &amp; Terblanche, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Klose &amp; Robertson, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Potter et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Mortality rates of eggs further increased after exposure to low humidity, likely caused by dehydration facilitated by the low egg mass and a concomitantly high volume–surface ratio (Addo‐Bediako, Chown, &amp; Gaston, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Chown, Sørensen, &amp; Terblanche, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). The level of humidity used in our treatments was very low (10%), but exposure time was quite short (2 × 2 hr). Therefore, we do think that our treatment conditions were reasonable to mimic effects of low humidity during drought periods, although it is evidently difficult to extrapolate such laboratory results to field conditions. For instance, eggs are in nature attached to host plants and may benefit from buffering microclimatic conditions (Potter et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1978</xref>). Furthermore, wilted as opposed to fresh leaves and the associated food stress increased hatchling mortality rates as expected. All above results are in agreement with our first hypothesis, although it is interesting to note that effects of desiccation and food stress were even more pronounced than those of heat stress. This suggests that exclusively focusing on upper thermal limits while neglecting the impact of drought periods is insufficient for predicting the fate of species and populations under changing climate (Cooper, Tharp, Jernberg, &amp; Angilletta, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Rezende, Tejedo, &amp; Santos, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Mosquito distribution, for instance, may be limited by egg desiccation resistance (Kearney, Porter, Williams, Ritchie, &amp; Hoffmann, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), and fruit flies from the Australian wet tropics are known to have a low desiccation resistance and concomitant heritability, which is likely a crucial factor limiting their distribution (Hoffmann, Sørensen, &amp; Loeschcke, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Kellermann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
