<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most interesting result though is that indeed the three species investigated here differed in their responses to environmental stress, as evidenced by the significant species by treatment interaction for egg mortality, in agreement with our second hypothesis. Specifically, egg mortality increased most strongly in the arguably most vulnerable species 
 <italic class="italic">L. helle</italic>, followed by 
 <italic class="italic">L. dispar</italic> and finally 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic> (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33588-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>a). Note that these results fit very well with our predictions based on the general ecology of the three species concerned (Ebert &amp; Rennwald, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; Fischer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Brunzel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Settele et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Lindman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Hampe &amp; Jump, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Table 
 <xref rid="ece33588-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). While the glacial relict species 
 <italic class="italic">L. helle</italic> is associated with cool and moist habitats (Fischer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>) and should therefore suffer from both, heat and desiccation (Habel et al. 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0501" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), 
 <italic class="italic">L. dispar</italic> is associated with moist but (at least partly) warm habitats (Lindman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), such that the species should in first place suffer from desiccation rather than heat stress. Concomitantly, 
 <italic class="italic">L. dispar</italic> responded less strongly to heat stress than 
 <italic class="italic">L. helle</italic> but (nearly) as strongly to desiccation, while 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic>, being a habitat generalist with respect to moisture and temperature (Brunzel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Ebert &amp; Rennwald, 
 <xref rid="ece33588-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>), showed moderate responses only to both stressors. Note that the above conclusions rest mainly on comparisons relative to controls. This might be problematic given that 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic> showed the highest baseline mortality, which may drive the significant interaction for egg mortality (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33588-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). However, this pattern for 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic> is unusual as egg hatching success in this species is typically around 90% or higher under control conditions as found in both other species (K. Fischer, personal observation). The most likely explanation for the reduced hatching success in 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic> under control conditions seems random variation in female quality, for instance, caused by differences in female age (i.e., we assume that field‐caught 
 <italic class="italic">L. tityrus</italic> females were on average a bit older than in both other species). We exclusively used field‐caught females here, as these species do not mate in captivity. To account for such effects, we are convinced that the most straightforward way to interpret our data is comparisons relative to control levels. Anyway, note in addition that 
 <italic class="italic">L. helle</italic> showed the highest mortality rates under stress also in absolute terms.
</p>
