<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In general, wildlife population ranges shift toward the poles and to higher elevations under climate change conditions (Hole et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Our results are coincided with previous studies at the spatial shift of giant panda habitat in northward, upward, and northwestward (Fan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Tuanmu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), but vary a great deal as following: (1) The significant loss of habitat was not detected compared to the results of Songer et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) and Fan et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>); (2) the further fragmentation of habitat was not projected supporting the finding of Songer et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) and opposing the results of Shen et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>); (3) we firstly quantify the spatial shift of habitat by climate change and found an additional predicted an 11‐km eastward shift for giant panda habitat by 2050 which was not reported by previous studies. The reason for such contrasting results may be explained by study scale and the quality of variables. All previous studies set their study areas far more big than current giant panda population range a, but we just restricted our study area within current population range from the FNGPS, and the data of giant panda occurrence for habitat modeling are still within the region currently used by giant panda. So there maybe is a spatial autocorrelation from the bias of distribution in calibration data to cause the great loss out of current population range during habitat projection. Due to the change in giant panda population pattern in Qinling since 2000 (Gong et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), the latest occurrence data from the FNGPS in our study can better associate the relationship between presence and habitat variables including climate factors. Further, to lessen the uncertainty of projection results by different GCMs, the value of climate variables for modeling in our study was averaged based on used GCMs. The high AUC value in the Maxent model proved our results were reliable, the variable contribution and permutation importance of habitat factors in our study were consistent with previous studies of climate impacts on giant pandas (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Songer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and the results from giant panda habitat selection studies that found fidelity for specific slopes override elevation and aspect because of the need to maintain balance between energy intake and expenditure (Hu, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>; Schaller, 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1985</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32650-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Moreover, our study provides a methodological case to analyze future climate variables with better accuracy and can be applied to other climate change studies.
</p>
