<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The studies of the mechanical energies of Earth's atmosphere were initialized ∼100 years ago. In 1903, Margules
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" class="xref">59</xref> defined the available potential energy as the maximum amount of total potential energy available for conversion into kinetic energy under any adiabatic redistribution of mass. To generalize the definition of available potential energy, Lorenz
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref> introduced another definition for the whole atmosphere, in which the available potential energy was defined as the difference between the total potential energy of the whole atmosphere and the minimum of total potential energy. Using the definition of available potential energy and a common definition of kinetic energy in an atmospheric system, Lorenz further introduced a formulation of atmospheric energies and energy conversions in wind and temperature fields, which is generally knowed as the Lorenz energy cycle
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>. The Lorenz energy cycle was almost immediately used by Philips
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref> in his classical work simulating the general circulation of Earth's atmosphere in a two-level quasi-geostrophic model. Saltzman
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref> extended the formulation in the wave-number domain by employing a Fourier transform so that different scales of motions, including planetary, synoptic and mesoscale circulations, could be examined. In 1964, Oort
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> reformulated Lorenz's equations of atmospheric energetics in a mixed domain of space and time based on the primitive equations of motion. The formulation by Oort
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> has been widely used in recent years, because it does not make hydrostatic and geostrophic approximations. The other advantage of Oort's formulation is that it can discriminate between transient eddies (perturbations in time) and stationary eddies (perturbation in space). Peixoto and Oort
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref> further organized and used the formulation to analyse the annual distribution of the mechanical energies with observations. The organized formulation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref> is used in this study. There are generally two methods of evaluating the Lorenz energy cycle of the global atmosphere—the monthly evaluation and the yearly evaluation
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref>—in which the eddies are defined as atmospheric processes lasting less than 1 month and 1 year, respectively. In our previous study
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>, we suggested that the large-scale meridional circulation is better resolved in the monthly evaluation than in the yearly evaluation. Therefore, we present the monthly evaluation that characterizes the spatio-temporal characteristics of the Lorenz energy cycle.
</p>
