<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece35129-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0001" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Aim</title>
  <p class="p">Global change seriously threatens the salt marsh ecosystem, while it remains unclear how 
   <italic class="italic">S</italic>. will respond to climate change and sea level rise. Here, we investigated interactions among variables and identified the impacts of climate change, sea level rise, and their interactions on the distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">Spartina alterniflora</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0002" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Location</title>
  <p class="p">Northern Chinese coast and Southern Chinese coast.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Taxon</title>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">Spartina alterniflora</italic> Loisel.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">With global sensitivity analysis, we determined interactions among variables and their relative importance to the distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic>. Integrating the Venn's four‐set diagram, we built ecological niche models under current and three future scenarios to identify pure, shared, and coupling effects of climate change and sea level rise on the distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">Mean diurnal range (Bio02) and Elevation were the two most critical variables controlling the distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora </italic>on the Chinese coast, and interactions among variables of the northern coast were much greater than that of the southern coast. Habitats change was mainly caused by pure effects of climate change, except habitats reduction on the southern coast. Pure effects of sea level rise were low, but it can influence habitats change through shared and coupling effects from complex interactions with climate change. Interactions of climate change and sea level rise can drive habitats change, and the changed habitats caused by shared and coupling effects were mainly distributed the areas near the landward side.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35129-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Main conclusions</title>
  <p class="p">Our research suggests paying attention to interactions among variables when calculating the relative importance of explanatory variables. Identifying pure, shared, and coupling effects of climate change and sea level rise for the distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> will provide scientific references for assessing the risk of similar coastal species.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
