<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To calculate the voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> in each grid cell over the eastern United States from 2016 to 2100, the daily mean surface air temperatures from the coupled CESM1-CAM5 simulations were used and two steps of calculations (i.e., bee emergence and 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> development) were implemented (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0161319.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). First, because 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> starts its development after 
 <italic class="italic">Osmia</italic> bees emerge so that it can hitchhike the bees to move to a new bee nest for colonization and development, the Julian day of bee emergence was required to be determined first. The LDT and thermal constant for 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">cornifrons</italic> were set as 8.6°C and 179.8 DD, respectively, which were reported in White et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0161319.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Degree-days were calculated by subtracting LDT from daily mean air temperature and used to obtain CDD for the bee emergence in each grid cell of the eastern United States. No accumulation of degree-days was made in days when daily mean air temperature was lower than LDT. Dates for the bee emergence in spring were obtained by determining the date when CDD was greater than or equal to thermal constant. Second, to calculate the voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic>, LDT and thermal constant found in this study were used. Because it takes ca. two days for hitchhikes bees, move to a new nest, and lay eggs, the CDD for 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> was calculated by adding two days into the Julian day of bee emergence (i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> + 2 in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0161319.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). The voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> was determined by dividing CDD by thermal constant of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic>. The calculated number of generations per year in each grid cell was displayed over the eastern United States based on the four RCP scenarios. A series of maps for the voltinism of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> were generated for the years of 2015, 2050, and 2100. In addition, the differences in the voltinism between 2015 and 2100 under different future climate scenarios were calculated to estimate the spatio-temporal changes in 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">krombeini</italic> voltinism.
</p>
