<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4.4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> lineages
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">18 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> lineages were found in this study (
  <a rid="tbl4" ref-type="table" href="#tbl4">Table 4</a>). 3 of these lineages were previously found in other countries, suggesting a wide distribution. Of these, TUCHR01 was found from Japanese thrush (
  <span class="italic">Turdus cardis</span>), being of the same genus as all the previous hosts. Although not as strict as 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> is known to have host specificity to a certain degree. Moreover, this lineage, which belongs to the species 
  <span class="italic">H. minutus</span>, is known to have high specificity in thrush (
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">Valkiūnas, 2005</a>, 
  <a rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36">Palinauskas et al., 2013</a>). This study is hence supportive of this specificity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all the remaining lineages, except for 1 with a single previous detection within Japan, there is no vector or avian information regarding distribution or transmission. This is in part due to the fact that most of the lineages were detected for the first time. There are very few previously reported lineages of 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> in Japan, although reasons are unknown. Also, while there are at least 82 known species of 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> spp. in Japan (
  <a rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib51">Yanase et al., 2014</a>), there have been no studies regarding haemosporidian infection in 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> spp. or any other biting midge genus. However, 11 of these lineages were detected from resident breeders, strongly suggesting that these lineages are transmitted within Japan. For the 4 lineages derived solely from migratory breeders, further sampling and studies on both the vector and host species are needed for any further speculations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is interesting to note that there were no lineages found solely from wintering visitors, unlike 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>. In the other 2 genera, there were many lineages from wintering visitors, but tended to be of a specific host species or order. There is a possibility that such host specific lineages of 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> were simply not sampled in this study. Of the 4 wintering visitors infected with 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, only 2 were identified to a specific lineage due to co-infection. The 2 lineages from wintering visitors were also found from resident breeders. There are three possibilities for these lineages. One is that they were infected in their breeding grounds. LARCRA01 has been previously detected in Spain from Caspian gull (
  <span class="italic">Larus cachinnans</span>), which suggests that this lineage has a wide distribution, as mentioned above. Another possibility is that they were infected within the facilities, also discussed earlier. The last possibility is that they were infected in Japan during the winter. Seasonal dynamics of 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> spp. have been studied in other countries and generally, they agree that there are no active 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> spp. from November to April (
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">Ander et al., 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Santiago-Alarcon et al., 2013</a>). However, another study found parous biting midges in February, suggesting that bloodsucking activities occur even during the winter (
  <a rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib22">Mayo et al., 2014</a>). Although the seasonality for 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> spp. in Japan is unknown, there is a possibility that 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> may be transmitted even during the winter. In order to do any further discussion, more information regarding 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, including the identification of vector species, is needed.
 </p>
</sec>
