<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avian haemosporidia, including 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> have been reported throughout the world, including Japan (
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">Murata, 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">Valkiūnas, 2005</a>, 
  <a rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib31">Nagata, 2006</a>, 
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Atkinson and Lapointe, 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">Bueno et al., 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib33">Olias et al., 2011</a>, 
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Imura et al., 2012</a>). They are transmitted by blood-feeding vectors, each genus assigned to a different group of arthropod. For example, biting midges (Ceratopogonidae) and louse flies (Hippoboscidae) transmit 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, and mosquitoes (Culicidae) and blackflies (Simuliidae) transmit 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> respectively (
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">Valkiūnas, 2005</a>). The distribution of avian haemosporidia is closely linked with the distribution and habitat of the vector (
  <a rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib49">Waldenström et al., 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">Valkiūnas, 2005</a>) i.e., avian 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> prevalence decreases along with mosquito abundance, in relation to an increase in habitat elevation (
  <a rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib48">Van Riper et al., 1986</a>). Meanwhile, high-altitude forests are a preferred habitat for blackflies and high 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> prevalence has been reported among wild birds in this habitat (
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Imura et al., 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migratory birds travel long distances between breeding and wintering grounds, and can serve as important carriers of avian malaria (
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Atkinson and Lapointe, 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">Garamszegi, 2011</a>). Migratory birds include wintering visitors that spend the winter and breed further north, migrant breeders that breed in the area and winter further south, and passage visitors that breed further north and winter further south. These migratory birds are distinguished from resident breeders, or sedentary birds, which do not migrate and stay in the same area year-round. Japan is a part of the East Asian-Australian Flyway and serves as a breeding ground, wintering ground, and stopover point for various migratory birds, making Japan an important area for ecological studies (
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">Higuchi et al., 2009</a>). Therefore, migratory birds may carry new pathogens from one area to another (
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">Murata, 2007</a>). New parasite lineages may be easily carried into the Kanto area by migratory birds that travel to other areas. Also, both bird and vector distributions have changed in association to global climate change. The rise of air temperature has changed the arrival timing and numbers of migratory birds to their breeding and wintering sites, while in some species the wintering grounds have moved northward (
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Atkinson and Lapointe, 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">Higuchi et al., 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">Garamszegi, 2011</a>, 
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">Elbers et al., 2015</a>). Also, various ecological changes have also been reported in the arthropod vectors such as the extension of range, elongation of active period, and increased density due to shortening of developmental period (
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Atkinson and Lapointe, 2009</a>, 
  <a rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib13">Garamszegi, 2011</a>, 
  <a rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib11">Elbers et al., 2015</a>). For these reasons, distributions of avian malaria may possibly expand, hence threatening various birds, including endangered species that may be naïve to the pathogen. This suggests that both the prevalence of avian malaria and monitoring of the distribution of birds and vectors are important.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is often difficult to capture and obtain blood from wild birds. This is a large element as to why the prevalence of avian malaria in various regions and species of Japan are still unstudied. Avian malaria from wild birds has been studied in limited areas such as Hokkaido, Tsushima Island, Minami-Daito Island, Hyogo and some mountains for Japanese rock ptarmigan (
  <span class="italic">Lagopus mutus japonicus</span>) (
  <a rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib27">Murata, 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib26">Murata, 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib31">Nagata, 2006</a>, 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Sato et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib30">Murata et al., 2007</a>, 
  <a rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib28">Murata et al., 2008a</a>, 
  <a rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib18">Imura et al., 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib45">Tanigawa et al., 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">Yoshimura et al., 2014</a>), but most areas of Japan are unstudied. In the Kanto region, including Tokyo and the surrounding areas, there are a few facilities that treat and care for injured wild birds. Birds in these facilities are rescued for various reasons such as weakness, concussion and bone fracture due to window collision, car accidents and other causes. These factors might result in poor body conditions and may cause failure in the evaluation of adequate pathogenicity and virulence caused by infection of any haemosporidia. Some birds, including migratory birds, stay in the facility for long terms and migratory evaluations are not always necessarily in the natural state. However, these facilities are a valuable site for studying the prevalence and distribution of avian malaria in the Kanto region. Particularly, these facilities include Anseriformes and Accipitriformes which are both difficult groups of birds to capture. Throughout the year, there is a wide variety of rescued species, both resident and migratory birds, suitable for understanding the diversity of avian malaria in the Kanto area. In this study, we investigated the prevalence of avian malaria in injured and rescued wild birds in the Kanto region. We also evaluated the effect of migration on prevalence by monitoring avian malaria infections in each migratory status such as wintering, breeding and sedentary.
 </p>
</sec>
