<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The debate about the causes of the rapid demise of many societies in the eastern Mediterranean at the end of the LBA includes a number of factors such as climate change, earthquakes, famine, political instability and/or invasions by the infamous Sea Peoples [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Lately the number of studies investigating the role played by climate at the end of the LBA in the eastern Mediterranean has increased and a number of them suggest aridity as a major factor [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Paleoclimate data, primarily from Cyprus and the Levant, suggest that a 300-year period of arid conditions that began around 3200 yrs BP led to reductions in agricultural productivity and subsequently contributed to a general socioeconomic crisis in the eastern Mediterranean [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. However, it was recently pointed out that many of these datasets do not have sufficient chronological resolution to reliably tie climate information to archaeological data [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Despite chronological uncertainties and the fact that attributing sociopolitical changes to drought can be seen as overly simplistic and deterministic [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], the idea of widespread aridity has recently gained a prominent position in discussions about LBA societal change in the eastern Mediterranean as well as on the Greek mainland. Even though direct climate evidence from mainland Greece has not been available for this period, it has been suggested that the destruction of the Mycenaean Palatial centers towards the end of the LBA should be viewed in light of the severe aridity recorded for this period elsewhere see e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189447.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. In this paper, we present new high-resolution paleoclimate data extracted from a cave located just off the coast of the Greek mainland, in close proximity to one of the major Mycenaean Palatial centers.
</p>
