<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results provide the first regional quantitative analysis of social-ecological vulnerability to coral bleaching across many national jurisdictions, incorporating data from 30 island nations and territories. Previous studies of resilience and vulnerability to anthropogenic impacts have produced qualitative results [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C16">16</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C36">36</a>] or have focused either on ecological aspects [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C12">12</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C25">25</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C26">26</a>] or vulnerability and management of individual sectors [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C37">37</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C39">39</a>]. We focused on the insular Caribbean, an area already struggling to cope with reef degradation but that has been poorly covered by recent global assessments due to data gaps for individual islands [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C31">31</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C40">40</a>]. Crucially, we find that overseas territories have greater socio-economic sensitivity and lower adaptive capacity than independent islands, indicating that these territories, many of which have been excluded from previous assessments, may be at much greater risk to the socio-economic impacts of coral bleaching than previously appreciated. We found low correlation between the different components of vulnerability, consistent with an assessment focused on climate change impacts on fisheries [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C31">31</a>] and indicating that high vulnerability can result from a range of factors. This low correlation has implications for management, as it indicates that the drivers of high vulnerability vary from island to island. The indicator-based framework we developed, as well as our findings relating sovereignty and environmental management to reduced vulnerability, are relevant to coral reef ecosystems around the world.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found greater variation in socio-economic than ecological variables, implying that variation in overall social-ecological vulnerability across the Caribbean is in large part due to socio-economic differences. This is perhaps unsurprising, given the socio-economic diversity across Caribbean islands, including large differences in the economic importance of reef ecosystems and in governance characteristics. Of the socio-economic variables, the proportion of GDP from reef-based tourism had the greatest weighting in our equation (electronic supplementary material, table S25), but literacy rate, presence of ecological monitoring, and domestic consumption of local fish had greater average contributions to the islands' social-ecological vulnerability scores (electronic supplementary material, figure S1), due to the relatively high values of these variables.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the ecological variables generally displayed less variation than the socio-economic variables, 
  <span class="italic">Diadema antillarum</span> density showed a high level of variation, reflecting uneven recovery of urchin populations following a major disease epidemic and population crash in the early 1980s, with important implications for the suppression of algal overgrowth on reefs [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C41">41</a>]. There was relatively low variation in the coral species richness and coral sensitivity score for each island, reflecting species homogeneity in the region [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C42">42</a>] and low variation in taxonomic responses to bleaching [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C43">43</a>]. Of the ecological variables, the environmental stress score had the largest contribution to the value of the overall social-ecological vulnerability (electronic supplementary material, table S25), but there was relatively little spread in the values of stress scores across the region (electronic supplementary material, table S23).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analysis of potential covariates of vulnerability indicates that independent islands (i.e. sovereign states) and islands with more fisheries regulations (e.g. catch limits, seasonal closures, species protections) have greater socio-economic adaptive capacity, due to a higher frequency of environmental monitoring and adaptive management. Fisheries regulations and MPAs have been promoted as management tools to enhance ecological resilience [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C44">44</a>], but we did not find a strong relationship between the percentage of an island's reefs protected by MPAs or the number of fisheries regulations and either ecological sensitivity or ecological recovery potential. The MPA result may in part reflect the different levels of use restrictions and management effectiveness in MPAs: our dataset included all types of MPAs (including areas that allow some fishing activity), and enforcement and management effectiveness and associated ecological outcomes vary widely in the region [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C45">45</a>]. MPAs may still play an important role in reef recovery, resilience, and conservation in locations where they have adequate management regulations and capacity. The lack of impact of fisheries regulations on ecological vulnerability may similarly reflect barriers to effective enforcement of restrictions in the region [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C46">46</a>]. Our analysis of MPA impacts may also be complicated by biogeographic patterns, as well as historic and ongoing ecological degradation on Caribbean reefs; Swain 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C43">43</a>] found that the tropical Atlantic had relatively low taxonomic sensitivity to coral bleaching, and the dominance of coral taxa with low sensitivity may reflect die-offs of more sensitive species during previous bleaching events. Protected reefs may thus have higher abundances of more sensitive coral species because their protected status reduces localized stressors; the dominance of more sensitive species in protected areas may then lead to greater ecological sensitivity to coral bleaching [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C47">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although territorial governments, and in some cases, the dependent territories themselves, may view overseas territories as benefitting in some ways from a colonial relationship, we found that islands that are overseas territories had greater socio-economic sensitivity to coral bleaching, resulting from higher economic dependence on reef-based tourism and a greater contribution of locally landed fish to domestic seafood consumption. The higher dependence on tourism may reflect development priorities of overseas governments and the propensity of tourists to visit their country's territories. Furthermore, at least some of the increase in the percentage of fishery landings that are consumed on-island may also be related to increased dependence on tourism, as tourists can drive demand for seafood [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C48">48</a>]. The greater economic reliance on reef-based tourism in territories implies less diverse economies and greater economic losses if climate change-related coral bleaching, sea-level rise, and increased storm intensity reduce tourism [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C49">49</a>]. Sample sizes are insufficient to determine whether the territories of different countries have significantly different patterns of vulnerability. However, a visual assessment of the results suggests that Dutch territories appear to have lower socio-economic adaptive capacity than the other territories (electronic supplementary material, figure S2).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We produced an unprecedented compilation of socio-economic and ecological data across 30 Caribbean islands. The analytical framework we have developed can be extended to other locations or updated easily if new data are collected in the region, and our results reveal data gaps that could be filled to improve regional vulnerability assessments. For example, we see opportunities to improve assessments of socio-economic sensitivity and adaptive capacity through the collection of standardized data; unemployment and poverty rates may be important indicators of socio-economic vulnerability, but there are no systematic surveys of these variables across the Caribbean region and island-level surveys use different thresholds and definitions. Furthermore, data on fishing activity may be unreliable, as substantial activity in the artisanal and subsistence sectors is unreported [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C50">50</a>]. Another important limitation of our assessment of social-ecological vulnerability is the lack of data on larval connectivity, recruitment, and post-settlement survival in our index of ecological recovery potential. While the dispersal and recruitment of coral and reef fish larvae is a significant factor in the recovery of coral reef ecosystems [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C44">44</a>], the stochasticity of larval connectivity [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C51">51</a>] and the behavioural, ecological, and oceanographic data required for accurate models of dispersal and recruitment patterns limit our ability to incorporate these factors [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C52">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We combined diverse indicators to develop measures of ecological and socio-economic exposure, sensitivity, recovery potential, and adaptive capacity, and subsequently combined these components of vulnerability into an index of social-ecological vulnerability. Indicator selection and methods of aggregation can influence the final vulnerability scores, but we attempted to use indicators that could be assessed consistently across the study region and to ground our aggregation decisions in established vulnerability frameworks. Furthermore, in the absence of expert or stakeholder input on the relative importance of the different indicators or components in the specific context of Caribbean coral reef social-ecological systems, we chose to use equal weightings [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C53">53</a>], but these weightings could be modified if more information were available. We also did not include all economic sectors or ecosystem services that could be impacted by coral bleaching or climate change, such as shoreline protection, in our analysis [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C6">6</a>]. Future vulnerability assessments for the Caribbean that address these assumptions and limitations merit attention.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative values of each component of vulnerability (and their underlying variables) can guide managers and policymakers in their efforts to reduce vulnerability: although large-scale vulnerability assessments should be complemented with more localized assessments with stakeholder participation to better target local policy interventions [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C30">30</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C54">54</a>], they still reveal important broad-scale patterns (e.g. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20182365F4" href="#RSPB20182365F4">figure 4</a>). Islands with high potential for ecological impacts and low recovery potential, like Haiti and Saba, could use management measures to reduce their ecological exposure and sensitivity (e.g. by improving land use planning and agricultural practices to decrease erosion and nutrient pollution, using less sensitive coral taxa in reef restoration efforts and shifting fishing effort to less reef-dependent species) and/or to increase their ecological recovery potential (e.g. by reducing land-based pollution that promotes macroalgal growth; by protecting important components of the ecosystem currently subject to fishing through appropriate fisheries management; and by using reef restoration or artificial reefs with high architectural complexity to increase coral recruitment and densities of parrotfish and other herbivores [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C55">55</a>]). Islands with low potential ecological impacts and low recovery potential, like Montserrat and St. Barthelemy, could focus their efforts on maintaining low exposure and sensitivity while enhancing ecological recovery potential. Islands with high potential socio-economic impacts and low adaptive capacity (and thus high overall social-ecological vulnerability), such as Saba, could use policy measures to increase adaptive capacity (e.g. by increasing literacy levels and decreasing income inequality, implementing adaptive environmental management, and establishing ecological and fisheries monitoring) and/or decrease socio-economic sensitivity through economic diversification. While some factors contributing to ecological exposure are impossible to manage at the island level (e.g. sea surface temperature and solar radiation), all islands could reduce their risk of experiencing bleaching conditions by managing local water quality and other land-based impacts to reefs [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C56">56</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A key advance of our approach is assessing vulnerability at the national scale across many jurisdictions. Although this scale may mask important local-scale and socially differentiated variation in vulnerability, the island-level estimates of vulnerability are policy-relevant and actionable. Our findings regarding the importance of socio-economic factors such as ecological monitoring and adaptive environmental management suggest responses at the island level. Furthermore, our research complements and contextualizes site-based research [
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C57">57</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182365C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182365C58">58</a>], which can identify more focused, local-scale interventions within an island-wide framework. Finally, this scale of analysis enabled important insights that could not have been identified from local-scale analyses. Specifically, we determined that different components of vulnerability are uncorrelated at a national scale across a diverse region like the Caribbean; that socio-economic factors can be more important than ecological factors, including exposure to climate threats, in driving variation in climate vulnerability; and that independent nations may be more robust to climate change than dependent territories. These insights contribute to our understanding of climate change vulnerability across multiple dimensions and can inform policy interventions to reduce vulnerability to coral bleaching.
 </p>
</sec>
