<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several other factors can affect regional precipitation, and these can vary by season. Beyond Lee et al. (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and Zhang et al.'s (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) demonstration of the impacts of land cover changes on tropospheric temperatures, our study shows that the impacts of irrigation also extend into the upper atmospheric levels and can be different from near‐surface changes (Figures 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref> and 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0008" ref-type="fig" class="xref">8</xref>). The differing temperature responses at the upper levels and the surface such as over SAS in spring are likely linked to diabatic heating associated with enhanced moisture fluxes that extend into the lower to mid troposphere (Figures 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref> and 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0012" ref-type="fig" class="xref">12</xref>). Large‐scale changes in the horizontal and vertical temperature gradients in the atmosphere can influence regional precipitation patterns by altering circulation patterns and atmospheric stability to a greater extent than changes in moisture availability. We demonstrate such substantial effects of irrigation relative to land cover on low‐level circulation, moisture convergence, and MSE (Figures 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0011" ref-type="fig" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0012" ref-type="fig" class="xref">12</xref>). For instance, over SAS, despite increases in moisture availability due to irrigation, the weakening of the circulation, associated with changes in the meridional thermal gradient and reduction in MSE, leads to negative impacts on summer monsoon rainfall in contrast to land cover changes. In other regions, irrigation substantially amplifies land surface influences on the larger‐scale circulation and, thus, its subsequent precipitation. Such impacts of irrigation are also seasonally dependent. For example, while our results show that irrigation leads to a weakening of the summer monsoon circulation over SAS, Wey et al. (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) show that irrigation‐induced near‐surface cooling leads to a strengthening of the winter monsoon circulation (also see Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S5</xref>).
</p>
