<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological niche models (ENMs) based on correlative species-environment relationships are widely used to assess the impact of past and future global change on biodiversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Despite the long-standing and important role of ENMs in global change research
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, these correlative approaches present important shortcomings that challenge their applicability in a changing, highly dynamic world (see e.g.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>). One such limitation is the low transferability (i.e. model extrapolation) of parameterised models to other regions or times beyond the range of data used for model fitting (see
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, for a review). However, the spatial and temporal transferability of ENMs is rarely evaluated prior to predicting species distribution in different regions or times.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have provided evidence that model transferability is influenced by the modelling technique, as different algorithms show different sensitivities to spatial dimensionality and correlation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Ensemble modelling and consensus methods have been proposed as an alternative to avoid overreliance on a single technique and reduce uncertainty across individual models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Moreover, excessively complex models risk overfitting the data used for calibration, ultimately leading to predictions that can be too specific to the reference system to be transferable
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Most parsimonious models – built upon a small set of predictors – are expected to lead to greater transferabilities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Thus, one critical step to ensure that models are ecologically meaningful, and therefore may support transferability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, is the choice of predictor variables
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. However, many studies appear to use only environmental data that are readily available, while failing to consider other variables that may be ecologically relevant to the species distribution (i.e. causal rather than substitute predictors)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, and often missing important environmental drivers. New research on how the integration of key environmental drivers affects the transferability of ENMs is urgently needed given the increasing consensus on the importance of addressing the combined impacts of future climate and land-use/cover changes on biodiversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. In this regard, the incorporation of less common but equally important predictors is now increasingly feasible, as remote sensing data are more readily available
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. This broad range of available predictors can help improve the performance of ENMs and, in turn, their transferability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. This is the case for the intra- and inter-annual variability and seasonal dynamics of vegetation indices obtained from monthly images captured by satellite sensors. Several metrics summarising such dynamics are considered robust, integrative descriptors of ecosystem functioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> and have recently been found to be meaningful predictors for species distributions and their temporal dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. However, to the best of our knowledge, there is only one study that has assessed the role of these remotely-sensed ecosystem functional variables on model transferability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, although without considering the potential advantages of combining those variables with other relevant environmental drivers such as climate and land use change.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To advance on the application of model extrapolation in time and space, a better understanding of the processes and conditions that affect transferability is needed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The ecology of species has also been demonstrated to impact model performance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> and predictor ranking
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Indeed, the effects of species traits (i.e., characteristics or qualities of the organisms of a species influencing performance or fitness)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> on the predictive ability of ENMs were found to override any differences in modelling technique, as these traits may reflect the different responses of species to processes that control species distributions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. For instance, a global meta-analysis has showed that species traits such as body size, dispersal model and trophic position may be good indicators of predictability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Other studies found that non-endemic species with greater dispersal capacity, intermediate levels of prevalence, and little fire adaptation held higher model transferability than endemic species with limited dispersal capacity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. In addition, ENMs based upon climate, land cover and soil type variables performed less well for highly mobile species with large ranges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. A recent study also highlighted that the predictive ability of ENMs differs with regard to life history characteristics such as range, migration, habitat and rarity of a species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the growing body of research and evidence, the relationship between specific traits, predictor variables and model transferability still remains poorly understood
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. To address this caveat, here we tested four primary hypotheses involving the role of species traits and environmental predictors in model performance and transferability (see Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> for a detailed description):
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Hypotheses and sub-hypotheses, expectations arising from each hypothesis, and corresponding comparisons of model accuracy.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Hypothesis</th>
      <th>Sub-hypothesis</th>
      <th>Expectations and rationality</th>
      <th>Comparison</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>(H1) Model transferability hypothesis</td>
      <td/>
      <td>Model accuracy usually evaluated with a split-sample approach, i.e. repeatedly and randomly leaving out a subset of data used for calibration (‘Cross-validation’), will be higher within than beyond the model calibration time frame
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>
       </span>. We also expect higher model accuracy after testing the temporal projections against temporally (but not spatially) independent data (‘Internal TT’) than against spatially and temporally independent data (‘External TT’). This hypothesis aims to assess if cross-validation procedures are good indicators of model transferability.
      </td>
      <td>‘Crossvalidation’ vs ‘Internal TT’ and ‘External TT’.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>(H2) Environmental-predictor hypothesis</td>
      <td/>
      <td>The lack of ecologically relevant predictors will substantially reduce ENM performance and transferability
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
       </span>. While holding the number of variables constant (i.e., trivariate models), model accuracy − both within and beyond the model calibration time period − will increase with the combination of different types of environmental predictors related to climate, habitat availability, and ecosystem functioning conditions.
      </td>
      <td>‘Individual’ vs ‘combined’ models.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>(H3) Hierarchical-integration hypothesis</td>
      <td/>
      <td>Model accuracy will improve, particularly beyond the model calibration time period, with the hierarchical integration of environmental drivers whose effects are more evident and relevant at regional scales (i.e., climate) with those more important at local scales (i.e., land use/cover and ecosystem functioning)
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
       </span>. Climate-driven models calibrated at regional scales (i.e., Iberian Peninsula) will be able to capture a larger range of species distributions and, therefore, wider range of climate conditions where the species can currently occur or not
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>
       </span>. These ‘regional’ climate-driven models will be able to define the climate niche of species more generally (i.e. fewer omission errors) than ‘local’ models, and they can then be improved by the incorporation of land use/cover and ecosystem functioning at finer scales (i.e. Gerês-Xurés Biosphere Reserve).
      </td>
      <td>‘Hierarchical’ vs ‘non-hierarchical’ modelling approaches.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>(H4) Species-traits hypothesis</td>
      <td/>
      <td>Performance and transferability of ENMs will be influenced by species traits
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
       </span>. Species ecological characteristics will affect our ability to describe their distributions within the time frame used for model fitting (i.e. calibration) and to predict distributional shifts through time (i.e. temporal projections). If so, species’ traits might help to identify environmental predictors more suitable for predicting species’ distribution.
      </td>
      <td>Species traits across crossvalidation, ‘TT Internal’ and ‘TT external’.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">(H4.1). Biogeographic-climate hypothesis</span>
      </td>
      <td>If climate is the determining factor of bird species distributions (
       <span class="italic">sensu</span>)
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>
       </span>, the performance of ENMs based upon climate variables will be strongly dependent on the species traits related to their biogeographic origin. Given that Mediterranean species are relatively scarce and rare in our study area, we can expect that their distributions can be 
       <span class="italic">a priori</span> more easily predictable in space and time (due to combined effects of a narrow niche and small range size)
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
       </span> than for Eurosiberian species, yielding the highest model accuracy.
      </td>
      <td>‘Eurosiberian’ vs ‘Mediterranean’</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">(H4.2). Habitat-landcover hypothesis</span>
      </td>
      <td>Model performance and transferability will be higher for habitat-specialists than for generalists when predicted with models built with land cover (but not necessarily with climate) variables
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
       </span>. However, the predictive accuracy of our models should not be affected by species’ habitat preference (i.e. forest or open habitat).
      </td>
      <td>‘Habitat-specialist’ vs ‘habitat-generalist’ for ENMs based upon land cover, climate variables; and, ‘open-habitat’ vs ‘forest-habitat’ for ENMs based upon land cover, climate variables.</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">(H4.3) Phenology-EFAs hypothesis</span>
      </td>
      <td>Migrating birds track vegetation dynamics; i.e., the birds move with the seasonally progressing green-up of vegetation
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
       </span>, so species traits related to their phenology will potentially contribute to explain the performance and transferability of ENMs based upon ecosystem functioning attributes (‘EFAs’)
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
       </span>, which are derived from inter-annual variability and seasonal dynamics of vegetation indices.
      </td>
      <td>‘Migrant’ vs ‘sedentary’ for ENMs based upon EFA</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td/>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">(H4.4) Trait-predictor hypothesis</span>
      </td>
      <td>Since EFAs are directly affected by climate and land use/cover change
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
       </span>, they can potentially provide information about the integrative response of species to global environmental change
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>
       </span>, Thus, we would expect that those species traits with impacts on the performance and transferability of climate and/or land-cover models will also affect our predictions based upon EFAs.
      </td>
      <td>Species traits for ENMs based upon EFAs vs ENMs based upon climate and/or land-cover variables.</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(H1) 
  <span class="bold">Model transferability hypothesis</span>: Model accuracy will be higher within than beyond the model calibration time frame
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(H2) 
  <span class="bold">Environmental-predictor hypothesis</span>: Model accuracy, both within and beyond the model calibration time period, will increase with the combination of different types of relevant environmental predictors related to climate, habitat availability and ecosystem functioning conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(H3) 
  <span class="bold">Hierarchical-integration hypothesis</span>: Model accuracy will improve, particularly beyond the model calibration time period, by hierarchically integrating environmental drivers whose effects are more evident and relevant at regional scales (i.e. climate) with those found to be more important at local scales (i.e. land use/cover and ecosystem functioning)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(H4) 
  <span class="bold">Species-traits hypothesis</span>: Model performance and transferability will be influenced by species traits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> (see Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> for expectations and sub-hypotheses).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test these hypotheses, we compared the predictive accuracy of ENMs based upon (1) climate, (2) land-use/cover and (3) ecosystem functional attributes, and (4) the combination of these factors, for 27 bird species within the model calibration period (year 2000) and in a different time frame (year 2010), in a highly dynamic landscape of NW Iberia (Gerês-Xurés Biosphere Reserve). The predictive accuracy was aggregated by species traits related to biogeographic origin, migratory status and habitat preference and specialization.</p>
</sec>
