<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model transferability</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temporal transferability of the ENMs (i.e. the ability of the model to predict species distribution in a different time frame) was tested by comparing the environmental suitability predicted for 2010 − derived from ensemble models calibrated for 2000 − against observed occurrence data available for 2010 from two independent sources: (1) a dataset obtained from the replication in 2010 of a subset of the initial point counts used to calibrate the models, which enables a temporally (but not spatially) independent assessment of model transferability (i.e. ‘Internal TT’); and (2) another dataset obtained from a distinct set of locations and using a different sampling methodology, which offers a more independent − spatially and temporally − evaluation of the model transferability (i.e. ‘External TT’).</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As described above, the AUC of the ROC and Sensitivity were also used as accuracy metrics to evaluate model transferability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. We also calculated the number of species with AUC higher than 0.7 as a complementary indicator. To compare the spatial predictions for years 2000 and 2010, derived from the different ENMs, we calculated the Schoener’s D metric, the most common measure of niche overlap
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
  </span>. In particular, we computed niche overlap between spatial predictions derived from ‘individual’ and ‘combined’ models for each species using the function ‘nicheOverlap’ available in the R package ‘dismo’, version 1.1–4
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Then, the Schoener’s D metric values were summarised by computing the average across species for each type of model.
 </p>
</sec>
