<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species traits and model transferability</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings showed that species traits have a significant impact on both model performance and transferability (‘H4’; cf. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), despite the large variability among species (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">S3</a>). These results confirm the important role of species ecology on model performance, as previously suggested
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>
  </span>. However, our results also suggest that the effects of species traits on predictive accuracy within the model calibration time period are not necessarily translated into its temporal transferability (cf. Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Thus, while biogeographic origin was found to affect model performance and transferability, habitat specialization and migratory status only impacted model performance (not transferability), and habitat preference did not impact either model performance or transferability (cf. Table 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Interestingly, the results also indicate a trait-predictor relationship as some specific traits seem to be linked to specific environmental predictors. For instance, model performance was higher for habitat specialists than for generalist species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span> (see ‘crossvalidation’ in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Generalist species often have local subpopulations that differ in ecological characteristics, so modelling all these subpopulations together could overestimate the species ecological breadth and hence reduce model accuracy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span>. On the contrary, specialist species that inhabit in more restricted environmental conditions are usually more accurately predicted, as long as these conditions are not widely distributed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>. Similarly, Mediterranean species showed higher predictive accuracy than Eurosiberian species, especially in ENMs that included climate variables (see ‘External TT’ in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>; ‘H4.1’), due also to a narrower niche and smaller range size in the study area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
  </span>. Hence, our ability to properly model species distributions hinges upon the niche breadth–range size relationship
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
  </span>, even though this does not necessarily have to affect model transferability (‘H4.2’; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). In fact, some studies found greater model transferability for wide-ranging organisms with broad environmental niches than for narrow-ranging specialists
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. In addition, our results showed that migrant species were more accurately predicted than sedentary species (‘H4.3’; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). This is consistent with recent studies that demonstrated that migrating birds track vegetation dynamics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>; i.e., the birds move with the seasonally progressing green-up of vegetation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>
  </span>. Food availability is one of the most important resources determining breeding success. On the basis of the well-established principle that resources availability is related to primary productivity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>
  </span>, several studies successfully correlated species distributions with the inter-annual variability and seasonal dynamics of vegetation, measured through satellite-derived indices
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is particularly interesting to note that species traits affecting the performance and transferability of ENMs based upon climate and land cover variables also affected the predictive accuracy of ENMs based upon EFAs (H4.4, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). This may be explained by the fact that EFAs can be directly affected by climate and land use/cover change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> and can thus potentially provide information about the integrative response of species to global environmental change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>
  </span>. Indeed, ENMs based exclusively upon EFAs showed higher niche overlap with the combined models – that integrate the three types of environmental predictors – than land cover or climate models (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). These results suggest that satellite-derived EFAs, in addition to assisting the on-going assessment of essential biodiversity variables (EBVs) related to ecosystem functioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> (see also Working Group Ecosystem function GEOBON, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geobon.org/working-groups/ecosystem-function/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://geobon.org/working-groups/ecosystem-function/</span>), can also contribute substantially to near real-time biodiversity monitoring. Our results therefore confirm the ability of EFAs to accurately model bird distribution – especially for migrant, forest specialist species – although they cannot ensure model transferability by themselves (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Their integration with other ecologically relevant factors, such as climate and land use changes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>
  </span>, into ENMs will be key to improve temporal predictions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the study findings confirm the important role of species traits and environmental predictors in model performance and transferability for bird distributions, especially in highly dynamic systems. The progressive integration of ecologically relevant predictors related to climate, land-use/cover and ecosystem functional conditions significantly enhanced model performance within the calibration time period, under both hierarchical and non-hierarchical integration approaches. These findings provide additional support to the importance of integrating climate, land-use/cover and ecosystem functional variables to improve our future biodiversity projections. Unfortunately, the hierarchical multiscale approach did not show substantial advantages in terms of model transferability in comparison with the classic, non-hierarchical integrative approach, undermining its suitability for predicting bird distribution under global change scenarios. We strongly emphasize the importance of considering model transferability, in addition to traditional measures of model accuracy, and the need for caution when using ENMs to predict shifts in bird distributions as high discriminatory power within the calibration time frame does not guarantee the predictive ability of a model. Our findings also showed that species traits may significantly impact both model performance and transferability. In particular, the accuracy of prediction was highest for Mediterranean, migrant, habitat-specialist species, which provides guidance for the suitability of ENMs as an approach for predicting global change responses for birds in our region. However, the findings also suggest that the positive effects of species traits on predictive accuracy within model calibration are not necessarily translated into higher temporal transferability.</p>
</sec>
