<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par62" class="p">
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par63" class="p">Deterministic skill depends on the number of ensemble members averaged up to 6–7 members, then the skill saturates. Deterministic skills to hindcast an observed DCV index and to hindcast an ESM’s internally-generated DCV index - which can be called signal skill and noise skill, respectively – vary among the ESMs and also vary among lead times after initialization. In all ESMs and the MME for all DCV indices, higher deterministic skill hindcasts have larger signal skills than noise skills in the first 4 years. Only MIROC5 hindcasts of the PDO index have higher signal skill than noise skill in the first 4 years, resulting in a higher overall determinstic skill. TAG hindcasts by all ESMs and the MME have higher noise skills than signal skills in the first 4 years. Hindcasts of detrended and non-detrended WPWP indices by all ESMs have higher signal skill than noise skill in the first 4 years; both indices have high overall skills. Deterministic skills of the PDO and TAG improve in the CCSM4, HadCM3, and CM2.1 at lead times longer than 4 years when signal skills become at least equal to noise skills. Ranges of individual member correlation coefficients and RMSEs for the all three DCV indices are generally smaller when correlation coefficients are largest, especially at lead times closer to initialization.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par64" class="p">Probabilistic skill, as represented by the ROC AUC, was estimated for the ability of the decadal hindcasts to discriminate among positive, neutral, and negative phases of the three DCV indices. There is no discrimination skill in hindcasts of the PDO index in some of the initial years, but show an increase in discrimination skill as the lead years increase for both positive and negative phases. For the TAG index, there is no discrimination skill in the first year after initialization, but the majority of subsequent lead years show high discrimination skills. For the WPWP index, there is high discrimination skill in the initial years, with decreasing discrimination skill at longer lead years. There is no discrimination skill for the neutral phase of all three indices in any of the ESM’s hindcasts. The general consistency of the dependence of deterministic and probabilistic skills on lead time increases confidence in both types of skill estimates.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par65" class="p">Ensemble-average hindcasts of the three DCV indices made with the four ESMs and the MME have generally comparable phase occurrence rates with respect to observed rates. There is a moderate to high probability of phase persistence or same-phase transitions of PDO and WPWP phases from one year to the next in observed data and also generally in the ensemble-average ESM hindcasts, whereas the same-phase transition probability of TAG phases is moderate. There is a general tendency of all four combinations of PDO and TAG phases in the observed and ensemble-average ESM indices to remain in the same combination for at least two years, although there are cases in which probabilities are higher for transitions to other combinations.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par66" class="p">Ensemble-average and most of ensemble members of MIROC5 hindcasts correctly predict PDO phases one and two years after initialization in all five decades from 1961 to 2010. Prediction success rate decreases from the first year to the second in CCSM4, CM2.1, and HadCM3 hindcasts. Ensemble-average and most of ensemble members of the MME hindcasts correctly predict PDO phases one and two years after initialization after 1980; they correctly predict only the first-year PDO phase in 1960s and 1970s.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par67" class="p">Major, low-latitude volcanic eruptions in 1963 (Mount Agung), 1974–1975 (Volcan de Fuego), 1981–1982 (El Chichón), and 1991–1992 (Mount Pinatubo) are associated with sustained phase transitions of DCV indices in observed data and in some of the ensemble-average decadal hindcasts. Three of the four major volcanic eruptions were associated with PDO phase changes in observed data and almost all hindcasts. The WPWP index phase changes associated with all four eruptions were hindcast by all ESMs and the MME. In contrast, no one of the nine TAG phase transitions in observed data was present in any hindcast. Hindcasts from some of the ESMs and the MME show approximately correct phase transitions in the absence of AOD changes also, implying that the initialization of the ESM hindcasts with observed data is beneficial in predicting phase transitions of DCV indices.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
