<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par69" class="p">The results presented in this paper indicate that the persistance and phase transition probability statistics of DCV indices and their predictability by the ESMs, and also perhaps long-term evolutions, can be exploited for prediction of these indices’ possible impacts on hydro-meteorology, streamflows, agriculture, and other societal sectors. For example, the PDO, the TAG, and the WPWP SST indices are associated with precipitation, temperature, river flows, and crop yields in the Missouri River Basin (MRB)—the largest river basin in the U.S. and a major “bread basket” of not only the U.S. but also of the world. Positive phase of the PDO and negative phase of the TAG increase wetness and river flows, and negative phase of the PDO and positive phase of the TAG decrease wetness and river flows in the MRB. As a result, as described in the Introduction, a successful prediction of phases of these phoenomena one year in advance can be very useful to the agricultural economy of the MRB. Another example of usefulness of successful phase prediction is in predicting Mississippi River flow variations associated with the PDO and the TAG a year or longer in advance. Over 500 million tons of grain and other cargo are carried by barges on the Mississippi River annually, and both low-flow and high-flow conditions associated with the PDO and the TAG make substantial impacts on the water-borne commerce economy of the Mississippi River. Both these applications of DCV phase prediction are under way in collaboration with stakeholders in these two river basins. At longer than one or two years’ lead times, MIROC5 ESM appears to have the best overall performance from this group of ESMs. This reasonably encouraging performance of MIROC5 in hindcasting the PDO and WPWP indices over the 1961 to 2010 period was the reason for using the MIROC5 data to hindcast decadal hydrologic cycles in seven countries of southern Africa by Mehta et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2014</xref>) and can be used for other applications also.
</p>
