<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When phenological changes are observed, they often are taken as evidence that species are adjusting to changing environmental conditions in ways that help mitigate the effects of climate change. Yet the responses in nearly half of a set of studies reporting phenotypic changes in phenology, body mass, or litter size in mammals actually were associated with a decline in fitness.
 <xref rid="R95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">95</sup>
 </xref> For example, the advanced breeding of Chillingham cattle (
 <italic class="italic">Bos primigenius taurus</italic>) in response to warming led to more calves being born in winter, which resulted in an increase in calf mortality.
 <xref rid="R111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">111</sup>
 </xref> The responses in only one third of the studies qualified as adaptive phenotypic changes in phenology on the criterion that both the direction and the rate of change were appropriate.
 <xref rid="R95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">95</sup>
 </xref> Because species may show rates of phenological change different to those of other species on which they depend, asynchrony or a mistiming of key ecological events can result.
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">17</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">112</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>
 <xref rid="R114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">114</sup>
 </xref> For example, the calving date of caribou (
 <italic class="italic">Rangifer tarandus</italic>) on Greenland has been advancing more slowly, with warming, than has the onset of plant growth, creating a trophic mismatch and increasing calf mortality.
 <xref rid="R115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">115</sup>
 </xref> Numerous studies have demonstrated the ecological and metabolic costs of such mistimed ecological events,
 <xref rid="R112" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">112</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="R116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">116</sup>
 </xref> which ultimately may lead to a decrease in biodiversity.
</p>
