<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f4" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Results from optimal detection analysis of upper-ocean temperatures anomalies.</title>
  <p class="p">(
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>) Estimated scaling factors for two-signals of anthropogenic (ANT) and natural (NAT) forcings by which the simulated 2-year averaged T
   <sub class="sub">220m</sub> and T
   <sub class="sub">14°C</sub> responses in the oceans should be multiplied to best match the observations over 1951–2010. Best estimates (data points) and 5–95% confidence intervals (error bars) of the scaling factors are displayed. Black squares under scaling factor pairs indicate that the residual variability remaining in the observations after removing the scaled response is inconsistent with model internal variability. (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>) Estimated scaling factors for two-signals of ANT (x-axis) and NAT (y-axis) forcings based on a five-point spatial model fingerprint, composed of the average T
   <sub class="sub">220m</sub> (gray) and T
   <sub class="sub">14°C</sub> (black) responses in the North Atlantic, South Atlantic, North Pacific, South Pacific and Indian Oceans over 1951–2010 from CMIP5 (solid) and CMIP3 (dashed) ensembles, using an EOF truncation of 30. The 5–95% joint confidence for two-signals are represented by ellipses. (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) The same as (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>) but using CMIP5 for two sensitivity tests, 1) repeating the analysis over the period 1951–2000 (solid), and 2) repeating the analysis using lower temporal resolution (i.e. 5-year time series, dashed). In all panels, a detectable response to an individual forcing occurs when scaling factors are significantly greater than zero. Consistency between observed and simulated responses is determined when scaling factors are not significantly different from unity.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="srep26926-f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
