<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0019" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Disease and parasite load</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the influence of resource availability on warning signals demonstrates, animal coloration is strongly influenced by factors that affect an individual's condition (Griffith, Parker &amp; Olson, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0131">2006</a>). Disease and parasite load both negatively influence condition and consequently can lead to trade‐offs between immune function and signal expression (McGraw &amp; Hill, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0234" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0234">2000</a>). For example, increased parasite load leads to generally duller coloration in fish and birds of both sexes (Martínez‐Padilla 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0226" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0226">2011</a>; Ciccotto, Dresser &amp; Mendelson, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0060">2014</a>). Currently it is uncertain how such factors may influence aposematic signals specifically, but based on the shared physiological basis of aposematic and non‐aposematic coloration (e.g. sexual signals), it is possible that a similar ‘condition‐dependent’ relationship may occur (Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0019">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How the melanic component of aposematic coloration will be influenced by parasites and disease is unlikely to be clear cut. In common with coloured parts of warning signals, the production of melanin has various associated costs which may lead to trade‐offs between the production of melanin for pigmentation and immune responses (Guindre‐Parker &amp; Love, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0138" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0138">2014</a>). Under such a scenario, a negative relationship between melanin pigmentation and disease or parasite load can occur (Cotter 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0068">2008</a>; Gangoso 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0118">2011</a>) and may result in polytypisms if these loads vary spatially. However the association between melanisation and resistance to pathogens is not straightforward; for example, in invertebrates, cuticle melanisation acts directly in the protection of individuals from pathogens (Dubovskiy 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0086">2013</a>). Melanic pigmentation is also highly heritable in both invertebrates and vertebrates (Roff &amp; Fairbairn, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0298" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0298">2013</a>; Roulin &amp; Ducrest, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0308" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0308">2013</a>). It has been suggested that in many species the association between melanic coloration and a suite of disease‐resistance characteristics is a consequence of linkage disequilibrium and/or pleiotropy (Roulin, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0307" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0307">2016</a>). The result is differential life‐history strategies between more‐ and less‐pigmented individuals of the same species, the associated fitness of which is environmentally dependent (Emaresi 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0093">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The preference of parasites, particularly ovipositing parasites such as parasitic wasps, for specific colour morphs and for within‐morph conspicuousness (or traits correlated with within‐morph conspicuousness) may act as alternative selection pressures on warning coloration. Parasites may prefer one colour morph over another, as is the case for the aphid parasitoid wasp 
  <span class="italic">Aphidius ervi</span> which preferentially lays eggs in pea aphids, 
  <span class="italic">Acyrthosiphon pisum</span>, of a colour morph not favoured by predators (Losey 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0205" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0205">1997</a>). As discussed previously, coloration in aposematic species may be quantitatively linked to chemical defence (Summers 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0369">2015</a>), levels of which have been linked to decreased (Weldon 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0413" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0413">2006</a>) and increased (Zvereva &amp; Kozlov, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0427" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0427">2016</a>) parasitism risk, the latter being especially prevalent for specialist parasites (Al Abassi 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0002">2001</a>). Chemical defences have even been hypothesised to arise as a mechanism of preventing parasitism, with subsequent predator avoidance a secondary benefit (Weldon 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0413" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0413">2006</a>). This relationship between colour and defence may be further complicated by the fact that some chemical defences can also have antimicrobial properties (Mina 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0245" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0245">2015</a>). It is therefore conceivable that in areas with high risk of parasitism, colour morphs or levels of conspicuousness less attractive to parasitoids may be selected for, either through the parasites' direct response to colour or their response to levels of the strongly associated chemical defence. This may be especially important if infection dramatically reduces host survival (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Dinocampus coccinellae</span>; Maure 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0228" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0228">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, disease has the potential to cause continuous variation in the chromatic and achromatic parts of an aposematic signal due to current infection, plastic changes at the individual level where infection stimulates increase in melanisation, and local adaptation 
  <span class="italic">via</span> correlated trait responses if coloration is linked to factors such as immunocompetence and if the level of infection risk varies spatially. Pathogens may also cause local extinctions, or repeated bottlenecks, which can disrupt purifying selection and maintain colour variation (Gordon, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0125">2013</a>; Idris &amp; Hassan, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0161" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0161">2013</a>). Meanwhile, parasitism is likely to influence both morph abundance and within‐morph conspicuousness in populations of aposematic species. These areas are ripe for exploration, and have huge potential for contributing to the understanding of diversity in aposematic coloration and the life‐history trade‐offs involved in its determination.
 </p>
</sec>
