<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0017" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">The resource‐allocation hypothesis and quantitative honesty</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nature of the relationship between an aposematic signal and defence is complex and likely to play a role in the way resource availability shapes aposematic signal variation, especially within‐morph variation in conspicuousness. While aposematic species are inherently qualitatively honest, they may not necessarily be quantitatively honest (i.e. show a positive relationship between the level of signal and the level of defence). For example, positive relationships between conspicuousness and toxicity have been identified in a number of species [e.g. ladybird beetles (Bezzerides 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0017">2007</a>; Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0018">2012</a>; Arenas 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0007">2015</a>) and paper wasps (Vidal‐Cordero 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0409" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0409">2012</a>)]. However, the association is not universally positive, with negative correlations between levels of signal and defence identified across sexes or populations of the same species (Daly &amp; Myers, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0074">1967</a>; Wang, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0411" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0411">2011</a>; Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0018">2012</a>). Furthermore, in some groups it seems that related species can reach approximately equal protection from predators with multiple different signal–toxin strategies (Darst, Cummings &amp; Cannatella, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0076">2006</a>). A number of theories have been proposed to explain these differences (comprehensively reviewed by Summers 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0369">2015</a>). Research on the availability of resources, those used for coloration and preventing autotoxicity (antioxidants), has provided a feasible mechanism: the ‘resource‐allocation hypothesis’ (Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0019">2009</a>). In this model, coloration and chemical defence both utilise antioxidants which are commonly acquired from the diet. Thus, individuals have to balance investments in the signal and defence, or deal with a trade‐off between investing in the signal or the defence (Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0019">2009</a>). The model predicts that when resources are low individuals will signal honestly, whereas under high resource conditions quantitative honesty would degrade as individuals would preferentially invest in defence over warning coloration. These predictions indicate that the influence of spatial or temporal variation in resource availability upon warning‐signal conspicuousness is unlikely to be consistently linear.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical tests of the resource‐allocation theory are scarce however, and results equivocal in their support, showing that resource variation can lead to both positive and negative relationships between signal and defence (Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0018">2012</a>). The predictions of theoretical models investigating how individuals might invest in each component of an aposematic signal when resources vary also differ, depending on whether the model assumes that individual conspicuousness is an intrinsic component of the defensive signal or can act as a stand‐alone defensive trait (Blount 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0019">2009</a>; Holen &amp; Svennungsen, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0154" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0154">2012</a>; Summers 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0369">2015</a>). The latter refers to a scenario where the warning coloration alone elicits wariness or acts as a deterrent against predators through its conspicuousness or novelty (Guilford, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0135" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0135">1994</a>). Alternatively, other work has suggested that the honesty of aposematic signals is not mediated by the cost of production, but instead by costs imposed by predators, because predators are able to determine levels of protection rapidly while sampling potential prey (Guilford &amp; Dawkins, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0137">1995</a>; Hurd &amp; Enquist, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0160" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0160">2005</a>). It is therefore clear that whether individuals respond to increased resource availability with a concomitant increase in warning‐signal conspicuousness will depend on the mechanisms of honesty enforcement at work. Further work to clarify the mechanisms determining the honesty of signalling in aposematic species (Summers 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0369">2015</a>) will therefore aid predictions about how spatial and temporal variation in resources will influence within‐ and between‐population variation in conspicuousness.
 </p>
</sec>
