<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Types of variation in predators, and potential consequences</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a given predator (species or individual), defended prey vary in their degree of unprofitability (Brower 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0037">1968</a>), from mere distastefulness to deadly toxin loads. The impact of this difference is in part dependent on the specific predator and thus will differ among predators according to their susceptibility to specific toxins (Endler &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0097">2004</a>; Mappes 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0218" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0218">2005</a>), while the willingness of any individual to attack and consume defended prey will further be modulated by other factors, such as motivation and experience. Specialist predators, such as grosbeaks and orioles feeding on defended monarch butterflies, 
  <span class="italic">Danaus plexippus</span> (Fink &amp; Brower, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0110">1981</a>; Brower, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0035">1988</a>) or raptors preying on vipers (
  <span class="italic">Vipera</span> spp.; Valkonen 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0401" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0401">2012</a>), can overcome the defences of aposematic animals, whether through resistance to their defences or careful handling. As such, attracting their attention with bright aposematic signals would be detrimental to prey survival. Tolerance of prey defences can vary across species but also among populations of predators; for example, some populations of garter snakes, 
  <span class="italic">Thamnophis sirtalis</span>, have evolved resistance to newt tetrodotoxin (Geffeney, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0120" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0120">2002</a>). This may lead to polytypic or polymorphic variation in the conspicuousness of defended prey, following the distribution of more‐ or less‐tolerant predators across populations and microhabitats.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predator sensory systems, including their perception of visual cues and other cognitive functions (e.g. ability to learn, remember and generalise between signals), may also facilitate the maintenance of polytypic and polymorphic variation among aposematic prey. The key sensory systems used for hunting differ among predator taxa, so, for the same defensive effect, prey may need to employ a diversity of signal forms to maximise their ‘avoid me’ signal efficacy (Guilford &amp; Dawkins, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0136">1991</a>). Predation experiments with artificial prey demonstrate that only some predators respond to visual cues; for example, while avian predators avoid warningly coloured dendrobatid frog models, crabs and lizards do not (Willink 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0417" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0417">2014</a>). Variation in the effectiveness of warning coloration when confronted with different predator communities may lead to conflicting selective pressures on prey signals. In Japan, the relative abundance of avian predators, which rely on vision when hunting, compared to mammalian predators, for whom visual properties are less relevant, may be responsible for the variation in the extent of red coloration in 
  <span class="italic">Cynops pyrrhogaster</span> newts between island and mainland populations (Mochida, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0248" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0248">2011</a>). Among visually oriented predators themselves, there is considerable variation in perceptual abilities (Osorio &amp; Vorobyev, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0274" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0274">2008</a>), suggesting that some predators could perceive or distinguish visual signals that others may not. In addition, sensory processing in the brain plays a role in determining key features influencing the effectiveness of warning signals, such as detectability, discriminability and memorability (Guilford &amp; Dawkins, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0136">1991</a>). Finally, environmental conditions also affect the visibility and effectiveness of warning colours, dependent on ambient light and the characteristics of natural backgrounds (Endler, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0094">1990</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0095">1993</a>; Bond &amp; Kamil, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0025">2006</a>; Rojas, Rautiala &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0301" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0301">2014b</a>); so aposematism overall, or some specific colour morphs, may be more effective in particular habitats.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beyond perception of the signals, higher‐level cognitive processes may also influence predator responses to prey signals, and thus ultimately impact the adaptive value of conspicuousness and warning coloration. Generalisation between visual signals, whether they cannot be perceptually distinguished or are grouped together by higher‐order cognitive processes, is especially interesting, as it would effectively allow different colour morphs to co‐occur with equal fitness (Amézquita 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0003">2013</a>; Richards‐Zawacki 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0293" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0293">2013</a>; Stuckert, Venegas &amp; Summers, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0366" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0366">2014b</a>; Rönkä 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0304" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0304">2018</a>). For example, tests with multiple passerine species suggest that they differ in their ability to generalise prior experience of red firebugs (
  <span class="italic">Pyrrhocoris apterus</span>) to yellow morphs of this species (Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0104">2006</a>). Although it would not itself select for variation, generalisation between morphs could facilitate the maintenance of different forms (which could provide other selective benefits; see alternative selection pressures in Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0013" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0013">V</a>) in populations where predators tend not to distinguish between morphs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if predators classify signals as distinct, further differences in their response will arise due to variation in general neophobia, cautiousness when handling novel prey, and dietary conservatism. These effects can potentially facilitate the evolution of novel conspicuous morphs (Marples, Roper &amp; Harper, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0222" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0222">1998</a>; Thomas 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0380" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0380">2003</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0379" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0379">2004</a>; Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0104">2006</a>); although experimental evidence suggests dietary conservatism may not be sufficient to counteract positive frequency‐dependent selection against novel morphs when these are rare and conspicuous (Marples &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0221" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0221">2010</a>). In some cases, innate avoidance of specific patterns plays an important role, as demonstrated by the aversion of naive turquoise‐browed motmots (
  <span class="italic">Eumomota superciliosa</span>) and great kiskadees (
  <span class="italic">Pitangus sulphuratus</span>) to coral snake (
  <span class="italic">Micrurus</span> spp.) patterns (Smith, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0354" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0354">1975</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0355" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0355">1977</a>). Strong innate responses may allow polymorphisms in warning signals to evolve if the predators avoid a broad class of visual signals, such as all ringed patterns in the case of coral snakes. Finally, variability in the learning abilities of predators will affect the benefit of aposematic signalling for defended prey (Endler &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0097">2004</a>; Mappes 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0218" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0218">2005</a>). Recent work on domestic chicks (
  <span class="italic">Gallus gallus domesticus</span>) showed variation in avoidance learning among different breeds of this species. Chickens bred for high productivity were initially less wary of aposematic prey, but also formed weaker associations between signals and defences over time than the other breeds of chicken, leading to differential prey survival in laboratory experiments (Rowland, Fulford &amp; Ruxton, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0311" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0311">2017</a>). Predators in the wild may also differ in their learning abilities, leading to variation in predation risk for aposematic prey with different signals, and are also likely to differ from domestic chickens. Further research on learning in more relevant predators could alter our expectations of predator capabilities and responses to aposematic prey; for example, evidence that predators can rapidly memorise many different signal forms would challenge the assumption of strong selection for aposematic signal monomorphy.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Classic experiments on neophobia and dietary conservatism in passerine birds also reveal further intraspecific variation, which cannot be attributed to factors such as differences in territory, experience or sex (Marples 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0222" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0222">1998</a>). These could be linked to personality, known to affect both initial reactions to aposematic prey and the learning process (Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0103">2010</a>), or individual condition. A predator's level of hunger and current condition will determine its motivation and willingness to attack and consume risky prey, including warningly coloured individuals, which will impact the relative benefit of aposematic displays. Rather than rejecting aposematic prey outright, predators consider all available prey types to make adaptive foraging decisions, based on the relative costs of ingesting toxins 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> the nutritional gain from consuming the prey (Barnett 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0012">2012</a>). Experiments with European starlings (
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span>) suggest they can distinguish not only undefended from toxic prey, but also different levels of chemical defences, 
  <span class="italic">via</span> taste‐rejection (Skelhorn &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0351" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0351">2006</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0353" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0353">2009</a>), as well as gaining nutritional information about the prey (Skelhorn 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0350" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0350">2016</a>). This allows them to make educated decisions while foraging, depending on their motivation to feed; accordingly, starlings are more willing to consume defended prey when their own reserves are experimentally reduced (Barnett, Bateson &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0011">2007</a>), early‐life or current conditions are harsher (Chatelain, Halpin &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0054">2013</a>; Bloxham 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0020">2014</a>), or the prey have greater nutritional value relative to their toxicity (Halpin, Skelhorn &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0140">2014</a>; Smith, Halpin &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0356" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0356">2016</a>). While there is a growing body of evidence, primarily from laboratory experiments, suggesting that varying levels of motivation affect prey choice by predators, how this may impact the survival of aposematic prey and selection pressures on signal form in the wild is not yet clear. The physiological mechanisms and cognitive processes responsible for these adaptive decisions are still relatively poorly known, but there is scope for mediation of this toxicity–nutrition trade‐off to vary among species, populations and personalities (Skelhorn 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0350" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0350">2016</a>). Exploring how different predators deal with the trade‐offs associated with foraging in a natural setting, such as balancing the time required to assess the profitability of warningly coloured prey accurately, while managing their own exposure to predators and efficient foraging, would be extremely valuable for obtaining a more well‐rounded picture of predation risk for aposematic prey.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Motivation is not the only highly variable trait affecting predator responses to aposematic prey. Prior experience is critical in determining whether a predator will choose to attack and consume a prey item. This can vary widely across species and populations of predators, as traits such as dietary specialisations (Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0101">2003</a>; Ihalainen 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0162">2012</a>) and territoriality (Endler &amp; Rojas, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0098">2009</a>) affect which prey assemblages a predator may experience. For example, omnivorous and more specialised passerine birds respond differently when presented with aposematic invertebrates (Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0101">2003</a>). Similarly, great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) from Finland are more reluctant to attack aposematic prey than great tits from Bohemia, possibly due to a reduced exposure to warningly coloured invertebrates, and a higher proportion of neophobic and migratory birds in the population (Exnerová 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0102">2015</a>). On a finer scale, a predator's level of experience will depend on the number of encounters with defended prey, so may differ between age classes (Lindström, Alatalo &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0202" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0202">1999</a>). Seasonal fluctuations in overall predator naivety may occur as young predators learn to forage for themselves and sample aposematic prey for the first time, thereby impacting the relative benefits of conspicuousness and crypsis for defended prey at different times of the year (Mappes 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0219" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0219">2014</a>) and potentially favouring seasonal polyphenism, as seen in striated shieldbugs, 
  <span class="italic">Graphosoma lineatum</span> (Tullberg 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0389" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0389">2008</a>; Johansen 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0164" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0164">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, variation in predator traits interacts with other forms of variation in the whole community of organisms in a given habitat, such that the characteristics of this community, and the interactions between all its members, will ultimately shape the selective pressures acting on warning signal form. From the predators' perspective, the presence, abundance and nutritional value of alternative prey, as well as the effort required to locate them and the toxin load already ingested, all impact the net benefits of attack (Turner &amp; Speed, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0397" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0397">1999</a>; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0338" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0338">2003</a>; Rowland 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0315" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0315">2010c</a>; Carle &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0050">2014</a>; Skelhorn 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0350" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0350">2016</a>), and the strength of selection for convergence in prey signals (Fig. 
  <a rid="brv12460-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#brv12460-fig-0004">4</a>; Kokko, Mappes &amp; Lindström, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0181" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0181">2003</a>; Lindström 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0201" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0201">2004</a>). The diversity of prey coloration within populations is equally important, not only in shaping predator experience, but also because of the demands it places on predators' cognitive skills. Selective pressures for signal uniformity may be relaxed in more complex communities, as predator learning is limited by their ability to memorise multiple signals and their associated risks and benefits (Ihalainen 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0162">2012</a>). In an even broader ecological context, the predation risk experienced by the predators of aposematic prey themselves may also contribute to their response to warning signals (Lima &amp; Dill, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0195" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0195">1990</a>), due to variable costs of exposure to predators incurred by longer prey‐handling times, or increased searching behaviour to find alternative prey. As such, differences in both prey and predator communities among populations, as well as spatio‐temporal heterogeneity within populations, combine to produce variable selection pressures affecting warning signal form.
 </p>
</sec>
