<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0021" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Intraspecific interactions</span>
 </div>
 <sec id="brv12460-sec-0022" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Mate choice and parental effects</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mate choice can act either to reinforce or to disrupt the selection imposed on warning coloration by predators. The interaction between warning signals and sexual selection can occur when aposematic traits play a function in mate choice and recognition, or when there is a trade‐off between traits used in mate acquisition and those involved in predator defence. As anti‐predator defence is a key survival trait, we would expect that natural and sexual selection would work in tandem, with better protected individuals also gaining advantages during mating and reproduction, thus enforcing purifying selection on warning coloration. However, when this is not the case sexual selection may act to counter the effect of selection imposed by predators, allowing for polymorphism and other forms of warning‐signal variation to arise (e.g. Cummings &amp; Crothers, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0072">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sexual selection could also lead to sex‐specific differences in warning coloration. For example, increased brightness in male poison frogs could be the result of female preference for brighter males (Maan &amp; Cummings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0207" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0207">2009</a>; but see Meuche 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0242" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0242">2013</a>). Whether such selection would lead to true polymorphism in the eyes of predators depends on the strength of the respective pressures, as well as the sensitivity of the signalling system itself to evolutionary inputs. In the case of poison frogs, the colour cues selected for by females (i.e. brightness) may be different from those selected by predators (i.e. hue). Indeed there is evidence that 
   <span class="italic">Heliconiu</span>s and 
   <span class="italic">Melinaea</span> co‐mimics show increased interspecies variation in colour combinations that are less visible to their avian predators, allowing for ‘cryptic’ signalling of species identity (Llaurens 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0203">2014</a>) and similar patterns may exist for within‐species signalling. Alternatively, if the visual conspicuousness of both sexes is already very high, any increases as a result of sexual selection may have no effect on predator learning (Maan &amp; Cummings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0207" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0207">2009</a>; Crothers &amp; Cummings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0069">2013</a>). Variation in the strength of female preferences among populations (e.g. Maan &amp; Cummings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0207" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0207">2009</a>) may create divergent evolutionary trajectories in different populations, causing polytypisms to arise, whilst assortative mating or local morph preference can enable their persistence and even lead to the exaggeration of morph differences. In such cases, warning signals may constitute so‐called ‘magic’ traits, as they are both subject to ecological pressures from predators and contribute to non‐random mating, as is the case for many 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> species (Merrill, Chia &amp; Nadeau, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0239" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0239">2014</a>). Assortative mating by morph may also occur if individuals in a population have different anti‐predator strategies. For example, associating with a conspicuous individual may increase your own risk of attack if you are cryptic (Segami Marzal 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0332" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0332">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to assortative mating, disassortative mating, where individuals prefer to mate with colour morphs different from themselves, can also occur. For example, in the polymorphic 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius numata</span> females show a strong aversion to mating with males of their own morph, preferring instead males of a different morph to themselves. Thus, while males of rare morphs may suffer increased predation risk, they will also have a higher mating success with females of the common morph (Chouteau 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0059">2017</a>). This may be the result of heterozygote advantage, which has been suggested as a possible mechanism for the maintenance of many polymorphisms (Hedrick, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0144">2012</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, warning signals may not always be indicators of mate quality. Instead, there may be trade‐offs between traits related to predator defence and those that grant higher mating success. In addition, while selection on aposematic‐signal colour patterns is expected to be positively frequency dependent (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12460-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0002">II</a>), it could potentially be opposed if negative frequency‐dependent sexual selection also acts on the signals. Evidence for both phenomena has been found in the wood tiger moth. In this species white males have less‐effective warning signals (Nokelainen 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0264" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0264">2012</a>) than the yellow morph they coexist with, but gain higher mating success in white‐biased populations, despite showing no advantage over yellow males in offspring hatching success (Gordon 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0126">2015</a>). This could be due to differences in flying behaviour and mating effort (Rojas, Gordon &amp; Mappes, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0303">2015</a>). Thus, frequency‐dependent selection could allow yellow and white males to co‐exist, as whites compensate for their higher predation rate through increased mating success. Sexual selection may therefore allow for the maintenance of polymorphism within populations, in particular if it leads to, or is a consequence of, a trade‐off between anti‐predator defence and mating success/fecundity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While we naturally expect mate choice to influence offspring aposematic phenotype 
   <span class="italic">via</span> genetic inheritance, transgenerational non‐genetic effects are also likely to play a role, especially in determining continuous within‐morph variation in warning coloration (Winters 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0422" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0422">2014</a>). It is increasingly clear that offspring phenotype is influenced non‐genetically 
   <span class="italic">via</span> maternal investment in response to a multitude of abiotic and biotic variables present in the offspring environment (Wolf &amp; Wade, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0423" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0423">2009</a>; Day &amp; Bonduriansky, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0081">2011</a>). Mothers can alter offspring phenotype in response to mate ‘quality’ (‘differential allocation’; Ratikainen &amp; Kokko, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0291" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0291">2010</a>) and reliable cues of the offspring environment (‘anticipatory maternal effects’; Marshall &amp; Uller, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0224" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0224">2007</a>). In terms of mate choice, as mentioned above, male warning coloration has been shown to be influential in female mate choice in aposematic species (Nokelainen 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0264" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0264">2012</a>; Mishra &amp; Omkar, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0246" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0246">2014</a>). Theoretical and empirical work suggest two likely responses, that females will either increase investment in response to the brightness or colour of male warning coloration (‘positive differential allocation’; Sheldon, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0334" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0334">2000</a>; Horváthová, Nakagawa &amp; Uller, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0157" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0157">2012</a>) or decrease it (‘negative differential allocation’; Saino 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0321" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0321">2002</a>; Bolund, Schielzeth &amp; Forstmeier, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0023">2009</a>). Recent work provides the first evidence that such a phenomenon may take place, with female 
   <span class="italic">Adalia bipunctata</span> laying brighter eggs when mated with brighter males (Paul 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0280" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0280">2018</a>). This is important as offspring aposematic phenotype in early life can persist into adulthood (Winters 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0422" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0422">2014</a>) and such differential allocation could therefore facilitate the perpetuation of variation in male warning coloration through subsequent generations. However, it is worth noting that work on differential allocation has also shown that a female's reproductive response to signals of male ‘quality’ varies with female age and phenotype (Sheppard 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0336" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0336">2013</a>). Combined with other effects linked to maternal phenotype, condition, or maternal response to the offspring environment, this differential maternal investment in response to male phenotype is likely to lead to a mosaic of continuous colour variation within and among populations of aposematic species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12460-sec-0023" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(ii)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Social signals and competition</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If warning signals can be used as signals during mate choice, and there is evidence that they can, they may also play a role in other forms of intraspecific interactions such as male–male competition, dominance and territorial disputes. While there are many studies that show the importance of visual signals in such interactions [see Shreeve, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0345" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0345">1987</a>, Setchell &amp; Wickings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0333" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0333">2005</a>, López‐Idiáquez 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0204">2016</a> for examples], few have considered aposematic species. One example comes from work on male–male competition in the frog 
   <span class="italic">O. pumilio</span>; male brightness affected both their own behaviour and the behaviour of other males towards them. Brighter focal males were more likely to approach intruders to their territory, and brighter intruders elicited more calls and approaches than dull ones (Crothers, Gering &amp; Cummings, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0070">2011</a>). This suggests that continuous variation in male brightness may be a conditional signal in this species, and that male–male aggression may play a role in its maintenance within populations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intraspecific warning signals may also occur when conspecifics can benefit from signalling their presence to others, and by heeding such signals. This may arise when competition between conspecifics is particularly costly. Possible examples include larval coloration signalling the presence of existing larvae on potential host plants to ovipositing females in order to reduce larval cannibalism in the pipevine swallowtail butterfly 
   <span class="italic">Battus philenor</span> (Papaj &amp; Newsom, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0278" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0278">2005</a>) and bright colours in male damselflies signalling their presence to other males in order to reduce male–male mating attempts during scramble competition (Sherratt &amp; Forbes, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0342" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0342">2001</a>). While intriguing, honest communication of this sort seems unlikely to result in signal polymorphism, as it should also favour a single signal. If however, signals are dishonest, with signallers attempting to deceive the conspecific receivers, then there is the potential for red queen/chase away selection dynamics to unfold, similar to those that may occur during Batesian mimicry. Dishonest intrasexual signalling has been suggested as a potential reason for females displaying male‐like coloration, as this deceives mate‐searching males and reduces male harassment in butterflies (Cook 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0064">1994</a>) and damselflies (Hammers &amp; Van Gossum, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0142" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0142">2008</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As well as increased competition for resources, high conspecific density is linked to increased detectability by predators (Riipi 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0294">2001</a>). In aposematic species such aggregations actually augment signal strength and thus predator deterrence (Finkbeiner, Briscoe &amp; Reed, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0111">2012</a>; Rowland, Ruxton &amp; Skelhorn, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0314" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0314">2013</a>), changing the costs and benefits of large conspecific densities. This is reflected in the developmental ‘phase shift’ of the desert locust (
   <span class="italic">Schistocerca gregaria</span>). Coloration in these toxic locusts changes from a cryptic phenotype to an aposematic yellow and black when raised at high conspecific densities (Sword, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0373" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0373">1999</a>). This shift in anti‐predator strategy is a response to the increased likelihood of detection by predators when the cryptic locusts are in large aggregations. Predators learn to associate prey with toxicity more quickly when they are conspicuous rather than cryptic (Sword 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0374" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0374">2000</a>) and the detection costs of warning coloration are diminished by gregariousness (Gamberale &amp; Tullberg, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0117">1998</a>; Riipi 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0294">2001</a>). Conspecifics can therefore influence not only within‐ but between‐morph variation in aposematic signalling.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
