<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">III.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EVOLUTIONARY AND GENETIC CONSTRAINTS ON WARNING‐COLOUR DIVERSITY</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies of the proximate mechanisms underlying aposematic variation have a limited taxonomic scope (but see Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0025" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0025">VI</a> and see online Table 
  <a rid="brv12460-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12460-supitem-0002">S1</a> for more possibilities), focusing primarily on 
  <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> butterflies. Thus our review of the genetic and developmental pathways engendering diversity in warning colours is similarly largely based on insights gained from 
  <span class="italic">Heliconius</span>.
 </p>
 <sec id="brv12460-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(1)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographic isolation and range shifts</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many of the well‐studied polymorphic/polytypic aposematic species occur in the Neotropics, and consequently early hypotheses explaining polymorphisms and polytypisms relied on the Pleistocene refugium theory (Turner, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0391" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0391">1965</a>; Brown, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0040">1979</a>). This theory states that high rates of allopatric speciation/subspeciation resulted from fragmentation of tropical forests during climate warming, and then when climate cooled, and forests became continuous, species became sympatric (for discussion see Merrill 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0240" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0240">2015</a>). The Pleistocene refugium theory has been invoked to explain the diversity of warning colours observed in poison frogs, neotropical Lepidoptera, and other tropical species, with refugia in Europe potentially playing a similar role for temperate species. However, this theory has recently been criticised and, in the case of 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span>, time‐calibrated phylogenies indicate that diversity was present before the Pleistocene (Nelson 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0260" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0260">1990</a>; Whinnett 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0414" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0414">2005</a>; Dasmahapatra 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0077">2010</a>; Kozak 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0184" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0184">2015</a>; Merrill 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0240" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0240">2015</a>). The current working hypothesis for how geographic or microhabitat variation has led to polymorphisms includes several stages. First, polytypisms arise through parapatric populations (populations with a narrow contact zone and low levels of gene flow) 
   <span class="italic">via</span> a variety of non‐climatic mechanisms, such as genetic drift or adaptation to the local abiotic environment (Mallet, Jiggins &amp; McMillan, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0216">1998</a>). Then, once populations are established, either gene flow continues or they eventually become sympatric, producing polymorphisms that may be transient (Mallet 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0216">1998</a>; Joron &amp; Iwasa, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0168" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0168">2005</a>). Polymorphisms/polytypisms can similarly arise due to earlier divergence of one clade, followed by subsequent mimicry by another clade (e.g. Symula, Schulte &amp; Summers, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0375" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0375">2001</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0376" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0376">2003</a>; Sanders, Malhotra &amp; Thorpe, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0327">2006</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12460-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic basis of warning coloration</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Investigations into both 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Papilio</span> (swallowtail butterflies) species have shown that a handful of specific genetic loci and associated regulatory elements are responsible for the varied phenotypes these genera present (Kunte 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0189" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0189">2014</a>; Kronforst &amp; Papa, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0186">2015</a>; Nishikawa 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0263" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0263">2015</a>). While a limited number of loci controlling colour and pattern would seem to be a fairly large constraint on the evolution of phenotypes, in both groups it is in fact the basis for extensive phenotypic diversity, resulting from repeated selection (Nadeau
   <span class="italic">,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0255" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0255">2016</a>). For example, a number of key loci are known to control switches in pattern elements within the mimetic radiation of 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> butterflies [e.g. 
   <span class="italic">WntA</span> (Martin 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0225" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0225">2012</a>), 
   <span class="italic">optix</span> (Reed 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0292" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0292">2011</a>; Supple 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0370" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0370">2013</a>) and 
   <span class="italic">cortex</span> (Nadeau 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0256">2016</a>)]. Kronforst &amp; Papa (
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0186">2015</a>, p. 12) suggest that in 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> the phenotypic lability resulting from the influence of a small number of loci under strong selection creates a ‘virtually unlimited number of possible wing‐pattern phenotypes’. Intuitively, this makes sense as a smaller number of loci will increase each locus' contribution to the phenotype and thus each locus will be under stronger selection (Gavrilets &amp; Vose, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0119">2005</a>). Ultimately a simplified genomic architecture facilitates the diversification of warning coloration.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hybridisation and adaptive introgression among species have also contributed to the diversity of warning coloration in 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> (Mallet 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0214" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0214">1990</a>; Gilbert
   <span class="italic">,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0124">2003</a>; Heliconius Genome Consortium, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0147">2012</a>; Pardo‐Diaz 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0279" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0279">2012</a>; Wallbank 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0410" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0410">2016</a>). Although adaptive introgression and hybrid speciation both involve crossing individuals of different species, there is a difference that is worth noting as they are evolutionarily different mechanisms (Grant, Grant &amp; Petren, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0127">2005</a>). Adaptive introgression results from gene flow from one species into the gene pool of another species through backcrossing of a hybrid with one of its parent species and can result in adaptive genes becoming incorporated back into the parental species (Grant 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0127">2005</a>; Kronforst &amp; Papa, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0186">2015</a>). Examples of adaptive introgression in natural systems are rare although reported cases do exist. Among 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> butterflies, 
   <span class="italic">H. cydno</span> can hybridise with 
   <span class="italic">H. melpomene</span>, and Pardo‐Diaz 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0279" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0279">2012</a>) found repeated introgression of adaptive alleles from 
   <span class="italic">H. melpomene</span> in 
   <span class="italic">H. timareta</span>. Hybrid speciation differs from adaptive introgression in that novel genomes are created from two parental species, which can lead to novel adaptive peaks in the landscape (Kronforst &amp; Papa, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0186">2015</a>). Known hybrids include 
   <span class="italic">H. heurrippa</span>, a hybrid of 
   <span class="italic">H. melpomene</span> and 
   <span class="italic">H. cydno</span> in the wild (Salazar 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0324" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0324">2005</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0325" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0325">2008</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0323" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0323">2010</a>). Furthermore, 
   <span class="italic">H. elevatus</span> was formed during a hybrid speciation event but is thought to have the colour patterns of 
   <span class="italic">H. melpomene</span> introgressed into its genetic pool (Heliconius Genome Consortium, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0147">2012</a>), thus revealing a fine line between the dichotomy of introgression and hybridisation. There is also strong evidence that such hybrid‐trait speciation in 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> is promoted by tight genetic linkage between mate‐choice and colour‐pattern loci resulting in assortative mating based on wing colour patterns (Mavárez 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0229" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0229">2006</a>; Kronforst, Kapan &amp; Gilbert, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0187" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0187">2006a</a>; Melo 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0238" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0238">2009</a>; Merrill 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0241" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0241">2011</a>). For example, 
   <span class="italic">H. cydno</span> and 
   <span class="italic">H. pachinus</span> mate preference segregates with forewing colour in hybrids, indicating that colour preference and wing colour are controlled by loci that are pleiotropic effects of a single locus (Kronforst 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0188" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0188">2006b</a>). Although our knowledge of hybrid speciation and adaptive introgression has come from Müllerian mimics
   <span class="italic">,</span> it is possible that non‐mimetic polymorphic aposematic coloration has resulted from both mechanisms.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conversely, whilst some level of recombination can facilitate diversity in warning signals, too high a level has the potential to have a homogenising effect (Mayr, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0230" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0230">1963</a>), and hybridisation is not always adaptive (Arias 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0008">2016</a>). In polymorphic populations, there should be tight linkage between loci to facilitate the coexistence of several combinations of congruous alleles, thus producing several different phenotypes (Merrill 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0240" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0240">2015</a>). Genes that are closely linked (i.e. supergenes) facilitate multiple functional elements to segregate as a single Mendelian locus despite recombination elsewhere in the genome, and have been found to be associated with polymorphic mimicry (Brown &amp; Benson, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0042">1974</a>; Charlesworth &amp; Charlesworth, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0053">1975</a>; Turner, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0394" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0394">1977b</a>; Joron 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0170" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0170">2006</a>; Thompson &amp; Jiggins, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0384" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0384">2014</a>). 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius numata</span> has several coexisting discrete mimetic phenotypes in the same population that are coded for by a single supergene (Joron 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0167">2011</a>; Merrill 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0240" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0240">2015</a>). Unsurprisingly, similar supergene architecture is not present in the sister species of 
   <span class="italic">H. numata</span>, which do not have local polymorphisms (Huber 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0158" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0158">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many of the genes identified in 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> as controlling coloration are conserved across Lepidoptera (Nadeau, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0255" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0255">2016</a>; Nadeau 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0256">2016</a>), which comprise a significant proportion of aposematic species and their mimics (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12460-supitem-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12460-supitem-0002">S1</a>). Whether similar genetic architecture underlies warning coloration polymorphisms in aposematic species outside this taxon is not yet clear. Work in ladybirds (Tan &amp; Li, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0378" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0378">1934</a>; Komai, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0182" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0182">1956</a>; Majerus, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0210" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0210">1994</a>), colubrid snakes that are Batesian mimics (Davis Rabosky, Cox &amp; Rabosky, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0078">2016a</a>), and a poison frog (Vestergaard 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0408" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0408">2015</a>) indicate that morph variation in these species is also determined by a small number of gene loci. However, in contrast to the more complex supergene organisation seen in 
   <span class="italic">H. numata</span>, mimetic warning coloration in colubrid snakes is the result of a much simpler multilocus system (Davis Rabosky 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0078">2016a</a>). These differences can have important implications for evolutionary dynamics in mimicry, for example 
   <span class="italic">via</span> their influence on evolutionary rate or even a subsequent evolutionary shift from warning coloration to crypsis, a phenomenon common in snakes but not in 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> (Davis Rabosky 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0079">2016b</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given this evidence, it is clear that in order to understand how the genetic architecture of warning coloration enables or constrains morphological variation we need more information about the genes and gene networks at play, as well as a broader taxonomic coverage of the genetic architecture. Alongside the work already carried out on snakes, promising taxa include wasps (Perrard 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0284" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0284">2014</a>) and ladybird beetles (Lee 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0193" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0193">2011</a>). The latter are particularly intriguing as, unlike 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span> spp., there is scant evidence of hybridisation, and for two highly polymorphic species (
   <span class="italic">H. axyridis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">A. bipunctata</span>) multiple morphs have been produced in the laboratory that are scarce in the field (Majerus, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0210" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0210">1994</a>; Hodek, van Emden &amp; Honek, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0152">2012</a>). Furthermore, recent work on the wood tiger moth 
   <span class="italic">Arctia plantaginis</span> has revealed a negative genetic correlation between the efficacy of larval and adult warning coloration that likely contributes to the maintenance of observed variation in aposematic coloration at both life stages (Lindstedt 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0199" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0199">2016</a>). Investigations into other such genetic correlations outside of 
   <span class="italic">Heliconius</span>, for example between different components of the warning signals themselves (e.g. in 
   <span class="italic">Pieris</span> butterflies; Kingsolver &amp; Wiernasz, 
   <a rid="brv12460-bib-0178" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0178">1991</a>), may therefore also prove fruitful to further our understanding of warning‐signal variation.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
