<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12460-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">II.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">THEORY</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Explaining the existence of phenotypic variation in the face of selection has long challenged evolutionary biologists and theoreticians (Bull, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0046">1987</a>; Roulin, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0306" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0306">2004</a>). The outstanding colour variation in aposematic species has been viewed as particularly problematic due to the pervasive view of predators as a ‘purifying’ selective pressure moving warning coloration towards monomorphism (Mallet &amp; Joron, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0217" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0217">1999</a>). The majority of theoretical work investigating the factors that determine such colour variation focuses on Müllerian mimicry (Joron &amp; Mallet, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0169" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0169">1998</a>; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0340" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0340">2008</a>), involving the evolution and maintenance of a shared warning signal in sympatric, aposematic species (Müller, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0252" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0252">1879</a>). While it may seem counterintuitive to discuss the theory behind the evolution of similarity to understand how variation might arise and be maintained, the factors responsible for creating or reducing variation in signal form are likely to be closely linked. That is, selection pressures for or against mimicry and within‐species ‘purifying’ selection may have many features in common.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early models predicted that when there are multiple morphs present (whether they belong to one species or multiple species), an adaptive landscape characterized by multiple fitness peaks is generated, and predators should act to push the population as a whole to the highest adaptive peak by removing morphs defining lower adaptive peaks (generally the less common morphs), particularly when there are numerous prey types (e.g. Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0337" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0337">2002</a>; Beatty, Beirinckx &amp; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0014">2004</a>; Ruxton 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0320" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0320">2004</a>). In a similar fashion, if variation within a population is not discrete, and the peaks are short with wide tails, then predators should push the population's adaptive peak up by removing outliers, i.e. those individuals most different from the ‘norm’ (Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0339" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0339">2006</a>). Furthermore, where discrete variation occurs, the different phenotypes should evolve towards similarity as long as there is protective overlap between these distinct phenotypes in peak space, except when the phenotype is determined by a single locus (Turner, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0395" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0395">1983</a>). This occurs because overlapping space in the fitness landscape increases survival, and individuals that become increasingly more similar have overall higher survival (Mallet &amp; Joron, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0217" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0217">1999</a>). This situation should only arise where there is a sufficient amount of overlap in fitness peaks in the adaptive landscape – if there is barely any overlap then the selection acting against phenotypes in the overlap area should be similar to that of a novel, unprotected form. In general, this scenario is more likely when there is one adaptive peak that is higher than others due to either population size or higher toxin load, in which case it should ‘capture’ the alternative species/morph (Turner, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0395" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0395">1983</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These models predict that intraspecific warning signal variation would only persist under certain conditions. Firstly, variation can be maintained where population sizes are large (Plowright &amp; Owen, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0286" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0286">1980</a>) and there is spatial or temporal variation in local predator communities combined with simple drift, resulting in a mosaic of different phenotypes (Franks &amp; Noble, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0113">2004</a>; Ruxton 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0320" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0320">2004</a>; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0339" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0339">2006</a>). Secondly, and slightly more contentiously, new morphs could arise and reach high local frequency through mechanisms such as bottlenecks, drift, mutation, 
  <span class="italic">via</span> fluctuations in local ecological factors, or through relaxed selection due to a decline in predator abundance, causing peak shifts and the creation of new adaptive peaks (Turner &amp; Mallet, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0396" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0396">1996</a>). Notably, the exact mechanisms by which this occurs are rarely covered in any greater detail than the above list, and are often treated as a ‘black box’. Herein, we attempt to flesh out both the mechanisms and circumstances that may lead to the creation and maintenance of these new phenotypes and corresponding adaptive peaks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once new peaks are created, theory posits that local predators should exert uniform, frequency‐dependent selection for all conspicuous species/morphs towards this new peak (Sheppard 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0335" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0335">1985</a>). This stabilising selection can then work on surrounding populations via movement of hybrid clines or individuals migrating into new populations. This idea is known as shifting balance, and has been implicated in the evolution of geographical mosaic patterns in aposematic species and mimicry rings (Brown, Sheppard &amp; Turner, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0044">1974</a>; Turner, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0395" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0395">1983</a>; Mallet, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0212" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0212">2010</a>; Chouteau &amp; Angers, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0057">2012</a>). A key prediction of the shifting balance idea is that any form of polymorphism should be strongly selected against, and therefore temporary. Similarly, continuous variation in the aposematic signal should be generally selected against as stabilising selection should remove the most‐different individuals (i.e. those furthest from the ‘average’ appearance). This, of course, depends on predators being able to discriminate against and remember subtle differences in aposematic signal over time (see Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0006" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0006">IV</a> and Sherratt &amp; Peet‐Paré, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0343">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unfortunately, very little of the warning colour variation observed in wild populations meets the conditions outlined above. For example, multiple morphs of the same species are frequently found existing in the same locality (e.g. Brown &amp; Benson, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0042">1974</a>; Borer 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0028">2010</a>), often at low densities and/or low frequencies within a population (Chouteau 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0059">2017</a>). Furthermore, the idea that such polymorphisms are likely to be transient and unstable has also been empirically challenged; for example, polymorphism in the poison frog 
  <span class="italic">Oophaga pumilio</span> has been persistent on Bastimentos Island in Panama (Richards‐Zawacki, Yeager &amp; Bart, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0293" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0293">2013</a>) and relaxed selection resulting from a decrease in predators produces a vastly reduced predation rate even on novel or intermediate forms (Chouteau &amp; Angers, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0057">2012</a>). The mismatch between theory and empirical examples is in part due to the overly simplistic assumptions made about predator behaviour in earlier models. It is increasingly apparent that predator behaviour is more complex than early evolutionary models of warning coloration and mimicry allowed (Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0340" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0340">2008</a>; Skelhorn, Halpin &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0350" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0350">2016</a>), such as the early (and incorrect) assumption that predators sample a fixed number of prey to learn the association between signals and unprofitability (Rowland 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0310" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0310">2010a</a>). The incorporation of some of this complexity in predator behaviour into models, e.g. optimal predator sampling strategies based on exploration–exploitation trade‐offs (Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0341" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0341">2011</a>), has started to close the gap between theory and empirical examples resulting in scenarios where warning colour variation is predicted to arise within and among species (Aubier &amp; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0009">2015</a>; Kikuchi &amp; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0176" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0176">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As these more recent theoretical models demonstrate, less‐paradoxical predictions about the emergence and maintenance of multiple fitness peaks in warningly coloured species can be generated by incorporating predictions derived from empirical work on the complexity of predator behaviour. However, there is still a great deal of nuance in predator behaviour that has yet to be captured in theoretical models (see Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0006" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0006">IV</a>). It is also important to note that genetic mechanisms may facilitate or constrain variation (McLean &amp; Stuart‐Fox, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0236" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0236">2014</a>; see Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0003">III</a>) and that independent fitness peaks can easily be reinforced by alternative biotic and abiotic selection pressures (other than predation) that may also act upon warning coloration (Calsbeek, Hasselquist &amp; Clobert, 
  <a rid="brv12460-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12460-bib-0049">2010</a>; see Section 
  <a rid="brv12460-sec-0013" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12460-sec-0013">V</a>). Below we outline these and other factors that future models could take into consideration, hopefully facilitating convergence of model predictions with the variation observable in the warning coloration of aposematic species.
 </p>
</sec>
