<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global datasets used in this study include daily surface meteorology records, satellite remote sensing data for driving the ET and PET algorithms, and precipitation and discharge records for the water balance analyses and ET validation. Daily meteorological data were from the NCEP/DOE AMIP-II Reanalysis (NCEP2)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>. We verified the quality of surface meteorological inputs against measurements from ground observation networks and through intercomparison with two other meteorological reanalyses, and confirmed a generally good quality in these forcings (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Section 4</a>). Remote sensing radiative flux data, including clear-sky incoming solar shortwave radiation, all-sky downward solar shortwave radiation, and all-sky net shortwave solar radiation, were from the NASA World Climate Research Programme/Global Energy and Water-Cycle Experiment (WCRP/GEWEX) Surface Radiation Budget (SRB) Release-3.0 datasets (hereafter denoted as the SRB3.0) and the Clouds and the Earth’s Radiant Energy System (CERES) SYN1deg radiative fluxes. The SRB3.0 grid has a resolution of 1 degree latitude globally, and longitudinal resolution ranging from 1 degree in the tropics and subtropics to 120 degrees at the poles, while CERES SYN1deg has a resolution of 1° × 1°. We applied a statistical method to fuse the SRB3.0 data with CERES SYN1deg data by preserving the inter-annual variabilities and temporal trends of SRB3.0 on a grid cell-by-cell basis (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Section 5</a>). The other remote sensing inputs data include the 500-m MODIS-IGBP collection 5 global land cover classification
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>, 1-km global canopy height data
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>, 1-km AVHRR Tree Cover Continuous Fields data
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">38</a>, 1/12° semi-monthly Global Inventory Modeling and Mapping Studies (GIMMS3g) NDVI
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>, 0.05° bi-weekly University of Arizona Vegetation Index and Phenology lab (VIP) NDVI
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" href="#b40">40</a>, and 500-m MODIS NDVI. The GIMMS3g, VIP, and MODIS records are available from 1982–2011, 1982–2010, 2000-present, respectively. We applied the same fusion method for the radiation data to adjust the GIMMS3g and VIP records to match the MODIS record by preserving their inter-annual variabilities and temporal trends on a grid cell-by-cell basis (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Section 5</a>). The adjusted GIMMS3g and VIP records were combined with the MODIS record to produce a consistent long-term NDVI record as the input to derive biome-specific canopy conductance for our ET algorithm
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">9</a>. Global monthly precipitation data were derived from four independent sources, including Global Precipitation Climatology Project Version 2.1 (GPCP)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a>, Global Precipitation Climatology Centre Version 6.0 (GPCC)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>, and Climate Research Unit TS3.22 (CRU) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cru.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/cru_ts_3.22" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cru.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/cru_ts_3.22</span>) datasets. The global basin observed monthly river discharge data were compiled and provided by Dai 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
