<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sites</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our modeled streams are based on actual headwater streams in the Trask Watershed in northwestern Oregon, USA (
   <a rid="pone.0135334.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s001">S1 Fig</a>); this location is part of a regional effort to understand the effects of forest harvest and climate change on fish (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://watershedsresearch.org/trask/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://watershedsresearch.org/trask/</span>). We simulated Gus Creek, Upper Mainstem Trask, Pothole Creek, and Rock Creek. Precipitation in the Trask Watershed study area occurs primarily during winter and varies by elevation, with rain at lower elevations and a mix of snow and rain at higher elevations. These climatic conditions, combined with steep terrain and shallow soils, lead to flashy winter flows linked to winter storms, followed by declining flows in spring and an extended low flow period in late summer [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref027">27</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref028">28</a>]. Our study period captured three years that were marginally higher in mean annual precipitation (2758 mm · y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>, 2834 mm · y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>, 2783 mm · y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>), one year that was lower (2255mm · y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>), and one representative year (2626 mm · y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>) when compared to the long-term annual mean (2500 mm ·y
   <span class="sup">-1</span>) for the Trask River watershed [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref029">29</a>]. Daily mean stream temperatures were moderate year-round ranging from 6–12°C. The fish communities of these streams were dominated by resident Coastal Cutthroat Trout 
   <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus clarkii clarkii</span>, with sculpins 
   <span class="italic">Cottus</span> spp., juvenile Steelhead 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">mykiss</span>, and juvenile Coho Salmon 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">kisutch</span> at some sites. Movement of fish among study streams consists of a very small rate of exchange (&lt;1%, J. Dunham, unpublished data), which is likely not important demographically [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref030">30</a>]. In these coastal streams, resident Coastal Cutthroat Trout spawn in the spring generally in April and May with fry commonly emerging from April to August [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref031">31</a>]. Although trout grow all year, most growth for age 1+ trout occurs in winter and spring [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref032">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Streams varied in their local features (
   <a rid="pone.0135334.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s004">S1 Table</a>; [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>]). Average summer flows were similar among all streams, but flows in Rock Creek were more variable in summer. Although Rock Creek was the largest stream in watershed area, it had similar availability of habitat in summer relative to Gus Creek, which is half its watershed area. Gus Creek has the most variable flow in winter, and at times it exceeded flows in Rock Creek. Upper Mainstem was the coldest stream year-round, and it was the smallest in both watershed area and wetted summer area. Pothole Creek had the highest and most variable turbidity in winter and the lowest in summer.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The trout model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The individual-based trout model we used was version 5.0 of inSTREAM, downloaded August 30, 2014 (
   <a rid="pone.0135334.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0135334.g001">Fig 1</a>). This model has been fully described, and is publically available ([
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref021">21</a>]; 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.humboldt.edu/ecomodel" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.humboldt.edu/ecomodel</span>). Unless noted here, default parameter values for Cutthroat Trout and small streams were extracted from the literature [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>] and details of model calibration are in [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref003">3</a>]. InSTREAM has shown realistic trout responses for individuals [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref034">34</a>] and populations [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref035">35</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref037">37</a>]. Details of model calibration can be found in Penaluna et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>]. Although we calibrated inSTREAM to each stream using three years of trout population estimates from each field site, values of model calibrations were the same at three of the four streams, except for Upper Mainstem (
   <a rid="pone.0135334.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s004">S1 Table</a>). Of the parameters considered in a sensitivity analysis (baseflow, benthic and drift food, summer temperature, hiding cover, piscivory risk, redd scour, spawning gravel, velocity shelter, winter temperature), biomass of adult trout was consistently sensitive to baseflow, with higher baseflows resulting in greater biomass of adult trout for these streams [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref033">33</a>]. Although there are multiple stochastic elements in inSTREAM, it is not a highly stochastic model. Mortality is the main process represented stochastically. Other stochasticity occurs in initialization of model run (various aspects), assignment of length when trout emerge from eggs, whether a female that is ready to spawn does on an actual day, and mortality of eggs [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref021">21</a>]. Hence, differences in replicate model runs represent natural variability and uncertainty in stochastic processes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">InSTREAM captures many complexities of real streams. Within the inSTREAM environment, each study stream was represented as a reach (here, 210–250 m in length) made up of rectangular cells (here, 31–35 cells per reach). Reach-scale variables included flow, stream temperature, and turbidity, which varied daily. Each cell represented a unit of microhabitat from one to several square meters in area that had a specific depth, velocity, area of velocity shelter for drift-feeding, area of spawning gravel, and distance to hiding refuge. Stream depth and velocity varied daily with flow. Trout were represented as freely feeding individuals following emergence from gravel. Each trout was attributed with a length, weight, condition, and sex, and was assigned to a cell within which it feeds. Because trout were modeled as individuals, population dynamics emerged from the behaviors and fates of individual fish. The complete trout life cycle was represented in the model (redds, egg, fry, juvenile, adult). Redds were represented by both the number of eggs they contain and egg developmental status.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">InSTREAM operated at a daily time step following a set schedule of actions (in order: spawning, habitat selection, growth, survival, and egg development). At the start of each day, daily flow, temperature, and turbidity were taken from input files for each scenario, which are based on actual field observations. Depth and velocity for each habitat cell were updated based on the flow input. Hence, these daily updates allowed for changing environmental conditions corresponding to each scenario (see scenarios and model input sections for more details).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Female trout spawn once per year if conditions, including date, flow and temperature thresholds, and female size, were met. When conditions for spawning were met, female trout moved to a cell with spawning gravel and created a redd. The number of eggs deposited increased geometrically as a function of spawner fork length. Each breeding adult (female and male) incurs a weight loss of 20% to represent energy loss due to reproduction. The model follows egg survival, development, and emergence. The developmental stage of eggs within a redd was a function of temperature degree days. Each day, the model updates developmental stage, determining how many eggs die due to processes such as temperature stress and disease, scouring, or desiccation. The timing of spawning was important because flow and temperature fluctuations, both high and low, influenced egg mortality. When surviving eggs within a redd were fully developed, they were converted into new trout, analogous to emergence and first feeding in nature.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All trout selected a cell and feeding activity to maximize short-term (90 day) fitness, which was a function of the growth and survival probability offered by each potential cell [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref035">35</a>]. Habitat selection was executed in order of fish size, with the largest fish selecting cells first, representing a length-based hierarchy. The version of inSTREAM we used assumes that trout fed during daylight hours and competed for the food available in each cell [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>]. Both metabolic and activity costs are subtracted from growth (net energy intake) and growth emerges as a function of trout size and habitat conditions (depth, and velocity). However, trout can also lose energy during spawning season (if they mature and if they spawn). Food intake was limited by food availability and the trout’s ability to capture food. Food availability depends on how much food was in each cell and how much was consumed by competing trout. The ability to capture food depends on trout size (with increasing length because larger trout see and swim better) and habitat conditions. There are two modes of feeding for trout, drift-feeding or search feeding. Food intake was represented with a drift-feeding approach where trout capture invertebrates as they are carried within range by the current. Search feeding is active searching for food. It is the primary feeding behavior for young-of-year and consists of 10–20% of food supply for adults [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref036">36</a>]. The survival probability offered by a cell was determined by functions representing mortality due to predation by terrestrial animals, trout predation, disease and starvation, and high temperature. These functions depended on individual length and weight and on habitat variables. Hence, trout grew and survived according to growth rate and survival probabilities of the selected cell.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scenarios</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We designed this study to mimic changes in stream temperature and flows associated with separate and combined effects of forest harvest and climate change. In addition to these changes, we modeled a baseline scenario that mimicked the natural variability in temperature and flow observed from 2007–2011 at each stream. We generated 63 years of results for each scenario (duration explained in detail in section on model input). To account for two forest harvests on a 40-year rotation, we applied changes to stream flow and temperature due to forest harvest in years 1 and 41 for all of our analyses. To understand the influence of each environmental regime, we also compared the separate and combined effects of stream temperature and flow for each scenario.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To model the effects of forest harvest, we comprehensively assessed information from recent forest harvest studies in the region. We used a conservative scenario of changes in magnitude and timing of stream temperature and flow. Accordingly, our forest harvest scenario represented a composite of current practices that include riparian buffers and a 40-year rotation. More generally, the literature suggested increased summer temperatures, increased summer flows, and increased flow from winter storm events for 1–2 decades following each harvest. Hence, for each cutting, we elevated stream temperatures for 15 years, with the first five years having daily mean stream temperature increased by 0.37°C [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref022">22</a>] uniformly, followed by a gradual, linear decrease in daily mean stream temperature by 0.037°C each year for 10 years until recovery of baseline conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref025">25</a>]. Therefore, baseline temperature values were restored in year 16 and again in year 57 because that is when the forest canopy would be expected to be restored, providing shade to the stream. Responses of flow regimes to forest harvest are variable, but in the Coast Range of Oregon, alterations to flow regimes can last for 20 years with changes to storm events and seasonal low flows [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref023">23</a>]. We increased daily water yield by 20% on the days when a storm event occurred that generated flow &gt; 2 standard deviations above the annual mean, because although water yield increases from forest harvest are highly variable, they generally increase by approximately 20% [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref023">23</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref024">24</a>]. We increased summer (July-September) daily mean flows by 45% above baseline for five years [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref023">23</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref038">38</a>], then decreased summer mean flows by 2.25% per year for 15 years until baseline was reached in year 20 post-harvest and again in year 60, because as the forest regrows, more water is used by trees.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We generated the climate change scenario by increasing year-round stream temperatures and decreasing fall and winter flows. We increased stream temperatures by 0.06°C per year, a rate based on stream temperature trends occurring in the Pacific Northwest over the past 50 years [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref026">26</a>], reaching 3.78°C higher than baseline at the end of the study period. This final increase in stream temperature is within the range of predicted warming for the Pacific Northwest [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref039">39</a>]. We decreased mean fall flows by 0.25% (October-December) and mean winter flows by 0.49% (January-March) each year [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref027">27</a>], resulting in a gradual decrease over time that reached 15.75% below baseline for fall flows and 30.87% below baseline for winter flows at the end of the simulation. Streams of coastal Oregon generally have hydrographs dominated by rainfall, not snowmelt and, hence, key changes related to climate change are occurring during peak winter months due to decreasing rain and not during spring and summer snowmelt [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref027">27</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the combined scenario, we first made the changes from forest harvest and then added alterations from climate change.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model Input</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We parameterized the model for each stream with field measurements of habitat features recorded during seasonal low flow (August-September) in 2009. Measurements of habitat were completed and used to delineate cells. For each cell, we measured availability of velocity shelter and spawning gravel as well as distance to hiding cover. Depth, velocity, and water surface elevation of each cell were measured over a range of low, medium, and high flows from 2009–2010. We computed daily mean (arithmetic) of flow, stream temperature, and turbidity from field measurements recorded every 10 minutes from March 2007 to September 2011 in each of the four streams. Mean turbidity was measured using an instream nephelometer, which measures the scatter of a focused light beam by suspended solids. We evaluated multiple years of simulated data under each scenario (i.e., baseline, forest harvest, climate change, combined) for each stream. Because we had observations from only 2007–2011, we randomly selected the environmental regimes from one of those initial years every year for 67 years (a duration chosen for computational reasons). This ordering of years became the baseline scenario and was modified to create all alternative scenarios. Once the ordering of years was set for a scenario, then daily values of each environmental regime were read into the model. After we ran our scenarios, we ignored the first four years of data from all scenarios to eliminate initialization effects [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref020">20</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref021">21</a>]. Accordingly, we applied the changes in stream temperature and flow from scenarios beginning in year five, which became year one after initialization effects were eliminated. Therefore, we used a total of 63 years of results to analyze each scenario.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses of trout</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed output produced every 30 simulated days from five replicate model runs for each scenario. We averaged population biomass (g), growth (cm/month; fork length), and survival (proportion of total that survived in each age class) by season each year based on the five replicate model runs (
   <a rid="pone.0135334.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0135334.s003">S1 File</a>). Seasons include summer (July, August) and winter (January, February). Age classes during winter were restricted to ages 1 and older because the model assigns an additional year to each trout on January 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> every year (in keeping with convention in fisheries biology), thus there are no age-0 trout in winter. For biomass, growth, and survival, we used average responses of each trout age class (ages 0, 1, 2, 3+). Timing of fry emergence was evaluated as the median emergence date (Julian day at which half the age 0 fish had emerged), estimated using MATLAB and Statistics Toolbox Release 2012 (The MathWorks, Inc. Natick, Massachusetts, US; see code in [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref040">40</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated population biomass (g), growth (cm/month; fork length), and survival (proportion of total that survived in each age class) by season each year over the five replicate model runs. To provide an overall view of differences among streams and scenarios, we evaluated summer and winter responses of median biomass, growth, and survival for each age class for each scenario (baseline, forest harvest, climate change, and combined) across all 63 simulation years using non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis one-way analysis of variance on ranks. In cases of statistically significant differences (alpha ≤ 0.05) indicated by these analyses, we evaluated pairwise comparisons among the four scenarios using a non-parametric Tukey’s test on ranks. We focused these tests on deviations of responses from a stream’s specific baseline scenario to responses observed for that stream related to forest harvest, climate change, and combined scenarios (i.e., baseline vs. other scenarios). When the scenario for a stream deviated significantly from its own baseline, we also examined the direction and magnitude of the observed differences.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual trends of both the median date of fry emergence and difference in magnitude of biomass of scenario compared to baseline for each stream were evaluated using the Mann-Kendall test [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref041">41</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref042">42</a>]. This rank-based test is robust to outliers and non-linear trends [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref043">43</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref044">44</a>]. The Mann-Kendall trend values were corrected for serial correlation [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref045">45</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref046">46</a>] using the package FUME for R [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref047">47</a>]. We evaluated annual trends of date of fry emergence and difference in magnitude of the scenario of interest and baseline over three timescales, including up to year 20, from year 20 to year 63, and over the 63-year duration of the study for all scenarios. By examining the trend up to year 20, we capture the time period when forest harvest may have the greatest impact and in a timeframe that a trend signal could be detected.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The question of whether total biomass of trout in summer under each scenario differed from baseline values at each stream was examined using a Wilcoxon signed rank paired test with continuity correction using the package STATS for R. In addition, within the simulated scenarios of forest harvest and climate change, we tested the individual influences of stream temperature and flow on differences in biomass of trout in summer relative to baseline values. We tested the null hypothesis that the median of the difference between baseline and the other scenarios was symmetric about 0. A nonparametric confidence interval and an estimator for the pseudo-median for the difference between the scenarios was also computed [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref048">48</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref049">49</a>]. The Kruskal-Wallis, Mann-Kendall analyses, and Wilcoxon signed rank analyses were analyzed using software R ver. 2.15.1 [
   <a rid="pone.0135334.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0135334.ref050">50</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
