<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control simulations of the modern Antarctic ice-sheet</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climatological fields from the PlioMIP pre-industrial experiments are used to predict a modern AIS, which can be compared with the Bedmap2 reconstruction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. We use forcing fields from each of the seven PlioMIP climate models to run simulations with three ISMs, producing an ensemble of 21 control simulations. Whilst there is some consistency across the ISMs in the prediction of the grounded extent of the modern ice-sheet, especially over the EAIS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), there are considerable differences in the predictions of the extent of the WAIS and also the ice-shelves.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Simulated modern ice-sheets. Predicted modern ice-sheet surface height (m) and ice-shelf thickness (m) when using the climatological forcing fields from the PlioMIP climate models. Initial modern (Bedmap2) ice-sheet is shown in the top left for ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
     </span>. Note that ice-shelves are only simulated by the ANICE and SICOPOLIS ISMs
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5179_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e520" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A visual comparison of the simulated modern ice-sheets highlights some GCM–ISM combinations that result in a poor reconstruction of the present day ice-sheet. The final simulated modern AIS grounded ice volume varies considerably between the models (23.64 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span>–37.36 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">3</span>), and is generally larger than the Bedmap2 reconstruction (26.54 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">3</span>; volume difference between Bedmap2 and ISM predictions equates to a difference in sea level of between +6.3 m s.e. and −25.3 m s.e. (metres of sea level equivalent); ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). In order that we only consider GCM–ISM combinations that provide a reasonable representation of the modern AIS in our Pliocene analysis, we developed performance criteria to assess predictions of the modern AIS, whilst also comparing our results to the Bedmap2 AIS reconstruction (see Methods and Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This leads to the removal of MRI-CGCM2.3 and MIROC4m from the Pliocene analysis. Whilst it is beyond the scope of the current study to fully investigate the potential reasons for a volumetrically divergent prediction of the present-day AIS, we examine the likely climate forcings driving this (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of ice-sheet predictions. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">i</span> Ice-sheet presence prediction for each of the climate scenarios (as a percentage of the total ensemble members). Also shown is the middle (
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span>, 
     <span class="bold">j</span>), smallest (
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">g</span>, 
     <span class="bold">k</span>) and largest (
     <span class="bold">d</span>, 
     <span class="bold">h</span>, 
     <span class="bold">l</span>) ice-sheet configuration (surface height (m) and ice-shelf thickness (m)). Middle is the 5th ranking ice volume from the list of 10 SIA-SSA model results. Results from the control simulations of MIROC4m and MRI-CGCM2.3 are not included in this figure to allow better comparison between the presented scenarios
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5179_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e598" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that the control simulations presented here were not tuned to give an optimal representation of the AIS using the different climate forcing fields and each ISM used only one set-up for each experiment (see Methods). This was done in order to allow for the assessment of model dependency of the results (without having to take into consideration the impact of potentially different ISM parameter value choices). We have shown that five out of the seven GCMs lead to a reasonable representation of present-day Antarctica. This gives us confidence when using the same model set-up to assess the climate model dependency of mid-Pliocene Antarctic simulations. For clarity, we have excluded two of the GCM–ISM combinations from our Pliocene analysis, however, the results from these GCM–ISMs are shown in Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a> to 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
