<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A warm interval during the Late Pliocene (the mid-Piacenzian Warm Period; mPWP; 3.264–3.025 Ma) offers the most recent time in Earth history where global annual mean temperatures were on average 1.8–3.6 °C higher
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> and while variable, carbon dioxide concentrations are suggested to be elevated relative to the pre-industrial
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Estimates of sea level change between 10 and 30 m above present day
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> have been reconstructed based on geological evidence, suggesting that a significant contribution to sea level from both the Greenland and Antarctic Ice-sheets (AIS) is required at certain intervals within the mPWP. This makes the mPWP an important interval to understand in terms of future climate change and ice-sheet stability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extent and nature of the AIS during the mPWP remains uncertain. Sedimentological evidence from the ANDRILL core suggests that there were periods where no ice was present on West Antarctica (WAIS) during the Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. Marine records from the margin of East Antarctica also have been interpreted to suggest a dynamic EAIS margin at this time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. A more recent study used a combination of cosmogenic nuclide exposure ages alongside ice-sheet modelling to suggest that the EAIS continental interior could have been up to 600 m higher than present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Such limited direct proxy evidence means that ice-sheet modelling is particularly important in understanding more about the behaviour and dynamics of ice-sheets during the Pliocene.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous modelling studies have supported the geological inferences and shown the potential for significant ice-sheet collapse events during the Pliocene in West Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. However, models are not in agreement as to what degree the EAIS could vary during the warmer intervals of the Pliocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Transient simulations with ice-sheet models (ISMs) have not shown significant ice retreat in the areas that proxy data suggests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. However, studies using climate forcings derived from climate models with imposed Pliocene boundary conditions (e.g. the PRISM boundary conditions; Pliocene Research, Interpretation and Synoptic Mapping) to force shallow ice approximation (SIA) ISMs have shown the potential for ice-sheet reduction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. More recent studies have advocated the inclusion of alternative physics within ISMs in order to facilitate the simulation of different extents of the Pliocene AIS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, and these have shown the potential for marine incursions into the Wilkes and Aurora subglacial basins (SGB). Nevertheless, it is difficult to perform a true comparison between such previous studies due to the very different models and modelling frameworks that have been adopted.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Pliocene Model Intercomparison Project (Part 1; PlioMIP1)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> offers a unique opportunity to test the dependency of ice-sheet simulations to the climate model forcing that is implemented. The models used in PlioMIP1 are similar in terms of complexity (all having atmosphere, land-surface, coupled ocean and sea-ice components) and are all models that were represented in the IPCC 5th Assessment report
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. All of the PlioMIP1 models implemented PRISM3 boundary conditions for their mid-Pliocene experiment, which included a reduced AIS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> (see Methods). It has been shown previously, that whilst the PlioMIP1 model results have commonalities in terms of the large-scale features of Pliocene climate, there is substantial regional variation in the sensitivity of models to the implementation of the Pliocene boundary conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Therefore, it is useful to assess the impact of any simulated regional climate differences over Antarctica on the prediction of the Pliocene.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we present results from the Pliocene Ice-sheet Modelling Intercomparison Project (PLISMIP)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, which was initiated in order to understand the extent to which using different climate and ISMs changes the predicted ice-sheet configuration for the warm Pliocene. We use output from the climate modelling intercomparison project, PlioMIP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, to force ice-sheet simulations of the mPWP. The significance of using different ISMs has been demonstrated previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> and therefore, here we force three different ISMs (representing different levels of complexity; ANICE
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, SICOPOLIS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> and BASISM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>) and simulate equilibrium ice-sheets following the initial PLISMIP experimental set-up
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> (see Methods). Using our ensemble of simulations, we demonstrate that there is a high level of climate model dependency in the reconstruction of the present-day AIS as well as the mPWP AIS. This is especially so in terms of the reconstructed ice volume. For the Pliocene, we use both PRISM3 and present-day AIS configurations to initialise our ISMs. We show that in general when using PRISM3 initial conditions in the ISMs, there is a consistent reduction in the broad extent of the WAIS in the Pliocene. However, some ensemble members retain ice over the West Antarctic Islands, while others lose this ice completely. When using present-day ice-sheet initial conditions different outcomes arise. One model predicts a WAIS with an extent equivalent to modern, whereas the remaining ice-sheet simulations reduce the size of WAIS. Over East Antarctica, the areas of ice reduction in the Pliocene (when compared to modern) differ according to which climate forcing but also importantly which of the ISMs is employed. It is worthy of note that there is more consistency in the results when present-day initial conditions are used within the ISMs. We conclude that it is very important to acknowledge the likely biases in Pliocene ice-sheet simulation based on a single model or even combination of models. Whilst it is useful to show the plausible range in Pliocene AIS reconstructions as a result of choosing different GCMs or ISMs, it is difficult to use the results presented here to directly inform us about the exact configuration of the AIS during the warmest intervals of the Pliocene due to insufficient geological data constraints on the ice-sheet itself.
 </p>
</sec>
