<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">Citizens living in informal settlements (slums) constitute a significant percentage of the urban population. A recent estimate states that 32.7% of the world’s population in developing regions is living in slums (UN-HABITAT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">2011</xref>). There were more slum dwellers in 2012 than in 2000, a trend that will likely continue in the future (WWAP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2017</xref>). Slum dwellers frequently rely on unsewered communal toilets, use open spaces or dispose of faeces in polythene bags. The inequality in sanitary services is significant. For instance, in India 56% of the population in the top 20% (household-income groups) has access to piped water, compared with 6% of the bottom 20% (World Bank 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">2017</xref>). Rapid urban expansion aggravates these challenges and the people are also disproportionately affected by the impacts of climate hazards (Jamil 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2013</xref>; UN-HABITAT 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2013</xref>; Varis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">2006</xref>; WWAP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2017</xref>). The proportion of the urban population living in slums in China, India, Indonesia, Philippines and Thailand is, respectively, 25, 24, 22, 38 and 25% (UN 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2018b</xref>). Furthermore, groundwater dependency is high in Asia, especially throughout South Asia and China. Approximately one-third of Asia’s population (some 1 billion to 1.2 billion people) is reliant on groundwater (Hirji et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2017</xref>; WWAP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">2018</xref>). The provision of basic water services (drinking water and sanitation and wastewater treatment) in informal settlements faces an even greater challenge (WWAP 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">2017</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">2018</xref>). Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref> shows the relation between population living in slums with access to improved sanitation and improved water sources.
</p>
