<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We considered the potential problem of sample selection bias [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>] and spatial autocorrelation [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] associated with our vampire bat occurrence data, and to evaluate whether sampling bias and spatial autocorrelation was a concern in our dataset we evaluated patterns of distance among occurrence locations and evaluated the spatially-structured variance in our data [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. We used the ‘spatstat’ package [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] for R statistical software [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] for spatial point pattern analysis to compute distances among occurrence locations and to evaluate spatial autocorrelation. We then used this information to consider the distance among unique occurrence locations in our final dataset, patterns of spatial clustering in occurrence records, and whether nearest neighbor occurrence locations were likely to be spatially independent. We concluded that use of thinning or other bias correction procedures (such as target background approaches; [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]) were not necessary given that our purpose was to develop empirically-based hypotheses of the distribution of vampire bats in North America. Furthermore, we concluded that some bias correction procedures, such as target background approaches, might add unknown biases to the modeling dataset, and we concluded that we could not assume that any sampling bias in the vampire bat data was equivalent to the bias in a higher taxonomic group (such as that of the family Phyllostomidae) using easily accessible online data (such as that contained in the Global Biodiversity Information Facility data; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gbif.org</ext-link>).
</p>
