<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot4-ijerph-15-01884" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Effects of Climate Change on Specific Population Groups</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is one of the tragic ironies of our times that the population groups that have contributed least to greenhouse-gas emissions are the first and the hardest hit by the effects of these emissions. South Africa is ranked as the second most inequitable country in the world, where the poorest 20% of the population consumes less than 3% of total expenditure, and the wealthiest 20% consumes 65% [
  <a rid="B75-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-15-01884">75</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our ability to adapt to climate change may be shaped by the same inequalities that have become the fault lines of society in South Africa, above all, gender [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-15-01884">35</a>]. Rates of gender-based violence in the country are amongst the highest in the world, affecting 1 in 3 women during their lifetime [
  <a rid="B76-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76-ijerph-15-01884">76</a>]. Again, it would be important to investigate whether these rates rise even further following extreme weather events in the country, as has been reported elsewhere [
  <a rid="B77-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77-ijerph-15-01884">77</a>]. During food insecurity in the country, women and girls disproportionately suffer health consequences of nutritional deficiencies and carry additional burdens, such as travelling further to collect water during droughts [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-15-01884">35</a>]. According to a UNICEF report, children in South Africa are especially vulnerable to climate change, facing higher risks during extreme weather, malnutrition during food shortages, and respiratory disease from increases in pollen and dust [
  <a rid="B78-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78-ijerph-15-01884">78</a>]. Of the 57 million people in South Africa, about 8 million are infected with HIV, the largest number worldwide [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-15-01884">54</a>,
  <a rid="B79-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79-ijerph-15-01884">79</a>]. Immunocompromised populations may also be more susceptible to the increased pathogen loads associated with higher temperatures, when factors such as stigma and poor health have already undermined their resilience. Migration, which is related in part to climate change, creates additional risks for HIV acquisition [
  <a rid="B80-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80-ijerph-15-01884">80</a>]. Clearly, the interface between climate change and HIV in South Africa is complex and warrants careful study [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-15-01884">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extreme weather conditions will have considerable impacts on those who depend on climate-sensitive resources and ecosystems for their livelihoods. Soil drying, coupled with irregular rainfall caused by rising temperatures, particularly in the western regions of South Africa [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-15-01884">20</a>], constrains agricultural production. This is potentially most harmful for subsistence farming communities who are already prone to geopolitical and economic marginalization. Rainfall shortages, higher temperatures and reduced soil moisture have all been associated with internal migration in the country [
  <a rid="B81-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81-ijerph-15-01884">81</a>]. This is especially true of communities that are highly dependent on natural resources for their livelihood (e.g., firewood, seeds and wild foods) [
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-15-01884">34</a>]. Movement to vulnerable inner-city areas and informal settlements is particularly concerning as these areas have the highest risks of HIV transmission [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-15-01884">18</a>,
  <a rid="B58-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-15-01884">58</a>,
  <a rid="B82-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82-ijerph-15-01884">82</a>]. These patterns, termed eco-migration, can accentuate the already high levels of urbanization in the country. Of note, migration carries increased risks of sexual violence for women and some female migrants in South Africa may have few options for survival other than sex work [
  <a rid="B83-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83-ijerph-15-01884">83</a>]. Eco-migration also erodes social networks—the practical and emotional resources underpinning health and well-being—and has fomented conflict in sub-Saharan Africa [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-15-01884">26</a>]. The potential for this to happen also in South Africa is high, as migration related to climate change may bring already festering xenophobic attitudes to the fore, and generate conflict and violence [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-15-01884" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-15-01884">26</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
