<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">Stickleback mothers adjusted the allocation of resources to eggs depending on the environment they experienced just prior to spawning, during the last phases of reproductive conditioning and egg maturation. On average, females acclimated to a constant mean temperature of 21 °C produced smaller eggs than females acclimated to a constant mean of 17 °C, and to both predictably variable and stochastic temperature regimes. Mean egg size also traded-off with clutch size, in that larger clutches were comprised of smaller eggs, and this was most evident for females acclimated to 21 °C (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref>). Female size is considered to be the best predictor of reproductive output in stickleback
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. Here, egg allocation varied with maternal acclimation environment independent of female size, suggesting that the egg size plasticity shown was likely not due to physical size constraints
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>, but possibly reflects selection for different sized offspring in different environments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. Egg size plasticity in response to oviposition temperature has been demonstrated in numerous taxa
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>, and larger eggs from females acclimated to 17 °C versus smaller eggs from females acclimated to 21 °C has been shown in two previous studies of this population
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. Large offspring from mothers acclimated to cold conditions is a common pattern of egg size variation, and may be selected for if larger offspring perform better at lower temperature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. Likewise, there is evidence suggesting that smaller eggs may be advantageous in warm conditions due to their lower oxygen demands
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. In both cases, such egg size plasticity would constitute adaptive TGP
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. However, this will depend on relative embryo and yolk sizes, in conjunction with their specific oxygen demands and their relationship to offspring performance in different environments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>, which remains to be tested for stickleback. Alternatively, females acclimated to a stressful constant 21 °C environment produced smaller eggs in favour of fecundity (selfish maternal effect 
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>), enabling them to maximise their own fitness over offspring fitness
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>. Variation in egg size and clutch size are discussed here in terms of maternal thermal environment (see also ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>), but how eggs are matured/allocated just prior to spawning can depend on a number of factors such as photoperiod
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>, salinity 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>, food availability (i.e. condition of the female
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>), age of the female
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, predators
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> and parasites
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>. Within the female, physiological processes like stress hormone
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>, yolk steroid
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup>, testosterone
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup> and carotenoid production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup>, as well as trade-offs with other traits like lateral plate production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup> and immune response
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>
 </sup> can also lead to variation in features of eggs and clutches. For the marine stickleback population studied here, little is known about habitat variability in the open sea where they overwinter and where the early stages of ova maturation begin
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>, but adults aggregate into small tidal channels and salt marsh pools for spawning starting in late spring (just prior to the last phases of egg maturation) where the habitat conditions (biotic and abiotic) are similar for all females (Shama, pers. obs.).
</p>
