<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of our survey experiment indicate that objective information about the scientific consensus has a short-run effect on the public’s beliefs about climate change. However, we do not observe an increase in either the public’s view that policy action is warranted or their willingness to donate real funds toward climate change causes. The lack of updating based on objective information in this context is consistent with a number of explanations, including strong priors, self-justification bias, selective attention, cultural norms, partisan bias, and information discounting [
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref022">22</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref024">24</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment also reveals a great degree of skepticism among the treated respondents toward the information about what scientists believe. The skeptics among the treated also believed that scientists were less certain about climate change relative to the control group. It is also possible that this “information discounting” stems from the partisan bias associated with the issue of climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref024">24</a>]. That is, conservative respondents may be more dismissive of the information because the Republican Party is typically skeptical of climate change. Finally, our findings are also consistent with the randomized survey evidence of skepticism toward information in other contexts, such as views and policy preferences for taxation and redistribution [
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref025">25</a>]. To shed light on the optimal design of information provision, further exploration of the different mechanisms behind the observed updating patterns would be useful.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numerous correlational studies have explored the relationships between climate change beliefs and various individual characteristics, such as political ideology, age, and education [
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref017">17</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref026">26</a>]. However, correlational findings often have ambiguous causal implications. For example, researchers have found that individuals who underestimate the degree of scientific consensus are also less likely to support policies that would combat climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0151469.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0151469.ref027">27</a>]. This finding has at least two possible explanations. One is that becoming informed about the scientific consensus increases support for policies aimed at combating climate change. Another is that those who are most concerned about climate change seek out more knowledge about the scientific consensus, thus becoming more informed. Our findings suggest that the former explanation is unlikely, at least in our sample: we find no evidence that providing information about the scientific consensus affects policy preferences or raises willingness to pay to combat climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our sample was not large enough to make further conclusions about the heterogeneity of the effects by demographic characteristics of the respondents, such as ideology, education, or prior climate change knowledge. We are also unable to make definitive conclusions about the long-run persistence of informational effects. Replicating the experiment with a larger sample size would be a fruitful path for future research.</p>
</sec>
