<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32335-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed the breeding ecology of four species of passerine birds in nest boxes in relation to the intensity of urbanization across Europe, North Africa, and the Middle East. Nest box characteristics, habitat, and geographic location were included in the models to account for potentially confounding environmental effects other than that of intensity of urbanization. To our knowledge, this is the first large‐scale study of the relationship between intensity of urbanization and avian breeding ecology. The intensity of urbanization was not correlated with laying date in the four species, while clutch sizes decreased with increasing intensity of urbanization in both collared and pied flycatchers.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all four species, our large‐scale analysis confirmed correlations between laying date, clutch size, and various environmental factors which have previously been demonstrated in single‐specific studies (Van Balen 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0090">1973</a>, 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0091">1984</a>; Mertens 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0050">1977</a>; O'Connor 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0056">1978</a>; Pearson and Lack 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0059">1992</a>; Summers and Taylor 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0086">1996</a>; Both and Visser 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0008">2001</a>; Ahola et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0001">2004</a>; Both et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0009">2004</a>, 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0010">2006</a>; Mänd et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0048">2005</a>; Arriero et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0003">2006</a>; Mizuta 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0051">2006</a>; Both and te Marvelde 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0007">2007</a>; Charmantier et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0016">2008</a>; Magi et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0046">2009</a>; Sisask et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0077">2010</a>; Mainwaring et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0047">2012</a>; Chmielewski et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0017">2013</a>; Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0015">2014</a>; Møller et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0053">2014</a>; Ruffino et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0067">2014</a>; Vatka et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0092">2014</a>). Thus, we focus the remainder of the discussion on the correlation between intensity of urbanization and breeding ecology.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urbanization is an ongoing process that has intensified over time and differs among countries. Indeed, temporal changes in urbanization varied between 0.1% per year in the Netherlands measured in 1992 (WRR 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0099">1992</a>) to more than 2% per year in France between 2000 and 2010 (Clanché and Rascol 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0018">2011</a>). With these differences in rate of urbanization, it was difficult to take temporal change in urbanization into account. In order to verify the validity of our measure of intensity of urbanization among years, we only analyzed data collected after 2000. However, we still found qualitatively similar results (analyses not shown). Thus, the use of a unique intensity of urbanization for a specific year seemed not to be an issue for the analysis of the correlation between urbanization on breeding phenology. Indeed, even if European cities did not grow at the same speed, a highly urbanized city in mid‐century is also likely to be equally highly urbanized today (EEA 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0026">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laying date was not related to the intensity of urbanization in any of the four species. The lack of significant relationship between the intensity of urbanization and laying date in all four species could be due to lack of sensitivity to urbanization or due to the proxy, the intensity of urbanization, used to quantify the degree of human impact on the environment. According to the relationship between CORINE land cover code and the intensity of urbanization, the index measured was related to anthropogenization of areas although radius could still be too small for some borders of monitored study plots. Although we studied local urbanization of study plots, it is still possible that human impact affects the environment at larger scales (Bol'shakov et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0006">2001</a>; Pickett et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0060">2011</a>; Gil and Brumm 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0030">2013</a>; Johnson et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0039">2013</a>; Vittoz et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0097">2013</a>). The findings could be affected by the lack of highly urbanized plots, because the plots sampled in our study did not cover all variation in the intensity of urbanization in all European countries. Data were limited by availability of boxes differing in extent of urbanization, although we consider that this is not a serious issue in the present study because rural plots included natural plots as forests and agricultural or industrial plots where people also live. Nevertheless, we have shown that laying dates of the four species were not related to the intensity of local urbanization and lack of data does not seem to affect this result.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collared and pied flycatchers showed a significant negative relationship between the intensity of urbanization and clutch size. Migratory status could be the decisive factor for the decrease in clutch size in flycatchers and the absence of such a difference in tits. The lack of a significant effect in tits could also be due to differences in thermal capacity as blue and great tits live at more variable latitudes than collared and pied flycatchers (Fig. S3; Svensson 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0088">1992</a>; Del Hoyo et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0019">2007</a>) and hence display a larger range of temperature tolerance. This is the first time that a negative relationship has been shown between clutch size and intensity of urbanization in the two long‐distance migratory flycatcher species (Both et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0009">2004</a>, 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0010">2006</a>; Laaksonen et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0042">2006</a>; Mizuta 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0051">2006</a>; Pulido 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0062">2007</a>; Sisask et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0077">2010</a>; Massa et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0049">2011</a>; Smallegange et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0080">2011</a>). More studies are needed to understand the underlying mechanism of intensity of urbanization on clutch size, and it is even possible that a reduction in clutch size was due to a combination of local conditions (Pearson and Lack 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0059">1992</a>; Both et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0010">2006</a>) determined by ambient temperature (Burrows et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0013">2011</a>; Stocker et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0085">2013</a>), artificial night light (Small and Elvidge 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0079">2011</a>; Dominoni et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0022">2014</a>; Fonken and Nelson 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0028">2014</a>), food availability (Stenning 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0083">1995</a>; Robb et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0065">2008a</a>,
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0066">b</a>; Saggese et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0069">2011</a>), avian population density (Krebs 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0040">1970</a>; Stenning et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0084">1988</a>), nest predation by cats (Zanette et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0100">2011</a>), or vandalism (Brahmia et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0011">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, in this first large‐scale study of life history traits and intensity of urbanization we showed a complex species‐specific major relationship between intensity of urbanization and breeding. The underlying mechanisms for the relationships between life history and intensity of urbanization remain to be determined. However, we propose that effects of food abundance or quality, avian population density, temperature, noise, pollution or disturbance by humans may on their own or in combination affect laying date and/or clutch size. Experiments could compare main and interactive effects of bird feeding by humans (Chamberlain et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0014">2009</a>) and temperature increases on advances in breeding date in neighboring urban and rural habitats.
 </p>
</sec>
