<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32335-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and Methods</div>
 <sec id="ece32335-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blue tits (
   <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>), great tits (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), pied flycatchers (
   <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>), and collared flycatchers (
   <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>) are all small insectivorous passerine birds that breed commonly in nest boxes in large parts of Europe. The two species of tits are residents or partial short‐distance migrants depending on their population (Nowakowski and Vähätalo 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0055">2003</a>), while the two flycatchers species are both migratory and spend the winter months in sub‐Saharan West Africa.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece32335-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual mean breeding dates, clutch sizes, and sample sizes of first clutches derive from an exhaustive attempt to obtain information from populations across Europe, North Africa, and the Middle East (Fig. S1; Møller et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0053">2014</a>). We used mean laying date per population and year of (1) 101 study populations of blue tits, with a total of 1127 study years for laying date, and 1124 study years for clutch size; (2) 138 study populations of great tits, 1439 study years for laying date, and 1436 for clutch size; (3) 66 study populations of collared flycatchers, with a total of 592 study years for both parameters; and (4) 23 populations of pied flycatchers, with a total of 259 study years. Information on latitude, longitude, altitude, mean study year, species, dominant breeding habitat (coniferous, deciduous, evergreen, or mixed forest), nest box floor area, and nest box material (wood or concrete) for all study plots were provided by scientists or reported in a previous publication (Møller et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0053">2014</a>). Borders and numbers of nest boxes depended on study plot as determined by researchers who monitored the populations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increase in the density of buildings is known to correlate with the increase in the total number of individual birds (Hedblom and Söderström 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0034">2010</a>), advanced laying date (Shustack and Rodewald 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0074">2010</a>), and increased breeding success (Ryder et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0068">2010</a>; Hedblom and Söderström 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0035">2012</a>). All study plots were classified by each researcher who followed a given population as either rural or urban without single criterion (see Supporting information). This dichotomy is commonly used, but inadequate when quantifying human influence because rural areas include agricultural, and natural habitats and urban areas include parks and gardens with mature trees. Therefore, we recorded an estimate of the density of buildings using information from ArcGIS Earthstar Geographics for each of the study plots (
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 199). An index of the “Intensity of urbanization” was obtained by dividing the number of buildings by the area of the study site (see next paragraph) followed by log‐transformation of density of buildings adding a constant of one to avoid values of zero and to normalize the data. We counted the number of roofs of each building as the number of roofs with one color and one direction, while L‐shaped buildings were counted as two roofs. We used the density of buildings and not the cover by roads or buildings because these descriptive variables are strongly positively correlated (Shustack and Rodewald 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0074">2010</a>). The percentage of built‐up area within 1‐km circles was strongly positively correlated with the number of roofs (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>1,32</sub> = 81.24, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.01), and previous studies have shown that it is the density of buildings that is correlated with population density (Brumm 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0012">2004</a>; Barber et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0004">2010</a>; Snell‐Rood 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0081">2012</a>; Slabbekoorn 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0078">2013</a>). Study plot coordinates were in the form 12.12345°N, 12.12345°E for 160 study plots and in the from 12.12°N, 12.12°E for 39 study plots where the scientist was inaccessible either due to retirement or death, and it was thus impossible to provide more precise coordinates (see Table S1). Analyses were repeated without these imprecise coordinates for study plots, but we found qualitatively similar results.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the effect of measurement scale, we analyzed the intensity of urbanization in subsamples of 34 of 199 study plots (all study plots classified as urban [
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 14] and 20 randomly selected from 185 plots classified as rural plots by scientists [see Table S1]) within a radius of 200, 500, and 1000 m from the centre of each study plot, by visually counting the number of buildings on digital orthophotographs (Shustack and Rodewald 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0074">2010</a>). The density of buildings was measured at the scale that allowed identification of different roofs, depending on the orthophotographs available. We used a radius of 200 and 500 m, respectively, because they were similar to the size of most study plots and 1000 m to validate the method at the level of study plots. Use of a buffer circular area around study plots provided conservative estimates of intensity of urbanization among study plots. However, the intensity of urbanization at the three distances was highly repeatable (200–500 m, 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>33,34</sub> = 8.20, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.01, intraclass correlation coefficient = 0.78 (Lessells and Boag 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0045">1987</a>) and 200–1000 m, 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>33,34</sub> = 3.30, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.01, intraclass correlation coefficient = 0.54). Therefore, we only used an estimate of the intensity of urbanization (log[number of building/area of study + 1]) for a radius of 200 m in the subsequent analyses; that is, an intensity of urbanization was recorded in each of the study plots in 2015 (
   <span class="italic">N </span>=
   <span class="italic"> </span>199). Our indicator of intensity of urbanization was on average 59 buildings/km
   <span class="sup">2</span> (SE = 4, range 0–1305 buildings/km², 
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 199). We found a strong positive relationship between the binomial score of urbanization provided by scientists and intensity of urbanization near the nest box plots for all study plots (Student 
   <span class="italic">t</span>‐test: 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>df</sub> = −6.26
   <sub>14.19</sub>, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.0001, Mean ± SE log‐transformed index = 0.47 ± 0.06 and 2.15 ± 0.26 for rural (
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 185) and urban (
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 14) areas, respectively, see Fig. S1A). Moreover, intensity of urbanization was negatively related to CORINE land cover code (Kendall rank order test: 
   <span class="italic">τ</span> = −0.46, 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>df</sub> = −7.11
   <sub>189</sub>, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.0001, 
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 191, see Fig. S1B). CORINE land cover code assessed the land cover in classes (agricultural areas, artificial surfaces or forests areas), with values decreasing with degree of anthropogenization of areas. Theses codes were available for most areas of Europe, but not North Africa and Middle East. Intensity of urbanization in agricultural areas was intermediate between that in urban and natural sites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For some species, latitude is correlated with laying date (Mainwaring et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0047">2012</a>; Ruffino et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0067">2014</a>), and to take this into account, geographic coordinates of study plots were used in the models. Latitude and longitude of the study plots were positively correlated (Pearson 
   <span class="italic">r </span>=
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.48, 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>197</sub> = 7.64, 
   <span class="italic">P </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.01, Fig. S2), although not causing problems of collinearity (based on correlograms; Dormann et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0023">2007</a>). The interaction between longitude and latitude and quadratic terms for latitude and longitude were entered in models to account for nonlinear relationships and spatial autocorrelation (Legendre 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0044">1993</a>). There was no autocorrelation in model residuals (Moran test; Dormann et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0023">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collared flycatchers only used wooden nest boxes, while the two species of flycatchers were absent from evergreen habitats.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece32335-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in R v. 3.2.0 (R Core Team 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0063">2015</a>). Explanatory variables were correlated, but coefficients were small (see Table S2). We used linear mixed models and backward elimination of factors using Akaike's information criterion (AIC) to select the best predictive model to explain variation in laying date (package nlme, function lme, method REML and package car, function Anova, type III). The initial model included the three‐way interaction (latitude × species × intensity of urbanization), two‐way interactions (latitude × species, species × intensity of urbanization, latitude × intensity of urbanization and latitude × longitude), study plot as random factor and intensity of urbanization, log‐transformed altitude, latitude, latitude squared, longitude, longitude squared, nest floor surface, material of nest box and dominant habitat as fixed factors. As the three‐way interaction was significant (see Table S3), models were subsequently developed and performed for each of the four species separately.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second part, for species for which the interaction between latitude and intensity of urbanization and the main effect of intensity of urbanization were not significant, the initial model to explain variation in clutch size included two‐way interactions (latitude  × intensity of urbanization and latitude × longitude), study plot as random factor and intensity of urbanization, laying date, log‐transformed altitude, latitude, latitude squared, longitude, longitude squared, nest floor surface, material of nest box, and dominant habitat as fixed factors. Altitude was log‐transformed to avoid residuals of models that deviated from normal distributions. As discussed in detail above, we used linear mixed models and backward elimination of factors using AIC (package nlme, function lme, method REML and package car, function Anova, type III).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several nests were followed in each plot and each year (blue tits: from 1 to 154 nests, mean ± SE = 17 ± 22 nests per year and per plot/great tits: from 1 to 210 nests, mean ± SE = 20 ± 24 nests per year and per plot/collared flycatchers: from 1 to 159 nests, mean ± SE = 26 ± 19 nests per year and per plot/pied flycatchers: from 1 to 189 nests, mean ± SE = 50 ± 35 nests per year and per plot). The number of nests per year and per study plot was used for weighting each data point, thereby assuring that each observation contributed to the models relative to the level of sampling (Draper and Smith 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0024">1998</a>; Kutner et al. 
   <a rid="ece32335-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0041">2004</a>). Likelihood ratio tests (LRT) were manually calculated for the random effect of study plot. No residuals of final models deviated from normal distributions.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
