<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32335-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in R v. 3.2.0 (R Core Team 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0063">2015</a>). Explanatory variables were correlated, but coefficients were small (see Table S2). We used linear mixed models and backward elimination of factors using Akaike's information criterion (AIC) to select the best predictive model to explain variation in laying date (package nlme, function lme, method REML and package car, function Anova, type III). The initial model included the three‐way interaction (latitude × species × intensity of urbanization), two‐way interactions (latitude × species, species × intensity of urbanization, latitude × intensity of urbanization and latitude × longitude), study plot as random factor and intensity of urbanization, log‐transformed altitude, latitude, latitude squared, longitude, longitude squared, nest floor surface, material of nest box and dominant habitat as fixed factors. As the three‐way interaction was significant (see Table S3), models were subsequently developed and performed for each of the four species separately.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second part, for species for which the interaction between latitude and intensity of urbanization and the main effect of intensity of urbanization were not significant, the initial model to explain variation in clutch size included two‐way interactions (latitude  × intensity of urbanization and latitude × longitude), study plot as random factor and intensity of urbanization, laying date, log‐transformed altitude, latitude, latitude squared, longitude, longitude squared, nest floor surface, material of nest box, and dominant habitat as fixed factors. Altitude was log‐transformed to avoid residuals of models that deviated from normal distributions. As discussed in detail above, we used linear mixed models and backward elimination of factors using AIC (package nlme, function lme, method REML and package car, function Anova, type III).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several nests were followed in each plot and each year (blue tits: from 1 to 154 nests, mean ± SE = 17 ± 22 nests per year and per plot/great tits: from 1 to 210 nests, mean ± SE = 20 ± 24 nests per year and per plot/collared flycatchers: from 1 to 159 nests, mean ± SE = 26 ± 19 nests per year and per plot/pied flycatchers: from 1 to 189 nests, mean ± SE = 50 ± 35 nests per year and per plot). The number of nests per year and per study plot was used for weighting each data point, thereby assuring that each observation contributed to the models relative to the level of sampling (Draper and Smith 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0024">1998</a>; Kutner et al. 
  <a rid="ece32335-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32335-bib-0041">2004</a>). Likelihood ratio tests (LRT) were manually calculated for the random effect of study plot. No residuals of final models deviated from normal distributions.
 </p>
</sec>
