<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. Selection Line Characteristics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental evolution is usually based on replicated lines with no/low genetic variation or replicated lines with standing genetic variation. Classically, experimental evolution with unicellular organisms, such as 
  <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> has used multiple identical clones to investigate evolution, with resulting variation stemming solely from novel mutations [
  <a rid="B137-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137-biology-01-00411">137</a>]. Similarly, studies with multicellular organisms such as 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span> make use of iso-female lines (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> founded with one female) to simulate clonal lines [
  <a rid="B138-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B138-biology-01-00411">138</a>]. Generally, though, multicellular organisms are more frequently used in experimental evolution experiments where populations start with standing genetic variation [
  <a rid="B139-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B139-biology-01-00411">139</a>]. Initial genetic variation can be manipulated to varying degrees as part of the investigation of the selection pressures under study. With regard to climate change, experimental evolution could hence be applied to investigate the evolutionary potential of populations with different initial genetic diversities qualitatively and quantitatively. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A further climate change-relevant application of experimental evolution is to manipulate the size or density of different populations. Using this idea, it has been shown that allopatric populations of the fly 
  <span class="italic">Sepsis cynipsea</span> have a larger potential to diverge reproductively if the populations were of high density rather than low density [
  <a rid="B140-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B140-biology-01-00411">140</a>,
  <a rid="B141-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B141-biology-01-00411">141</a>]. This finding has also been confirmed in another species [
  <a rid="B142-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-biology-01-00411">142</a>]. Such an approach could be employed to obtain standardized information about the minimal population size necessary to survive different strengths of environmental change. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using small and rapidly replicating organisms for such experiments has the advantage that evolutionary consequences can be monitored over many generations, for example, in order to measure time to extinction, such as shown by Bell and Gonzalez [
  <a rid="B143-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-biology-01-00411">143</a>] or Drake and Griffen [
  <a rid="B144-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144-biology-01-00411">144</a>]. Nevertheless, the same principles of manipulating effective and operational population sizes could be applied more widely, such as on organismal communities using mesocosms as proposed by Cohen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="B145-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145-biology-01-00411">145</a>]. In general, to represent natural systems more realistically, replicated selection lines should be viewed as multiple populations, where different environmental treatments can be applied. By using cages in the field, such as the artificial ponds used by Bolnick [
  <a rid="B146-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B146-biology-01-00411">146</a>], even organisms, which do not easily breed in the lab, could be used in future studies.
 </p>
</sec>
