<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2. Evolutionary Drivers and Mechanisms</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In experimental evolution experiments, it is possible to manipulate natural selection, sexual selection, drift, bottlenecks, etc., including different levels of strength and combinations of these processes [
  <a rid="B147-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B147-biology-01-00411">147</a>]. Natural selection can be imposed by subjecting populations to altered environmental conditions, which has been applied in many studies investigating adaptation to, for example, different temperatures [
  <a rid="B148-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B148-biology-01-00411">148</a>,
  <a rid="B149-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B149-biology-01-00411">149</a>], CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels [
  <a rid="B150-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B150-biology-01-00411">150</a>], novel resources [
  <a rid="B151-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151-biology-01-00411">151</a>], starvation [
  <a rid="B152-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B152-biology-01-00411">152</a>] or desiccation [
  <a rid="B153-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B153-biology-01-00411">153</a>]. How climate change could be simulated within this framework is discussed below in more detail.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In selection lines it is possible to enforce different mating systems, as for example in Holland and Rice [
  <a rid="B154-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B154-biology-01-00411">154</a>], or different sex ratios, such as in Michalczyk 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="B155-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B155-biology-01-00411">155</a>], to vary sexual selection pressure. In order to change the mating system in a population, the reproducing generation is only allowed limited access to specific mates. For example, strict genetic monogamy completely removes sexual selection, and this can be achieved by randomly forming mating pairs. In contrast, polyandry and polygyny allow sexual selection to act via competition and choice mechanisms. Thus, it is possible to contrast a selection regime where sexual selection is entirely absent (monogamy) 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> a regime where sexual selection is present (polyandry or polygyny). Using different sex ratios to start each generation is similar, but allows investigation of different sexual selection intensities rather than a presence/absence dichotomy. A female-biased sex ratio reduces sexual selection intensity (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span> decreased opportunities for female choice and male-male competition), whereas a male-biased sex ratio increases sexual selection pressure. This can be utilized to approximate natural populations where various factors such as population density or sex ratio may decrease or increase sexual selection pressure.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drift, bottlenecks and adaptability can be investigated by manipulating the initial population size and the number of individuals allowed to contribute to each generation. Starting with small populations (e.g., 100 or less individuals) greatly increases the likelihood of stochastic effects influencing evolution and potentially lowers the adaptive potential [
  <a rid="B156-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-biology-01-00411">156</a>,
  <a rid="B157-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B157-biology-01-00411">157</a>]. However, using certain model organisms (e.g., microorganisms and small arthropods such as 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Tribolium</span>) it is also possible to investigate much larger population sizes [
  <a rid="B143-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-biology-01-00411">143</a>]. Bottlenecks can potentially be an issue in experimental evolution, because often only a subset of individuals is allowed to contribute to the next generation, contrary to natural conditions where, in principle at least, the whole population has the chance to reproduce. Thereby, genetic diversity diminishes, generation for generation, as a side effect of the experimental set-up. Nevertheless, such mechanisms could also be deliberately promoted as part of an experimental treatment, for example, to investigate founder effects or minimum viable population sizes during climate change [
  <a rid="B156-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-biology-01-00411">156</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
