<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.3. Ecological Reality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change can be implemented in experimental evolution in the beginning so as to represent a sudden shift in conditions, simulating the colonization of a new habitat, a land-use change or extreme weather events [
  <a rid="B158-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B158-biology-01-00411">158</a>,
  <a rid="B159-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B159-biology-01-00411">159</a>]. For example, a physiological study on thermal tolerance could subject populations of a study organism to certain elevated temperatures and use experimental evolution to investigate up to which temperature the organism can adapt. Alternatively, environmental conditions can be manipulated more realistically between and within generations to simulate changing conditions as experienced by natural populations facing climate change [
  <a rid="B160-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B160-biology-01-00411">160</a>,
  <a rid="B161-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B161-biology-01-00411">161</a>,
  <a rid="B162-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B162-biology-01-00411">162</a>]. The IPCC report [
  <a rid="B127-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B127-biology-01-00411">127</a>] states specific predictions as to how environmental conditions might change over time. Therefore, future experiments could try to account for the complexity of how single environmental factors might change, and also for interactions between different factors. For example, to investigate global warming, temperatures could be raised gradually or temperatures could fluctuate with increasing mean temperatures. Contrasting these regimes could help disentangle effects of warming 
  <span class="italic">per se</span> and effects stemming from changes in extreme temperatures. Additionally, changing conditions over time would enable manipulation of the mode of selection, such as directional 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> diversifying, and also the strength of natural selection. A further advantage would be that selection occurs over a longer time period and, therefore, sexual reproduction can generate novel phenotypes, which might be crucial for successful adaptation to novel conditions. In addition, if experimental evolution can be performed over a very long time course, there might be the possibility to observe benefits of novel mutations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the classic lab setting, ecological reality could be achieved more easily in field experiments, especially if taking advantage of the naturally occurring environmental fluctuations. Small caged populations could thereby be subjected to either the natural conditions, as a control treatment, or to a manipulated treatment where environmental factors are altered. For example, effects of climate change on humidity could be studied by adding or removing water and global warming could be simulated using infrared radiators as done by Harte 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="B163-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B163-biology-01-00411">163</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides implementing abiotic factors more realistically, future experimental evolution studies could also be greatly improved by incorporating spatial aspects of climate change consequences [
  <a rid="B164-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B164-biology-01-00411">164</a>]. The classic experimental evolution set-up with allopatric selection lines could be extended to a meta-population scenario by using multiple replicates of different population sizes. Migration could then be quite simply performed by exchanging individuals among populations at a given rate [
  <a rid="B165-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B165-biology-01-00411">165</a>,
  <a rid="B166-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B166-biology-01-00411">166</a>,
  <a rid="B167-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B167-biology-01-00411">167</a>]. In particular, with regard to adaptation and speciation, gene flow and incoming migrants are expected to play important roles (see section 4). Using a meta-population experimental evolution set-up, it would be possible to investigate the consequences of climate change, habitat fragmentation and deterioration in combination. For example, populations experiencing climate change could simultaneously be subdivided over time, or habitats could be artificially impoverished by manipulating the available resources [
  <a rid="B168-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B168-biology-01-00411">168</a>]. Furthermore, conservation strategies, such as artificially relocating individuals or providing dispersal corridors, could be tested. 
 </p>
</sec>
