<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6. Conclusions and Future Directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A vast number of studies illustrate the very diverse immediate effects of environmental factors and hence climate change on reproduction leading to alterations on genetic, phenotypic and behavioral levels. Estimating reproductive fitness of affected populations may be crucial for predicting impacts of climate change for biodiversity; however, because of complex interactions among environmental effects, the overall reproductive output is difficult to foresee. Climate change will undoubtedly affect natural selection pressure as well as sexual selection regimes. Therefore, reproduction will be subject to a complex interplay of shifting selection pressures and this may alter adaptation, reproductive isolation and extinction risk. We urgently need an improved understanding of how natural and sexual selection shape biodiversity in detail, and how a changing environment will affect these processes.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to provide evolutionarily meaningful results concerning population fitness, for example to use as input data for models monitoring biodiversity or making conservation management decisions, it will be necessary to coordinate experimental methods and the traits of interest. More specifically, detailed multi-generational data on reproductive rate and longevity could be used to improve predictions regarding the minimum viable population size in a population viability analysis or the minimal habitat size to protect endangered species. Therefore, we propose making greater efforts to measure lifetime reproductive success as a common currency, as this can be used, for example, to calculate population growth rates. Furthermore, evolutionary biology provides useful resources for tracking long-term changes in reproductive output over multiple generations. In particular, we feel that experimental evolution could be used more extensively for simulating climate change, because it is an enormously versatile method. Crucially, it provides the opportunity to implement multiple environmental factors and their interactions as well as additionally manipulating selection on reproduction. In particular, there is a lack of experimental evolution studies using non-model organisms, or addressing interactions between several species or different metapopulation structures. In general, we suggest taking a step away from laboratory common garden settings towards applying more ecologically relevant environments, incorporating greater complexity and ultimately performing semi-natural experimental evolution in the field. With regard to tackling the challenges of climate change, ecologists and evolutionary biologists could hence benefit from increasingly working in tandem.</p>
</sec>
