<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Experimental Evolution Simulating Climate Change Impacts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to experimentally investigate evolutionary changes due to climate change systematically, it will be necessary to manipulate evolutionary drivers and mechanisms in detail and to implement increasing levels of ecological reality. In many contexts, experimental evolution enables researchers to achieve these goals simultaneously [
  <a rid="B136-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B136-biology-01-00411">136</a>]. Although imposed selection pressures make it possible to observe evolution over time, experiments following experimental evolution have so far taken the form of snapshots after certain numbers of generations. With regard to climate change, experimental evolution allows comparing results across time points, which could provide valuable information concerning adaptive plasticity, genetic adaptation, inbreeding, adaptive divergence or co-evolutionary dynamics between interacting species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Certainly, the classic experimental evolution approach is not suitable to study organisms with very long generation times or large home range sizes, such as large terrestrial and aquatic vertebrates. Due to many practical reasons, therefore, experimental evolution has so far been mostly applied to relatively few model systems. However, in order to improve our understanding of the evolutionary processes shaping biodiversity following climate change in nature, experimental evolution has a great potential to be expanded to many non-model organisms or even communities and to become much more methodologically sophisticated. In particular, with regard to biomass and species diversity in nature, many organisms are not considered for research, although their life span would allow experimental evolution studies. We hence would like to encourage researchers to use long-term experimental evolution on non-model organisms, novel organisms and communities. In addition, environmental conditions could be simulated more realistically in order to test impacts of climate change; for example, increasing mean temperatures or increasing extreme weather events [
  <a rid="B127-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B127-biology-01-00411">127</a>]. In the following subchapters, we review experimental evolution methods and propose novel directions for future studies.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. Selection Line Characteristics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental evolution is usually based on replicated lines with no/low genetic variation or replicated lines with standing genetic variation. Classically, experimental evolution with unicellular organisms, such as 
   <span class="italic">E. coli,</span> has used multiple identical clones to investigate evolution, with resulting variation stemming solely from novel mutations [
   <a rid="B137-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137-biology-01-00411">137</a>]. Similarly, studies with multicellular organisms such as 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span> make use of iso-female lines (
   <span class="italic">i.e.</span> founded with one female) to simulate clonal lines [
   <a rid="B138-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B138-biology-01-00411">138</a>]. Generally, though, multicellular organisms are more frequently used in experimental evolution experiments where populations start with standing genetic variation [
   <a rid="B139-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B139-biology-01-00411">139</a>]. Initial genetic variation can be manipulated to varying degrees as part of the investigation of the selection pressures under study. With regard to climate change, experimental evolution could hence be applied to investigate the evolutionary potential of populations with different initial genetic diversities qualitatively and quantitatively. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A further climate change-relevant application of experimental evolution is to manipulate the size or density of different populations. Using this idea, it has been shown that allopatric populations of the fly 
   <span class="italic">Sepsis cynipsea</span> have a larger potential to diverge reproductively if the populations were of high density rather than low density [
   <a rid="B140-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B140-biology-01-00411">140</a>,
   <a rid="B141-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B141-biology-01-00411">141</a>]. This finding has also been confirmed in another species [
   <a rid="B142-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-biology-01-00411">142</a>]. Such an approach could be employed to obtain standardized information about the minimal population size necessary to survive different strengths of environmental change. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using small and rapidly replicating organisms for such experiments has the advantage that evolutionary consequences can be monitored over many generations, for example, in order to measure time to extinction, such as shown by Bell and Gonzalez [
   <a rid="B143-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-biology-01-00411">143</a>] or Drake and Griffen [
   <a rid="B144-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144-biology-01-00411">144</a>]. Nevertheless, the same principles of manipulating effective and operational population sizes could be applied more widely, such as on organismal communities using mesocosms as proposed by Cohen 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
   <a rid="B145-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145-biology-01-00411">145</a>]. In general, to represent natural systems more realistically, replicated selection lines should be viewed as multiple populations, where different environmental treatments can be applied. By using cages in the field, such as the artificial ponds used by Bolnick [
   <a rid="B146-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B146-biology-01-00411">146</a>], even organisms, which do not easily breed in the lab, could be used in future studies.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2. Evolutionary Drivers and Mechanisms</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In experimental evolution experiments, it is possible to manipulate natural selection, sexual selection, drift, bottlenecks, etc., including different levels of strength and combinations of these processes [
   <a rid="B147-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B147-biology-01-00411">147</a>]. Natural selection can be imposed by subjecting populations to altered environmental conditions, which has been applied in many studies investigating adaptation to, for example, different temperatures [
   <a rid="B148-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B148-biology-01-00411">148</a>,
   <a rid="B149-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B149-biology-01-00411">149</a>], CO
   <sub>2</sub> levels [
   <a rid="B150-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B150-biology-01-00411">150</a>], novel resources [
   <a rid="B151-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151-biology-01-00411">151</a>], starvation [
   <a rid="B152-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B152-biology-01-00411">152</a>] or desiccation [
   <a rid="B153-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B153-biology-01-00411">153</a>]. How climate change could be simulated within this framework is discussed below in more detail.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In selection lines it is possible to enforce different mating systems, as for example in Holland and Rice [
   <a rid="B154-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B154-biology-01-00411">154</a>], or different sex ratios, such as in Michalczyk 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
   <a rid="B155-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B155-biology-01-00411">155</a>], to vary sexual selection pressure. In order to change the mating system in a population, the reproducing generation is only allowed limited access to specific mates. For example, strict genetic monogamy completely removes sexual selection, and this can be achieved by randomly forming mating pairs. In contrast, polyandry and polygyny allow sexual selection to act via competition and choice mechanisms. Thus, it is possible to contrast a selection regime where sexual selection is entirely absent (monogamy) 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> a regime where sexual selection is present (polyandry or polygyny). Using different sex ratios to start each generation is similar, but allows investigation of different sexual selection intensities rather than a presence/absence dichotomy. A female-biased sex ratio reduces sexual selection intensity (
   <span class="italic">i.e.</span> decreased opportunities for female choice and male-male competition), whereas a male-biased sex ratio increases sexual selection pressure. This can be utilized to approximate natural populations where various factors such as population density or sex ratio may decrease or increase sexual selection pressure.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drift, bottlenecks and adaptability can be investigated by manipulating the initial population size and the number of individuals allowed to contribute to each generation. Starting with small populations (e.g., 100 or less individuals) greatly increases the likelihood of stochastic effects influencing evolution and potentially lowers the adaptive potential [
   <a rid="B156-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-biology-01-00411">156</a>,
   <a rid="B157-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B157-biology-01-00411">157</a>]. However, using certain model organisms (e.g., microorganisms and small arthropods such as 
   <span class="italic">Drosophila</span> or 
   <span class="italic">Tribolium</span>) it is also possible to investigate much larger population sizes [
   <a rid="B143-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-biology-01-00411">143</a>]. Bottlenecks can potentially be an issue in experimental evolution, because often only a subset of individuals is allowed to contribute to the next generation, contrary to natural conditions where, in principle at least, the whole population has the chance to reproduce. Thereby, genetic diversity diminishes, generation for generation, as a side effect of the experimental set-up. Nevertheless, such mechanisms could also be deliberately promoted as part of an experimental treatment, for example, to investigate founder effects or minimum viable population sizes during climate change [
   <a rid="B156-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-biology-01-00411">156</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.3. Ecological Reality</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change can be implemented in experimental evolution in the beginning so as to represent a sudden shift in conditions, simulating the colonization of a new habitat, a land-use change or extreme weather events [
   <a rid="B158-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B158-biology-01-00411">158</a>,
   <a rid="B159-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B159-biology-01-00411">159</a>]. For example, a physiological study on thermal tolerance could subject populations of a study organism to certain elevated temperatures and use experimental evolution to investigate up to which temperature the organism can adapt. Alternatively, environmental conditions can be manipulated more realistically between and within generations to simulate changing conditions as experienced by natural populations facing climate change [
   <a rid="B160-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B160-biology-01-00411">160</a>,
   <a rid="B161-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B161-biology-01-00411">161</a>,
   <a rid="B162-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B162-biology-01-00411">162</a>]. The IPCC report [
   <a rid="B127-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B127-biology-01-00411">127</a>] states specific predictions as to how environmental conditions might change over time. Therefore, future experiments could try to account for the complexity of how single environmental factors might change, and also for interactions between different factors. For example, to investigate global warming, temperatures could be raised gradually or temperatures could fluctuate with increasing mean temperatures. Contrasting these regimes could help disentangle effects of warming 
   <span class="italic">per se</span> and effects stemming from changes in extreme temperatures. Additionally, changing conditions over time would enable manipulation of the mode of selection, such as directional 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> diversifying, and also the strength of natural selection. A further advantage would be that selection occurs over a longer time period and, therefore, sexual reproduction can generate novel phenotypes, which might be crucial for successful adaptation to novel conditions. In addition, if experimental evolution can be performed over a very long time course, there might be the possibility to observe benefits of novel mutations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the classic lab setting, ecological reality could be achieved more easily in field experiments, especially if taking advantage of the naturally occurring environmental fluctuations. Small caged populations could thereby be subjected to either the natural conditions, as a control treatment, or to a manipulated treatment where environmental factors are altered. For example, effects of climate change on humidity could be studied by adding or removing water and global warming could be simulated using infrared radiators as done by Harte 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
   <a rid="B163-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B163-biology-01-00411">163</a>]. 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides implementing abiotic factors more realistically, future experimental evolution studies could also be greatly improved by incorporating spatial aspects of climate change consequences [
   <a rid="B164-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B164-biology-01-00411">164</a>]. The classic experimental evolution set-up with allopatric selection lines could be extended to a meta-population scenario by using multiple replicates of different population sizes. Migration could then be quite simply performed by exchanging individuals among populations at a given rate [
   <a rid="B165-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B165-biology-01-00411">165</a>,
   <a rid="B166-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B166-biology-01-00411">166</a>,
   <a rid="B167-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B167-biology-01-00411">167</a>]. In particular, with regard to adaptation and speciation, gene flow and incoming migrants are expected to play important roles (see section 4). Using a meta-population experimental evolution set-up, it would be possible to investigate the consequences of climate change, habitat fragmentation and deterioration in combination. For example, populations experiencing climate change could simultaneously be subdivided over time, or habitats could be artificially impoverished by manipulating the available resources [
   <a rid="B168-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B168-biology-01-00411">168</a>]. Furthermore, conservation strategies, such as artificially relocating individuals or providing dispersal corridors, could be tested. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.4. Species and Species Interactions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although single species studies are valuable, they do not capture the full picture, as interactions between species, such as competition, can affect evolutionary responses to changing environments [
   <a rid="B169-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B169-biology-01-00411">169</a>,
   <a rid="B170-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B170-biology-01-00411">170</a>,
   <a rid="B171-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B171-biology-01-00411">171</a>,
   <a rid="B172-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B172-biology-01-00411">172</a>,
   <a rid="B173-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B173-biology-01-00411">173</a>]. To accurately assess impacts of climate change on biodiversity, it would hence be valuable to apply experimental evolution approaches incorporating realistic species networks [
   <a rid="B174-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-biology-01-00411">174</a>]. Thereby, it will be necessary to apply the method to non-model organisms and to investigate interacting and co-evolving pairs and groups of species. For studies on host-parasite co-evolution experimental evolution is already in use [
   <a rid="B175-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B175-biology-01-00411">175</a>,
   <a rid="B176-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-biology-01-00411">176</a>,
   <a rid="B177-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B177-biology-01-00411">177</a>,
   <a rid="B178-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B178-biology-01-00411">178</a>,
   <a rid="B179-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B179-biology-01-00411">179</a>,
   <a rid="B180-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B180-biology-01-00411">180</a>,
   <a rid="B181-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B181-biology-01-00411">181</a>,
   <a rid="B182-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B182-biology-01-00411">182</a>,
   <a rid="B183-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B183-biology-01-00411">183</a>,
   <a rid="B184-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B184-biology-01-00411">184</a>]. In addition, experimental evolution has successfully been established to investigate predator-prey and higher food-chains dynamics [
   <a rid="B185-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B185-biology-01-00411">185</a>,
   <a rid="B186-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B186-biology-01-00411">186</a>,
   <a rid="B187-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B187-biology-01-00411">187</a>]. Nevertheless, there is still an underused potential for experimental evolution. As the classic experimental evolution approach is restricted to organisms reproducing in a confined setting with short generation times, organisms such as arthropods, which fulfill these prerequisites, should be utilized much more widely. With regard to the enormous species richness and abundance, more different insects could be investigated, in particular, as they are expected to respond in disparate ways to climate change [
   <a rid="B8-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-biology-01-00411">8</a>]. In the future, however, experimental evolution should also be considered in novel areas, such as invasion biology (
   <span class="italic">i.e.</span> resident and incoming species interact in a disturbed environment). For example, by taking experimental evolution outdoors, this approach could be applied to many more organisms. In particular, many species, which are threatened by climate change, might be difficult to breed under lab conditions. Nevertheless, experimental evolution could be developed further in order to incorporate such organisms, which are more challenging to study in the lab. Depending on the organisms of interest, experimental evolution could be performed in multiple closed or open greenhouses, aviaries, cages, artificial or natural ponds 
   <span class="italic">et cetera</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.5. Assessing Fitness</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A clear advantage of experimental evolution is that responses to selection can be tracked over time. This could be extremely valuable, because it is conceivable that short-term fitness changes may differ from long-term changes. This was the case, for example, in 
   <span class="italic">Callosobruchus maculatus</span> beetles, where the rate of adaptation to a novel food source differed between treatments with or without sexual selection [
   <a rid="B123-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B123-biology-01-00411">123</a>]. This shows that taking multiple serial measurements is potentially very important. Experimental evolution should hence focus increasingly on temporal aspects of climate change, for example, by tackling the following questions: Do phenotypic and genetic adaptive responses arise sequentially or simultaneously? How fast does adaptation progress in response to different strengths of selection and based on different population characteristics? What are the dynamics of fitness changes, e.g., linear or exponential? Which reproductive traits change when over time, and are there general trends across organisms? How do different modes of environmental change (e.g., rapid or continuous) affect responses to selection over time? In addition to helping resolve these rather fundamental evolutionary questions, experimental evolution could also contribute to more applied questions, such as predicting species fitness following climate change. With regard to making conservation decisions, it might be helpful to not only theoretically model species abundance or distribution, but also to experimentally simulate certain management scenarios. Specifically, semi-natural experimental evolution experiments could be designed in order to assess short and long-term changes in fitness due to climate change. For example, regarding species extinctions due to environmental changes, researchers could assess experimentally how much biodiversity loss can be sustained by different ecosystems until productivity and nutrient-cycles are endangered. Such controlled experiments would be extremely valuable, in particular in order to identify the key species for maintaining ecosystem function.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To achieve a better overall understanding of evolutionary change, it would be crucial to standardize fitness measurements and assess multiple traits. Particularly, it may be expected that life-history strategies, such as reproduction-survival trade-offs, might shift in response to selection [
   <a rid="B114-biology-01-00411" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114-biology-01-00411">114</a>]. For example, results regarding a decrease in reproduction following a rapid change in environmental conditions might be very difficult to interpret if information about reproductive efforts later in life and longevity is missing. Therefore, we would like to emphasize once more the usefulness of measuring lifetime reproductive success at the individual level where possible, or alternatively, population growth or decline as a measure of total fitness.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
