<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We use an updated and intermediate version of the NASA GISS ModelE2 GCM (hereafter ModelE2), which utilizes vegetation characteristics from the Ent Terrestrial Biosphere Model (Ent TBM). ModelE2 is a major Earth system model that contributes to the CMIP5 (Eyring et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) as an ongoing development effort, with the most recently documented version, ModelE2 R/H (where R and H refer to different ocean models), described in Miller et al. (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), Nazarenko et al. (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and Schmidt et al. (
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). ModelE2 runs at 2° × 2.5° spatial resolution with 40 vertical layers in the atmosphere (model top at 0.1 hPa), where resolution is enhanced between 825 hPa and the tropopause. We note that ModelE2 produces slightly warmer temperatures over South Asia, slightly cooler temperatures over the midlatitudes, higher precipitation over parts of the midlatitudes, and lower precipitation over South Asia (Schmidt et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Shukla et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Despite these biases, ModelE2 simulated climatologies of temperature, precipitation, and circulation, and their responses to historical anthropogenic forcings are in general agreement with observations and observed trends (Miller et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Schmidt et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Shukla et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Further, because we are comparing simulated responses within a physically consistent model framework, these biases will be generally consistent across simulations. We utilize the noninteractive atmospheric compositions, prescribed ocean version of the model to evaluate equilibrated, climatological surface‐atmosphere dynamics.
</p>
