<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recently, extensive studies have been conducted on the response of runoff variation to climate change and human activities of different rivers in different areas worldwide. Moreover, separation and quantification of the two driving factors on runoff variation have become topical issues in hydrology [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. In the arid regions, for example, much attention has been paid to distinguishing the contributions of climate change and human activities to the changes in runoff over the past half-century, in order to provide effective control measures to protect the fragile local ecosystem and ensure the sustainable development of the Loess Plateau water resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]; in the semiarid regions, several previous studies have qualitatively investigated the influence of climate change and human activities on runoff in the Yellow River [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. And human activities have been shown to be the main cause of the decrease in water discharge [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]; in the humid regions, the annual water and sediment discharge exhibited a decreasing trend over the last decades in the Yangtze River. This reduction in water discharge is mainly controlled by precipitation change (72%), while human activities contributed 86% of the reduction in sediment discharge [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. At present, experimental watersheds methods and physical mechanisms-based hydrological models have been widely used to quantitatively estimate the response of runoff to climate change and human activity interference [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Experimental watersheds methods played an important role in water circulation process research [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. For example, Wang et al. (2015) determined the impact of human activities within paired datasets under the same or similar weather conditions (SWC) [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. However, experimental watersheds methods are purely empirical methods based on watershed-scale experiments, which should be long-term and continuous. And these methods are also applicable only to small research regions [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Meanwhile, some hydrology models based on the physical mechanism have been used to study the hydrological process and its response to interference through the development of computer and remote sensing technology. This type of model includes soil and water assessment tool [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], precipitation runoff modelling system [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]and land use change on hydrology by ensemble modeling [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. For example, Chang et al. (2015) employed the Variable Infiltration capacity (VIC) hydrological model to distinguish the impacts of climate variability and human activity on hydrology in the Weihe River Basin, and suggested that the percentages in change of runoff caused by human activity were 64%, 72%, 47%, and 90% in the 1970s, 1980s 1990s and 2000s, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Depeng Zuo et al. (2015) discussed the impacts of land-use and climate changes on water and sediment yields in the Huangfuchuan River basin of the Loess Plateau by combined use of statistical tests, SWAT and land-use maps. The result indicated that the Grain for Green Program has a significant effect on the changes [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Under usual circumstances, however, model factor parameterization is challenging in various methods and calibration methods because a large quantity of data required for simulation analysis with a hydrophysical model is not available. In addition, the practical application of a physical model is largely limited because of the particularity and complexity of the geological structure in karst drainage basins even though such a model exhibits a clear physical mechanism and high simulation accuracy [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. As an alternative, statistical methods have been proven effective in discussing the response of runoff to interference of various factors. Kong et al. (2016) investigated the features of variations in runoff increment in the YRB and quantitatively evaluated the impact of climate change and human activities on the mean annual net runoff by residual analysis based on double mass curves (RA-DMC) [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Xu (2011) used linear regression to separate and quantify the two driving forces on annual runoff variations, and showed that 78.6% of annual observed runoff and 72.9% of natural runoff decreases could be explained by climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. Zhang et al. (2014) [
 <xref rid="pone.0193073.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] applied a non-linear relationship exists between runoff and the climatic system in a ‘reference stage’, then assessed the respective impact of human activities and precipitation on runoff in the ‘affected stage’. However, previous studies focused mainly on the non-karst areas and the impact of climate change and human activities on runoff change is not yet fully understood in karst regions.
</p>
