<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6785531</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">51107</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-51107-x</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Vulnerability to climate change of islands worldwide and its impact on the tree of life</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Veron</surname><given-names>Simon</given-names></name><address><email>sveron@edu.mnhn.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mouchet</surname><given-names>Maud</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Govaerts</surname><given-names>Rafa&#x000eb;l</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Haevermans</surname><given-names>Thomas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Pellens</surname><given-names>Roseli</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 1657</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.462844.8</institution-id><institution>Institut de Syst&#x000e9;matique, Evolution, Biodiversit&#x000e9; (ISYEB UMR7205), Mus&#x000e9;um national d&#x02019;Histoire naturelle, CNRS, </institution><institution>Sorbonne Universit&#x000e9;, EPHE, Universit&#x000e9; des Antilles, CP 51, 57 rue Cuvier, </institution></institution-wrap>75005 Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2308 1657</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.462844.8</institution-id><institution>Centre d&#x02019;Ecologie et des Sciences de la Conservation (CESCO UMR7204) MNHN, CNRS, </institution><institution>Sorbonne Universit&#x000e9; - CP135, 43 rue Buffon, </institution></institution-wrap>75005 Paris, France </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2097 4353</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.4903.e</institution-id><institution>Royal Botanic Gardens, Kew, Richmond, </institution></institution-wrap>Surrey, TW9 3AE UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>14471</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>27</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>9</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Island systems are among the most vulnerable to climate change, which is predicted to induce shifts in temperature, rainfall and/or sea levels. Our aim was: (i) to map the relative vulnerability of islands to each of these threats from climate change on a worldwide scale; (ii) to estimate how island vulnerability would impact phylogenetic diversity. We focused on monocotyledons, a major group of flowering plants that includes taxa of important economic value such as palms, grasses, bananas, taro. Islands that were vulnerable to climate change were found at all latitudes, e.g. in Australia, Indonesia, the Caribbean, Pacific countries, the United States, although they were more common near the equator. The loss of highly vulnerable islands would lead to relatively low absolute loss of plant phylogenetic diversity. However, these losses tended to be higher than expected by chance alone even in some highly vulnerable insular systems. This suggests the possible collapse of deep&#x000a0;and long&#x000a0;branches&#x000a0;in vulnerable islands. Measuring the vulnerability of each island is a first step towards a risk analysis to identify where the impacts of climate change are the most likely and what may be their consequences on biodiversity.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Biogeography</kwd><kwd>Conservation biology</kwd><kwd>Evolutionary ecology</kwd><kwd>Macroecology</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>This work was supported by French state funds managed by the French National Research Agency within the Investissements d&#x02019;Avenir program under reference ANR-11-IDEX-0004-02.</institution></funding-source></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">It is now widely accepted by the scientific community that the Earth is undergoing drastic climate change due to increased greenhouse gas emissions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>. Changes in global climate have occurred several times throughout the Earth&#x02019;s history but have stretched over very long periods of time whereas currently these changes are taking place over the space of a century or less<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. This rapid change, associated with other threats resulting from human activity related to production and consumption<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>, are having a strong impact on biodiversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. Considered as one of the five main causes of species and populations losses<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>, climate change may lead to direct alterations of natural habitats, forcing species to move from their historical range, adapt to new environmental conditions, find refuge in unaltered microhabitats or may lead to species extinction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>. Importantly, climate change acts in synergy with other human-induced threats, such as land use intensification or biological invasion, increasing their effects.</p><p id="Par3">In this context, island biodiversity requires specific attention for several reasons. Insular communities, because they are spatially segregated and have evolved in isolation, are characterized by extremely high rates of endemism<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Although they occur on less than 5% of the Earth&#x02019;s terrestrial area, island plants and vertebrates have an endemic richness that may exceed that of mainland species by a factor of 9.5<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. Island biota are also very prone to extinction: around 80% of past extinctions and a third of threatened terrestrial species are found on islands<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>. Past extinctions were probably triggered by invasive species, the na&#x000ef;vet&#x000e9; of insular species, and the high range-restriction of some populations<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref></sup>. Although climate change might impact island biota in many different ways, it is likely that sea level rise and climate shifts will be of major importance due to their direct association with the availability of suitable habitats for terrestrial organisms. Sea level rise is expected to lead to the submergence of several islands<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref></sup>. Sea level rise may also increase coastal erosion and saline water intrusion, impacting natural habitats<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref></sup>. This means that elevation, area, and the complexity of shoreline inlets are of major importance regarding vulnerability to sea level rise<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>. As for climate shift, it includes changes in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather events (e.g. droughts, storm surges, hurricanes), as well as altered patterns of seasonal and mid-term weather systems. This leads to the displacement of suitable climatic conditions to different altitudinal or latitudinal ranges, which implies that for some island species, suitable climates may only be found far beyond their limits<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref></sup>. Island size and topographic heterogeneity will then play a central role in preserving habitats where species could survive. When suitable habitats disappear, species that are able to adapt or/and have advantageous traits, e.g. flowering times that can track temperature shifts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref></sup>, will probably be naturally selected under the new environmental conditions, whereas others may go extinct. Shifts in climatic conditions may then promote a cascade of local extinctions.</p><p id="Par4">Despite the importance of island biota to global biodiversity, the impact of climate change on insular biodiversity has just begun to be investigated<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. The few existing studies focused only on species richness, and the lack of knowledge of other biodiversity currencies certainly limits our understanding of this impact. In fact, species richness alone does not provide information regarding certain crucial aspects for species conservation such as evolutionary history<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref></sup>. Thus far, we do not know how climate change will impact the tree of life. Will it lead to the loss of deep and/or unique evolutionary branches, or to random pruning? Can we expect a certain tendency towards resilience, as observed on continents<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref></sup>? If so, for what reasons?</p><p id="Par5">To begin to understand these issues, we designed a study to estimate island relative vulnerability to climate change and assess its impacts on the monocot tree of life. Relative vulnerability allows to identify islands which may be the most threatened by climate change at a world scale. These issues are particularly important for this major group of plants, which has a worldwide distribution and high species richness and endemism on islands. Monocots also provide a wide range of products to mankind. We used the phylogenetic diversity (PD) measure from<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref></sup> to measure the expected PD at risk of being lost<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. PD is more than a simple assessment of the evolutionary aspect of biodiversity as it may highlight current and future benefits provided by biodiversity to people and ecosystems, i.e. option-values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. Moreover, the loss of PD can be much higher than the loss of species richness (SR) if (i) closely related species go extinct (thus threatening not only terminal branches but also deep branches shared by a set of species), or (ii) if species on long and isolated branches disappear<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. Patterns of PD loss may then help identify which parts of the tree of life are the most at risk from climate change. We analysed 1,497 genera distributed across 5,565 islands from across the globe. This is also the first global scale study of this kind to integrate regional variations of climatic change as estimated by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC).</p></sec><sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Frequency and distribution of vulnerability to climate change (step 1)</title><p id="Par6">Over the 5,565 islands studied, the most represented category was &#x0201c;moderate vulnerability&#x0201d;, followed by low, high and very high vulnerability, respectively, for all the types of threats. In general, global vulnerability was correlated to sea level rise, shift in temperature and shift in rainfall, however, scores for these three threats had lower correlations with each other (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Islands that were most vulnerable to threats from climate change were more frequently situated at low latitudes and/or in the Southern Hemisphere, e.g. in Australia or in the Pacific Ocean, such as Kiribati and French Polynesia islands (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Yet, some northern islands also had high vulnerability, especially regarding shifts in rainfall (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), for example in Norway and Sweden. In total, 54, 109, 165 and 34 islands had a very high vulnerability to sea level rise, shift in temperature, shift in rainfall, and global threat from climate change, respectively (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Supplementary Datasets&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> and <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Correlation coefficients between vulnerability scores for each threat across all islands using Pearson&#x02019;s correlation test.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>Sea Level Rise</th><th>Shift in temperature</th><th>Shift in rainfall</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Shift in temperature</italic>
</td><td>0.69</td><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Shift in rainfall</italic>
</td><td>0.67</td><td>0.71</td><td/></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Global vulnerability</italic>
</td><td>0.87</td><td>0.90</td><td>0.89</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>All results were significant (p-value&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;2.2*10<sup>&#x02212;16</sup>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Worldwide distribution of the 5,565 islands with native monocot species and their classification according to four categories of vulnerability (low, moderate, high, very high) to threats related to climate change: (<bold>a</bold>) sea level rise (<bold>b</bold>) shift in temperature, (<bold>c</bold>) shift in rainfall, and (<bold>d</bold>) global vulnerability to climate change. Red lines represent the fitted levels of vulnerability scores (cubic smoothing spline) along longitudes and latitudes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e511"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Spatial distribution of ExpPDloss (step 2)</title><sec id="Sec5"><title>Absolute ExpPDloss</title><p id="Par7">Estimates of expected loss of phylogenetic diversity&#x000a0;at a global scale (ExpPD<italic>loss</italic>) following local species extinctions indicated that the ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> per island was highest at low latitudes and in the eastern part of the world such as in Madagascar, Borneo, New Guinea, Taiwan, Sri Lanka, Sumatra but with Cuba being one of the most notable exception (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>; see Supplementary Dataset&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref> for the full list of islands and their ExpPD<italic>loss</italic>). The islands whose disappearance would cause the greatest ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> when only endemic genera were included were Madagascar, Sumatra, Tasmania, New-Caledonia, Honshu, Cuba, New Guinea, and Sri Lanka, among others (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). When corrected for sampling effort, the relative ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> values changed only slightly when considering either all genera or only endemic genera (Supplementary datasets S1 and S2).<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Distribution of the ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> caused by the independent loss of islands when considering (<bold>a</bold>) all monocot genera (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;1,497) found on islands worldwide (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;5,565); (<bold>b</bold>) only monocot genera that are endemic (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;96) to islands (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;72). Red lines represent the fitted levels of expected diversity loss (cubic smoothing spline) along longitudes and latitudes. Black dashed lines represent the fitted of the number of islands (cubic smoothing spline) along longitudes and latitudes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e562"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Where is ExpPDloss significantly high?</title><p id="Par8">By removing the effect of richness on the ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> using null models (see methods), we found that the most significant losses were predominantly expected at low latitudes and eastern longitudes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Islands with highly significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> were, among others: Madagascar, Borneo, New-Guinea, Tasmania, Sri Lanka, but also Cuba and Tierra del Fuego. For insular endemic genera, significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was found, among others, for Madagascar, Indonesia (Sumatra, Borneo, New Guinea, Sulawesi), the West Indies (Cuba, Jamaica, Hispaniola), Honshu, Sri Lanka, and Tasmania (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).<fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of islands where ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> is higher than expected at random: (<bold>a</bold>) considering all genera; (<bold>b</bold>) considering only genera that are endemic to islands. Curves at the top and to the left of the maps represent the fitted distribution of p-values<sub>ind</sub> (cubic smoothing spline) along longitudes and latitudes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e604"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Would the disappearance of highly vulnerable islands have a large effect on PD? (step 3)</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Loss of phylogenetic diversity per island and category of vulnerability</title><p id="Par9">We found that, on average, the ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> for each category of vulnerability was very similar across the four types of threats (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). However, the highest values of ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> were found for islands with moderate vulnerability (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Notable exceptions include Cuba and New Guinea, which were highly vulnerable to predicted sea level rise and shifts in rainfall, respectively, and whose disappearance would cause large ExpPD<italic>loss</italic>. Significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic>, i.e. higher than expected by chance (p_value<sub>ind</sub>), was found for only a small proportion of islands among all categories of vulnerabilities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). For shifts in temperature and sea level rise, the median p-value<sub>ind</sub> was highest in the &#x0201c;very high vulnerability&#x0201d; category (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). When considering only endemic genera, the highest ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was predicted to occur mainly for islands in the &#x0201c;moderately vulnerable&#x0201d; category (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Moreover, only a small proportion of islands had significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and they generally had a low or moderate vulnerability to climate change (e.g. Madagascar, large Indonesian islands).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Expected loss of phylogenetic diversity for each vulnerability category and type of threat. *0.95&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;p_value<sub>ind</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.99, **0.99&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;p_value<sub>ind</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.999, ***0.999&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;p_value<sub>ind</sub>&#x02009;&#x0003c;=&#x02009;1. &#x0201c;n&#x0201d; is the number of islands per category of threat.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e674"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Distribution of p_value<sub>ind</sub> frequencies for each vulnerability category and type of threat. 50% of p_values<sub>ind</sub> are higher than the median p_value<sub>ind</sub> and 50% are lower.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e692"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Would the extinction of all genera on vulnerable islands cause higher ExpPDloss than extinctions at random?</title><p id="Par10">We found contrasting results depending on the threat considered. For shifts in temperature, ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was higher than expected by chance only when all islands with low vulnerability were lost (p_value<sub>all</sub>; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Regarding sea level rise and global vulnerability to climate change, p_value<sub>all</sub> were relatively high in both islands with moderate and very&#x000a0;high vulnerability. As for the effect of a shift in rainfall, ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was the most significant when highly vulnerable islands were lost. Moreover,&#x000a0;for three out of the four threats considered, the loss of genera occurring on the most vulnerable islands would cause higher ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> than expected in 60% to 80% of our randomizations. Yet, we observed that&#x000a0;p_values<sub>all</sub> were poorly congruent with the phylogenetic signal of extinction probabilities (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>P_value<sub>all</sub> of the ExpPD<sub>loss</sub> for each vulnerability category and type of threat. Black and red curves represent the phylogenetic signal of extinction probabilities, calculated using Pagel&#x02019;s &#x003bb; and Abouheif&#x02019;s statistical tests.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e737"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">Similar results were found when focusing only on endemic genera. ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was generally greater than by chance with the loss of (i) islands with low vulnerability to shifts in temperature; (ii) islands that are highly vulnerable to shifts in rainfall; (iii) islands with either high or low vulnerability to sea level rise; and (iv) islands with moderate vulnerability to the global threats from climate change&#x000a0; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par12">The present change in climate is raising many questions regarding its effect on biodiversity and the conservation measures to be taken to mitigate its impacts<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref></sup>. In this study, we focused on islands to investigate the vulnerability to climate change of these segregated spatial units that strongly contribute to the world&#x02019;s diversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref></sup>. The main aims were to categorise islands worldwide according to their vulnerability to climate change and to investigate how the estimated vulnerability would impact the tree of life of monocots.</p><p id="Par13">As to be expected, for the set of features considered, the highest vulnerability values were assigned to islands that were small, low, jagged, and located in areas where sea level rise, shifts in temperature and/or rainfall were predicted to be the highest. Yet, the complex interaction between island features and threat levels meant that vulnerable islands were identified across the globe. In particular, low lying islands situated in the Caribbean and the Pacific were highly vulnerable to the effects of sea level rise (e.g. The Cook Islands, French Polynesia, the Marshall Islands)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. Large predicted shifts in rainfall in North America and Scandinavian countries combined with low elevations and small areas, may explain why many islands that are vulnerable to shifts in rainfall are located in the Northern Hemisphere (although many others are found near the equator and at Southern latitudes).</p><p id="Par14">By estimating the relative threat of climate change on insular biodiversity based on predictions from the IPCC, we identified islands where species may be most at risk in a context of uncertainty<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref></sup>. This could then help to anticipate the effects of climate change and establish strategies to preserve biodiversity. Similar analyses could be carried out for other groups of organisms, such as eudicots, mammals<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>, or to assess the risks faced by human settlements<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par15">As this is the first study at this scale, some critical features could not be taken into account due to the paucity of standardized information for a large number of islands. We lacked data on the lithology of many islands which is another important factor of vulnerability to sea level rise. For instance, islands with rocky shores are likely to be more stable, whereas islands with sedimentary shores may adjust in shape, size and position over very short periods of time depending on the supply and transportation of sediments<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref></sup>. As for reef islands, they might grow following shifts in sea levels (but see<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref></sup>). The study of Kench <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref></sup> illustrates this complex situation, in that 18 out of 29 coral islands affected by sea level rise had actually grown in size due to new gravel deposits during cyclonic events.</p><p id="Par16">Regarding estimates of vulnerability to shifts in temperature and rainfall, there are at least three main sources of uncertainties and limitations that should be considered. The first is that the scale of global predictions may fail to account for more localised effects and, in some cases, does not allow to distinguish spatially close islands with different environmental conditions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref></sup>. The second is the uncertainty concerning these estimates for islands located in regions that are largely influenced by major climate drivers with very high variability, and for which even the direction of their impact under climate change is hard to predict (e.g. El Ni&#x000f1;o Southern Oscillation)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref></sup>. The third is the climatic heterogeneity within islands, which is expected to be greater in larger and more elevated islands, with important climatic differences between windward and leeward regions<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref></sup>, or along altitudinal belts. This makes that a single vulnerability score may not be sufficient to capture the spatial heterogeneity of threats in large and/or mountainous islands. It must be considered, however, that part of this complexity is comprised in the vulnerability index, as area, altitude and topographic heterogeneity are integrated in the assessment of vulnerability. Our main conclusion regarding this point is that, although the vulnerability scores used here do allow comparing a wide range of islands at a global scale, more research is necessary to understand the effects of climate and topographic heterogeneity on the vulnerability to climate change. As a direction, we suggest focusing on large islands where a significant proportion of the Tree of Life could be lost if some species went extinct (e.g. Madagascar, Borneo, New-Guinea, Cuba, Taiwan, Sri Lanka, Sumatra). In addition, as vulnerability assessments can be conducted at different scales, one prospect would be to define different levels of vulnerability depending on conservation objectives. In this framework, our approach could for instance correspond to &#x0201c;level 1&#x0201d; based on island typology, level &#x0201c;0&#x0201d; could refer to the vulnerability of archipelagos, &#x0201c;level 2&#x0201d; to the vulnerability of habitats etc.</p><p id="Par17">In the Global Assessment Report on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services released by the Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (IPBES), PD is now recognised as a key indicator of one of &#x0201c;Nature&#x02019;s Contributions to People&#x0201d; (NCP 18 - maintenance of options)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. Indeed, PD provides options for future generations and for organisms to adapt in a changing environment<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref></sup>. The IPBES therefore highlighted that the loss of phylogenetic diversity implies irreversible losses of options to humanity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref></sup>. In this context, assessing the impacts of island vulnerability to climate change represents a first step to provide knowledge for conservation actions aiming at the reduction of irreversible losses.</p><p id="Par18">The first analyses of our research show that extinctions on the most vulnerable islands would remove relatively little insular PD. Indeed, vulnerable islands generally have small size and low elevation which are factors of low species richness<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, conducting to reduced loss of PD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. By contrast, islands that contribute the most to loss of PD were only moderately threatened by climate change. This was the case for Madagascar, Borneo, Honshu, Sri Lanka, Sumatra, New Caledonia, which all harboured high rates of endemic and evolutionary unique genera (Supplementary Method&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref></sup>. These islands are large and environmentally diverse which fosters high richness and endemicity but also offers greater opportunities for plants to track their climatic preferences<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par19">Nonetheless, the link between ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> and taxon richness may hide the fact that some long and/or deep branches of the tree of life may occur on vulnerable islands. By explicitly removing this association using comparisons with null models, we found that some highly vulnerable islands &#x02013; although not all of them &#x02013; may lose more PD than expected by chance. This is particularly true for islands that are highly vulnerable to sea level rise and temperature shifts, which is probably due to their greater frequency at low latitudes, where some range-restricted taxa representing relatively large amounts of PD occur (Supplementary method S2). This reinforces the claim that highly vulnerable islands could be home to evolutionary distinct, rare and endangered genera and that climate change would increase their likelihood of extinction<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par20">These outcomes correspond to a worst-case and island-centred scenario in which all genera on an island would become extinct, and in which the probability of extinction of a genus is proportional to the number of islands it disappears from. We acknowledge that sensitivity to climate change is highly complex and depend on many factors such as species ecological preferences and tolerances, traits (e.g. phenology), dispersal potential (e.g. among islands of an archipelago) or biotic interactions. Species-centred and trait-based approaches remain therefore essential to understand the responses of species to threats from climate change but may be more relevant at regional or local scales. Finally, we also encourage the mobilization of data hosted in natural history collections and complementary field sampling in islands where impacts of climate change are expected to be high. This would contribute to include several islands that were discarded from the present analysis due to lack of appropriate data, as for example, many islands along the entire coasts of South Asia, North Africa, in the Red Sea, or in the Maldives (only a single island of the archipelago could be included here).</p><p id="Par21">The simulation of the extinction of all genera occurring on vulnerable islands showed one more facet of the consequences of climate change. If genera occurring on vulnerable islands went extinct, the monocot tree of life would be pruned to non-negligible proportions (i.e. causing higher ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> than random). Several hypothesis can be evoked to explain this result. The first is that it is driven by the loss of the most evolutionarily distinct and/or range-restricted genera. Nonetheless, the different tests performed here showed that the expected loss of the most evolutionarily distinct genera and the expected loss of genus richness were rarely significant when all vulnerable islands were lost (Supplementary method S2). A second potential explanation for significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> on vulnerable islands&#x000a0;would be that genera are closely related<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref></sup>. However, the phylogenetic signal of extinction risks was relatively low on vulnerable islands, indicating that genera threatened by the loss of the most vulnerable islands tended to be randomly distributed among the tips of the phylogeny. The rejection of these hypotheses leads then to consider two other possibilities. The first is that certain range-restricted genera are clustered in species-poor clades, thus threatening the corresponding deep branches, whereas many others are over-dispersed, i.e. some deep branches also support safe taxa. The second explanation is that some relatively long branches are threatened, although many other evolutionarily distinct genera are secured. These hypotheses that there is a relatively low number of deep and long branches at risk is supported by the moderate frequency of cases where ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> is higher than random. Overall, these findings show that, as also observed by<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup>, taxa that are vulnerable to climate change may be found either on long or short branches, and whereas some are over-dispersed in the phylogeny, others are clustered in particular clades.</p><p id="Par22">Previous studies considering the impacts of climate change on PD<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref></sup> were conducted on a continental scale. They showed that climate change could lead to spatial homogenization of PD and that the tree of life would be, to a certain extent, resilient to this threat. In comparison, our study highlights the need to consider the specificity of island systems when devising conservation strategies. Water expanses may constitute a strong barrier against species dispersal. This implies that local extinctions, rather than shifts in the distribution range, are more likely, particularly when considering some features of insular biota such as the loss of dispersal ability, low population sizes, and narrow distribution ranges. Consequently, PD loss instead of PD homogenization is expected and insular PD is certainly more threatened than continental PD.</p><sec id="Sec11"><title>Conclusion and prospects</title><p id="Par23">To conclude, assessing the vulnerability of islands to climate change represents a first step towards identifying where its impact on biodiversity is most likely to be seen<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref></sup>. Importantly, by tackling the crucial challenges to predict and mitigate the effect of climate change on biodiversity, this study contributes to issues of global relevance as defined in the policies of the IPCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup> and the IPBES<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. We found that (i) sea level rise, shifts in temperature and shifts in rainfall may not cause high absolute ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> at a global scale&#x000a0;(ii) however, ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> on some vulnerable islands tends to be higher than if extinctions were random (iii) taxa found on vulnerable islands likely capture some deep and/or long phylogenetic branches. The expected significant loss of monocot PD on vulnerable islands is then another warning that climate change will affect human well-being<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref></sup>. The results of this study can be used in two ways. First, they can serve as a guide to identify where to act in order to protect the tree of life. While we focused on monocots, other highly diverse insular groups with many endemic species, such as eudicots, would be worth investigated in order to elucidate to which extent these findings can be generalized. Our analysis of islands worldwide provides a chart indicating where to focus to avoid imminent losses. This shows the need of moving from global to local in order to monitor the status of the local populations subtending these evolutionary branches that are under threat, and study ways to avoid their extinctions. The second perspective concerns the synergistic effects of climate change with other threats impacting biodiversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref></sup>. Even on islands not considered to be vulnerable to climate change, other factors, especially human-induced habitat losses and species invasions, may represent an immediate threat to their biodiversity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref></sup>. Future studies should consider the diversity of threats on island biodiversity, including biotic multipliers, and their interactions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Methods</title><p id="Par24">To assess the consequences of climate change on island phylogenetic diversity, we proceeded as follows:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par25">We calculated the vulnerability of each island to three threats related to climate change depending on some island features</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par26">We estimated how much phylogenetic diversity (PD) would be lost on a global scale when an island disappears. As the extent of the loss of PD depends on an island&#x02019;s genus richness, we also estimated whether these losses were significant or not, i.e. whether they were higher than by chance alone.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par27">We linked island vulnerability to loss of PD. In particular, we assessed how much PD would be lost when all islands in the same vulnerability category were removed and whether these losses were significant.</p></list-item></list></p><p id="Par28">The three steps were repeated for all monocot genera occurring on islands and then only for those genera that are restricted to islands, i.e., not observed on the mainland.</p><sec id="Sec13"><title>Data</title><sec id="Sec14"><title>Islands</title><p id="Par29">Following previous studies<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref></sup>, we defined an island as an area surrounded by water whose size is smaller than Australia and excluding islands within continents. Our island database was extracted from the Global Island Database released by the United Nations Environment Program which has information on 180,495 islands from all over the world<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. We worked at the island but not archipelago scale.</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Phylogeny and plant occurrences</title><p id="Par30">We used a monocot phylogeny that is well resolved at the genus level for the vast majority of genera<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref></sup>. Working at the genus level allowed us to take into account taxa united by solid shared evolutionary history, materialized by shared traits which made them successful on islands and which are therefore the object of frequent evolutionary and ecological research<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref></sup>. Genera names from this phylogeny were matched with the accepted names found in the eMonocot database and used as a reference to check for the synonymy of plant occurrence names. eMonocot is built by an international consortium of botanists and aims to provide the most reliable information on monocot taxonomy and occurrence.</p><p id="Par31">Plant occurrence points were downloaded from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility portal (GBIF, GBIF.org (09 February 2017) GBIF Occurrence Download https://doi.org/10.15468/dl.kyylbs). We selected all &#x0201c;basisOfRecord&#x0201d; occurences comprised within the island polygon boundaries, defined in the Global Island Database (GID)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. We used the taxon name structure from eMonocot to account for possible synonymies in the GBIF dataset and attributed an accepted name following the synonymy list in eMonocot for each record. We excluded all marine taxa.</p><p id="Par32">We then filtered out occurrences of species that are not native to island polygons using the eMonocot database which provides information on a species&#x02019; &#x0201c;native&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;non-native&#x0201d; status. To do so, we attributed a Taxonomic Databases Working Group polygon (TDWG; scale used in the eMonocot database<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref></sup>) to each island polygon used in our analysis<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup>. All GBIF occurrences associated with a TDWG polygon and corresponding to a non-native species in the eMonocot database were excluded, which could sometimes lead to the exclusion of a genus.</p><p id="Par33">However, with this method we could not identify the status of taxa with occurrences where information regarding the &#x0201c;native&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;non-native&#x0201d; status was missing in the eMonocot database. A second test was carried out for those species. For each, we delimited a polygon defined by the maximal and minimal latitudes and longitudes of their known native range. We then excluded the occurrences of species found outside their respective polygon.</p><p id="Par34">Crossing data from large databases - the GBIF, eMonocot, and GID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> databases &#x02013; we compiled 2,550,396 occurrences representing 15,901 species from 1,497 genera on 5,565 islands. Although this seems to be a small proportion of the initial sample (180,495 islands), suggesting that more sampling efforts are needed, this represents one of the largest dataset used for large scale conservation studies in islands. The use of eMonocot allowed reducing taxonomic and geo-localization errors and uncertainties, and therefore gave us more confidence in the validity of our data compared to using GBIF alone<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref></sup>. It also allowed to exclude non-native species, complete and correct a species&#x02019; area of distribution, and check for synonymies.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Step 1 - Assessing Island Vulnerability</title><p id="Par35">First, we assessed the vulnerability to climate change of the 5,565 islands harbouring native monocot species, by evaluating how they will be impacted by sea level rise, shifts in temperature, and shifts in rainfall. Vulnerability is a concept used to evaluate the potential impacts of climate change on a system<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref></sup>. The factors of vulnerability considered and the calculation of vulnerability scores are described below.</p><sec id="Sec17"><title>Factors of vulnerability</title><p id="Par36">To estimate island vulnerability, we used a set of features that are expected to have a strong influence on the effects of climate change on insular biodiversity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref></sup>. Vulnerability to the three threats mentioned above was estimated by considering the following factors:<list list-type="bullet"><list-item><p id="Par37"><italic>Sea Level Rise</italic>. We estimated the vulnerability to this threat using the values of sea level rise predicted by the IPCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> and considering four island features: area, maximal elevation, mean elevation and circularity. The choice of these variables was based on the reasoning that a large area, high elevation, and roundness (i.e. smallest possible perimeter) increase the proportion of the island surface not affected by floods, erosion, and saltwater intrusion. This consequently reduces the possibility of sea level rise affecting the island&#x02019;s entire biota<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref></sup>.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par38"><italic>Shift in temperature</italic>. We assessed the vulnerability to shifts in temperature by calculating the difference between predicted and current mean annual temperature and between predicted and current temperature seasonality (defined as the standard deviation of mean monthly temperatures). We also considered that the vulnerability of an island to a shift in temperature will depend on area and topographic heterogeneity. Indeed, a large and topographically heterogeneous island may comprise a wider range of climates and thus is more likely to maintain suitable climates in at least part of its territory.</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par39"><italic>Shift in rainfall</italic>. We assessed the vulnerability to shifts in rainfall by calculating the difference between predicted and current values of mean annual rainfall and the difference between predicted and current rainfall seasonality. We also considered factors related to area and topography, which are related to the likelihood of maintaining suitable climates (as with the vulnerability to shifts in temperature).</p></list-item></list><fig id="Fig7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Vulnerability scores for each factor of vulnerability and their associated threat. For each factor, islands were ranked according to the expected influence of that factor on their vulnerability. Islands were then assigned to five classes (from low (1) to high (5)) depending on their ranking position. For example, the highest score was attributed to islands in the top 5%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1135"/></fig></p><p id="Par40">Current climatic variables were extracted from WorldClim version 2.0<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref></sup>. Predicted temperature, rainfall and sea level rise values came from the IPCC<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup> (provided by WorldClim version 1.4) and represent climate projections from global climate models based on four concentration pathways of representative greenhouse gases. In order to determine which scenario(s) to use, we performed a series of preliminary tests to assess the impact of each scenario on estimates of island vulnerability. Results indicated that islands were ranked similarly in their vulnerability to climate change under different scenarios. Although scenarios differed greatly in their estimates of sea level rise, temperature, and rainfall changes, they did not differ much regarding the spatial distribution of these changes (i.e. regions expected to experience the most change were roughly the same). We therefore selected the scenario that considers 2.6 Watts per square meter of cumulative emissions of human greenhouse gases. This corresponds to the most optimistic scenario, where temperature rise remains below 2&#x02009;&#x000b0;C above pre-industrial values<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref></sup>, and is the proposed target of the Paris Agreement on Climate Change.</p><p id="Par41">Elevation and area data were extracted from Weigelt <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref></sup> and GID<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref></sup> databases, respectively. Island circularity was estimated as the ratio between the squared perimeter and the area divided by 4&#x003c0;, with values ranging from 0 to 1 (a perfect circle having a value of 1).</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Calculation of island vulnerability</title><p id="Par42">We estimated the vulnerability of each island to each threat, i.e. sea level rise, shift in temperature and shift in rainfall. For each factor associated with a particular threat related to climate change, islands were ranked according to the expected influence of that factor on island vulnerability (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). We then attributed a score between 1 (low rank) to 5 (high rank) to each island depending on its position in the ranking. For each threat, each island was given 4 or 5 scores (for shifts in temperature/rainfall and sea level rise respectively) (see above; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The vulnerability of an island to a threat is quantified as the mean of these scores.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Step 2 - Loss of Phylogenetic Diversity When Islands are Lost Independently</title><p id="Par43">As a second step, we measured the amount and significance of global PD loss following the independent loss of islands, i.e. local extinction of all taxa on a given island. The aim was to identify which islands would have the greatest impact on the tree of life if they were lost.</p><sec id="Sec20"><title>Measuring expected PD loss per island</title><p id="Par44">First, we estimated how much PD would be lost across the entire phylogeny of monocots if all genera occurring on a given island went extinct. To do so, we simulated the &#x0201c;loss&#x0201d; of an island, i.e. local extinction of all its taxa. We then estimated the probability of extinction for each genus on an island as the expected proportion of the genus&#x02019; global range lost if the island would disappear. Geographic range has been found to be one of the main predictors of species extinction risk, but presence-only data and the huge number of islands and species studied here did not allow assessing individual species range size. Yet, changes in the number of localities where a species occurs is also an essential factor of extinction risk and is used in the criteria B of the IUCN Red List threat status. In our analysis, species range was therefore measured as the number of islands a genus occurs on. This posits that each island equally contributes to a genus&#x02019; survival and, therefore probabilities of extinction are given by the proportion of native&#x000a0;islands from which a genus disappears. Following Faith<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>, each branch of the phylogenetic tree was weighted by the product of the extinction probabilities of all its descendants, <italic>i</italic>.<italic>e</italic>. equal to the proportion of the range lost for each genera found on the &#x0201c;lost&#x0201d; island and equal to 0 for all other genera. The branches supporting genera which had not lost any proportion of their range were considered safe (probability of extinction equal to 0). We calculated the expected loss of insular PD following the loss of a given island as the sum of weighted branch lengths (<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>; Eq.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>). This measure estimates how much PD is expected to be lost on a global scale following local extinctions on a given island. It also allows us to consider the phylogenetic complementarity of extinction risks, i.e. the shared responsibility of taxa to safeguard deep branches<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$ExpPDloss(tree,\,proba)=\sum _{b}{L}_{b}\,\prod _{{k}_{b}}{p}_{{k}_{b}}$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mi>l</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mi>s</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>p</mml:mi><mml:mi>r</mml:mi><mml:mi>o</mml:mi><mml:mi>b</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:munder><mml:mo>&#x0220f;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:munder><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>p</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>k</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mspace width=".25em"/></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>k</italic><sub><italic>b</italic></sub> designates the <italic>k</italic><sup>th</sup> descendant of branch <italic>b</italic> on the tree, <italic>p</italic><sub><italic>kb</italic></sub> is the extinction probability of the <italic>k</italic><sup>th</sup> descendant of branch <italic>b</italic>, and L<sub><italic>b</italic></sub> is the length of branch <italic>b</italic><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par45">We ran this analysis for every native insular plant genera. Using this measure, the probability of extinction of a taxon was related to the number of islands it was found on independently of its potential occurrence on continents. Here, ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> has to be interpreted as the impact of island disappearance on monocot PD across islands but not on monocot PD worldwide (representatives of these genera may survive on continents). To complement this measure, we estimated ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> from a pruned tree comprising only genera that are endemic to islands, i.e. those found on a single or in several islands but not on the mainland (96 genera from 72 islands). This represents the PD at risk of irreversible loss, because these genera will not survive anywhere else if the islands where they live are lost. Finally, to correct for low sampling on some islands, we corrected ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> using the predicted genus richness for each island as described in Supplementary method S1.</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Measuring the significance of ExpPDloss per island</title><p id="Par46">As absolute ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> may be correlated with genus richness on an island, we tested whether loss of plant PD on each island was higher than expected by chance. To do so, we randomized genera between islands but kept the genus richness of each island and the range of each genus (i.e. the number of islands a genus is present on). For each island and randomization, we calculated the new ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> when that island is lost. Simulations were run 1000 times. For each island, we then calculated the frequency at which the observed ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was higher than the 1000 ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> values calculated from simulations (p-values<sub>ind</sub>; unilateral test). This procedure allowed removing the dependency of ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> on genus richness while retaining the structure of the data. Expected PD losses from the original data were considered highly, moderately or slightly significant when they fell into the highest 0.1%, 1% and 5% of the distribution values obtained from simulations, respectively.</p><p id="Par47">To identify areas where range-restricted and/or evolutionarily distinct genera co-occur, we also estimated for each island the expected loss of species richness (ExpSR<italic>loss</italic>) and the expected loss of species richness in the most evolutionarily distinct species (ExpSR<italic>loss</italic><sub>ED</sub><sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref></sup>). We calculated absolute values and their significance. Results were often similar to those of ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> and are described in Supplementary method S2.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Step 3 - Linking Expected PD Loss to the Vulnerability of Islands</title><sec id="Sec23"><title>Absolute value and significance of ExpPDloss per island in relation to island vulnerability</title><p id="Par48">The third step of the analysis was to link island vulnerability (step 1) to the expected loss of PD (step 2). We first estimated the <italic>absolute</italic> ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> per island per category of vulnerability. Due to the high number of vulnerability scores we defined 4 categories of vulnerability: low (1&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;vulnerability score &#x0003c; 2), moderate (2&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;vulnerability score &#x0003c; 3), high (3&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;vulnerability score &#x0003c; 4) and very high vulnerability (4&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;vulnerability score&#x02009;&#x02264;&#x02009;5). From this we identified the islands and the categories of vulnerability where ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> would be the highest.</p><p id="Par49">Second, we linked the <italic>significance</italic> of ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> when islands were lost independently to the category of vulnerability they belonged to. We calculated the distribution of p-values<sub>ind</sub> (i.e. the departure from the null model described above) and the median p-value<sub>ind</sub> per vulnerability category. We identified in this way the categories where significant ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> was most frequent.</p></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Expected loss of PD when all islands with a similar vulnerability to climate change are lost</title><p id="Par50">As a second approach to link island vulnerability to loss of PD, we tested whether loss of <italic>all</italic> islands assigned to a given vulnerability category would lead to higher ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> than at random (p_values<sub>all</sub>). This differs from the previous analyses which considered the <italic>independent</italic> loss of islands (p_values<sub>ind</sub>).</p><p id="Par51"> Here we calculated extinction probabilities for each genus as the proportion of their range that would be lost if <italic>all</italic> islands with a similar vulnerability to climate change disappeared (in step 1 the extinction probability was measured as the proportion of a genus range lost when <italic>a single</italic> island disappeared). To explore this question, we defined the &#x0201c;range&#x0201d; of a genus as the number of vulnerability categories of the islands on which it occurs. For example, if a genus occurs <italic>only</italic> on highly vulnerable islands, its extinction probability would be 1 if all these islands were lost. The extinction probability of a genus occurring on islands from three categories (e.g. very high, high, and moderate vulnerability) would be 1/3 under a similar scenario. We then calculated the phylogenetic signal of extinction probabilities for each category of vulnerability and each type of threat using Pagel&#x02019;s &#x003bb;<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref></sup> and Abouheif&#x02019;s<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref></sup> statistical tests. These tests assume to reflect phylogenetic signal in a Brownian motion model of evolution and are&#x000a0;robust when polytomies are present, which is the case here<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par52">We then compared ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> when all genera found on islands belonging to a given category of vulnerability were lost to ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> when genera were distributed randomly among categories of vulnerability. In this randomization procedure, the number of genera per category of vulnerability and the number of categories of vulnerability a genus belonged to were retained. This procedure was run 1000 times and we calculated whether the frequency of the observed ExpPD<italic>loss</italic> per vulnerability category was higher than by chance (p_values<sub>all</sub>). This approach was similar to the one used in step 2 but here genera were randomized between categories of vulnerability instead of between islands as distinct units. To account for evolutionary distinctiveness and range-restriction, we also performed a similar analysis for ExpSR<italic>loss</italic> and ExpSR<italic>loss</italic><sub>ED</sub> (Supplementary method S2). Moreover, all analyses described above were conducted on all genera occurring on islands and then only on genera restricted to islands.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_MOESM2_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Dataset 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM3"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_51107_MOESM3_ESM.xlsx"><caption><p>Supplementary Dataset 1</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn><fn><p>Thomas Haevermans and Roseli Pellens&#x000a0;jointly supervised this work.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-51107-x.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>This work was supported by French state funds managed by the French National Research Agency within the Investissements d&#x02019;Avenir program under reference ANR-11-IDEX-0004-02. We are grateful to Dan Faith for his helpful advice on an earlier version of the manuscript.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>R.P., T.H., M.M. and S.V. conceived the project. S.V., R.P., T.H., M.M. designed this study and wrote the article. SV, RG and TH collected data. R.P., T.H. and M.M. obtained the financial support. All authors reviewed the manuscript. R.P. and T.H. are co-senior authors.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>Data will be made available following acceptance</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par53">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. Climate Change 2014: Synthesis Report. Contribution of Working Groups I, II and III to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. 151 (Pachauri, R. K. &#x00026; Meyer, L. A., 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPCC, 2019: Summary for Policymakers. IPCC Special Report on the Ocean and Cryosphere in a Changing Climate (H.-O. P&#x000f6;rtner, D.C. Roberts, V. Masson-Delmotte, P. Zhai, M. Tignor, E. Poloczanska, K. Mintenbeck, M. Nicolai, A. Okem, J. Petzold, B. Rama, N. Weyer, In press).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Yohe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A globally coherent fingerprint of climate change impacts across natural systems</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>421</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01286</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Millennium Ecosystem Assessment. Ecosystems and human well-being: synthesis (2005).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barnosky</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Has the Earth&#x02019;s sixth mass extinction already arrived?</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>471</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>57</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09678</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21368823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ceballos</surname><given-names>Gerardo</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>Paul R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirzo</surname><given-names>Rodolfo</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biological annihilation via the ongoing sixth mass extinction signaled by vertebrate population losses and declines</article-title><source>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</source><year>2017</year><volume>114</volume><issue>30</issue><fpage>E6089</fpage><lpage>E6096</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1704949114</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McLaughlin</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Boggs</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehrlich</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change hastens population extinctions</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2002</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>6070</fpage><lpage>6074</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.052131199</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972020</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavorel</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Araujo</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sykes</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change threats to plant diversity in Europe</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>8245</fpage><lpage>8250</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0409902102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15919825</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Sodhi, N., Brook, B. &#x00026; Bradshaw, C. Causes and consequences of species extinctions. <italic>The Princetown guide to ecology</italic> 514&#x02013;520 (2009).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Extinction risk from climate change</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2004</year><volume>427</volume><fpage>145</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature02121</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14712274</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bertelsmeier</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leadley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Courchamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of climate change on the future of biodiversity: Biodiversity and climate change</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>377</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1461-0248.2011.01736.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22257223</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pecl</surname><given-names>GT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity redistribution under climate change: Impacts on ecosystems and human well-being</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2017</year><volume>355</volume><fpage>eaai9214</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aai9214</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28360268</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dubos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Disentangling the effects of spring anomalies in climate and net primary production on body size of temperate songbirds</article-title><source>Ecography</source><year>2018</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1319</fpage><lpage>1330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ecog.03413</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Mittermeier</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>da Fonseca</surname><given-names>GAB</given-names></name><name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biodiversity hotspots for conservation priorities</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2000</year><volume>403</volume><fpage>853</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35002501</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10706275</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A global assessment of endemism and species richness across island and mainland regions</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2009</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>9322</fpage><lpage>9327</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0810306106</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19470638</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ricketts</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Pinpointing and preventing imminent extinctions</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2005</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>18497</fpage><lpage>18501</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0509060102</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16344485</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frankham</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inbreeding and Extinction: Island Populations</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>665</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.1998.96456.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cox</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Naivet&#x000e9; and an aquatic&#x02013;terrestrial dichotomy in the effects of introduced predators</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>674</fpage><lpage>680</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2006.07.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16879896</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilme</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biogeographic Evolution of Madagascar&#x02019;s Microendemic Biota</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>1063</fpage><lpage>1065</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1122806</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16709785</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caujap&#x000e9;-Castells</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conservation of oceanic island floras: Present and future global challenges</article-title><source>Perspect. Plant Ecol. Evol. Syst.</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ppees.2009.10.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wulff</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conservation Priorities in a Biodiversity Hotspot: Analysis of Narrow Endemic Plant Species in New Caledonia</article-title><source>PLoS ONE</source><year>2013</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>e73371</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0073371</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24058470</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caesar</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Grandcolas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellens</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Outstanding micro-endemism in New Caledonia: More than one out of ten animal species have a very restricted distribution range</article-title><source>PLOS ONE</source><year>2017</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>e0181437</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0181437</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28727847</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Vulnerability of biodiversity hotspots to global change: Biodiversity hotspots and global change</article-title><source>Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr.</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1376</fpage><lpage>1386</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/geb.12228</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vulnerability of island countries in the South Pacific to sea level rise and climate change</article-title><source>Clim. Res.</source><year>1999</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>137</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/cr012137</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Sober&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preliminary global assessment of terrestrial biodiversity consequences of sea-level rise mediated by climate change</article-title><source>Biodivers. Conserv.</source><year>2010</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1599</fpage><lpage>1609</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-010-9790-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Nunn, P., Kumar, L., Eliot, I. &#x00026; McLean, R. Regional coastal susceptibility assessment for the Pacific Islands: Technical Report. (2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impacts of climatic and oceanic processes on the threatened terrestrial vertebrates of the Pacific region</article-title><source>GeoResJ</source><year>2017</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.grj.2016.12.001</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Courchamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>BD</given-names></name><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclerc</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change, sea-level rise, and conservation: keeping island biodiversity afloat</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2014.01.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24486005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruhfel</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Primack</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller-Rushing</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic patterns of species loss in Thoreau&#x02019;s woods are driven by climate change</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>105</volume><fpage>17029</fpage><lpage>17033</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0806446105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18955707</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Will climate change promote future invasions?</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>3740</fpage><lpage>3748</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.12344</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bellard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Leclerc</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Courchamp</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Impact of sea level rise on the 10 insular biodiversity hotspots: Sea level rise and insular hotspots</article-title><source>Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr.</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/geb.12093</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wetzel</surname><given-names>FT</given-names></name><name><surname>Beissmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Vulnerability of terrestrial island vertebrates to projected sea-level rise</article-title><source>Glob. Change Biol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>2058</fpage><lpage>2070</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/gcb.12185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harter</surname><given-names>DEV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Impacts of global climate change on the floras of oceanic islands &#x02013; Projections, implications and current knowledge</article-title><source>Perspect. Plant Ecol. Evol. Syst.</source><year>2015</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>183</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ppees.2015.01.003</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Tehrany</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change impacts on the threatened terrestrial vertebrates of the Pacific Islands</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>5030</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-05034-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28706225</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preserving the Tree of Life</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2003</year><volume>300</volume><fpage>1707</fpage><lpage>1709</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1085510</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12805539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Consequences of climate change on the tree of life in Europe</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2011</year><volume>470</volume><fpage>531</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature09705</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21326204</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yesson, C. &#x00026; Culham, A. A phyloclimatic study of Cyclamen. <italic>BMC Evolutionary Biology</italic><bold>72</bold> (2006).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Conservation evaluation and phylogenetic diversity</article-title><source>Biol. Conserv.</source><year>1992</year><volume>61</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>10</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0006-3207(92)91201-3</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Threatened Species and the Potential Loss of Phylogenetic Diversity: Conservation Scenarios Based on Estimated Extinction Probabilities and Phylogenetic Risk Analysis</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>1461</fpage><lpage>1470</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.2008.01068.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18798854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Veron</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cadotte</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name><name><surname>Clergeau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavoine</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting loss of evolutionary history: Where are we?: Predicting loss of evolutionary history</article-title><source>Biol. Rev.</source><year>2017</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12228</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26467982</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forest</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Preserving the evolutionary potential of floras in biodiversity hotspots</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2007</year><volume>445</volume><fpage>757</fpage><lpage>760</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature05587</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17301791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Faith</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Evosystem services: an evolutionary perspective on the links between biodiversity and human well-being</article-title><source>Curr. Opin. Environ. Sustain.</source><year>2010</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cosust.2010.04.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purvis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nonrandom Extinction and the Loss of Evolutionary History</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>288</volume><fpage>328</fpage><lpage>330</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.288.5464.328</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10764644</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cahill</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>How does climate change cause extinction?</article-title><source>Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci.</source><year>2012</year><volume>280</volume><fpage>20121890</fpage><lpage>20121890</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2012.1890</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Eliot</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Stul</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An indicative index of physical susceptibility of small islands to coastal erosion induced by climate change: an application to the Pacific islands</article-title><source>Geomat. Nat. Hazards Risk</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>691</fpage><lpage>702</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19475705.2018.1455749</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure of coastal built assets in the South Pacific to climate risks</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>992</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andr&#x000e9;fou&#x000eb;t</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Conservation of low-islands: high priority despite sea-level rise. A comment on Courchamp</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2015</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>2</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2014.10.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25454210</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>CT</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Loss of coral reef growth capacity to track future increases in sea level</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2018</year><volume>558</volume><fpage>396</fpage><lpage>400</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41586-018-0194-z</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29904103</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kench</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>McLean</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coral islands defy sea-level rise over the past century: Records from a central Pacific atoll</article-title><source>Geology</source><year>2015</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>518</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1130/G36555.1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fick</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>WorldClim 2: new 1-km spatial resolution climate surfaces for global land areas: NEW CLIMATE SURFACES FOR GLOBAL LAND AREAS</article-title><source>Int. J. Climatol.</source><year>2017</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>4302</fpage><lpage>4315</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/joc.5086</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Palacios</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Island biogeography: Shaped by sea-level shifts</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>532</volume><fpage>42</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17880</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27027292</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Steinbauer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Late Quaternary climate change shapes island biodiversity</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2016</year><volume>532</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>102</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature17443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27027291</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cai</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Increasing frequency of extreme El Ni&#x000f1;o events due to greenhouse warming</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2014</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>111</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate2100</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ORSTOM. Atlas de la Nouvelle Cal&#x000e9;donie et d&#x000e9;pendances. 226 (Orstom, 1981).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">D&#x000ed;az, S. Summary for policymakers of the global assessment report on biodiversity and ecosystem services of the Intergovernmental Science-Policy Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services (2019).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Mutke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Kier</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barthlott</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global diversity of island floras from a macroecological perspective</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2008</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>127</lpage><?supplied-pmid 18036182?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18036182</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Whittaker, R. J. &#x00026; Fern&#x000e1;ndez-Palacios, J. M. Island biogeography: ecology, evolution, and conservation (2007).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">MacArthur, R. H. &#x00026; Wilson, E. O. The theory of island biogeography. (Princeton, NJ: Princeton UniversityPress, 1967).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Orozco</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Phylogenetic approaches reveal biodiversity threats under climate change</article-title><source>Nat. Clim. Change</source><year>2016</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>1110</fpage><lpage>1114</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nclimate3126</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yamada</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Nunn</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mimura</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Machida</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Methodology for the assessment of vulnerability of South Pacific island countries to sea level rise and climate change</article-title><source>J. Glob. Environ. Eng.</source><year>1995</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change CZMS. Common methodology for assessing vulnerability to sea-level rise. Report of the Coastal Zone Management Subgroup, IPCC Response Strategies Working Group, Ministry of Transport, Public Work and Water Management,. (1991).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">UNEP-WCM. Global islands database. (2013).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The IPBES Conceptual Framework &#x02014; connecting nature and people. Curr. Opin. Environ</article-title><source>Sustain.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>16</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Davies, K. <italic>et al</italic>. Chapter 2. Nature&#x02019;s contributions to people and quality of life. in IPBES Regional and subregional assessment of biodiversity and ecosystem services for Asia and the Pacific (M. Karki et al., 2018).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Sodhi</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradshaw</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergies among extinction drivers under global change</article-title><source>Trends Ecol. Evol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>453</fpage><lpage>460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tree.2008.03.011</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18582986</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Titeux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Henle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mihoub</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Brotons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change distracts us from other threats to biodiversity</article-title><source>Front. Ecol. Environ.</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>291</fpage><lpage>291</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/fee.1303</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Otto</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Unpaid extinction debts for endemic plants and invertebrates as a legacy of habitat loss on oceanic islands</article-title><source>Divers. Distrib.</source><year>2017</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>1031</fpage><lpage>1041</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ddi.12590</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tang, C. Q. <italic>et al</italic>. Global monocot diversification: geography explains variation in species richness better than environment or biology. <italic>Bot</italic>. <italic>J</italic>. <italic>Linn</italic>. <italic>Soc</italic>, 10.1111/boj.12497 (2016).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stuessy</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name><name><surname>K&#x000f6;nig</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sep&#x000fa;lveda</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Paraphyly and Endemic Genera of Oceanic Islands: Implications for Conservation<sup>1</sup></article-title><source>Ann. Mo. Bot. Gard.</source><year>2014</year><volume>100</volume><fpage>50</fpage><lpage>78</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3417/2012087</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garnock-Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence-based review of the taxonomic status of New Zealand&#x02019;s endemic seed plant genera</article-title><source>N. Z. J. Bot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>163</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0028825X.2014.902854</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Brummitt, R., Pando, F., Hollis, S. &#x00026; Brummitt, N. World geographical scheme for recording plant distributions. (2001).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multidimensional biases, gaps and uncertainties in global plant occurrence information</article-title><source>Ecol. Lett.</source><year>2016</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>992</fpage><lpage>1006</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/ele.12624</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27250865</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jetz</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bioclimatic and physical characterization of the world&#x02019;s islands</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>15307</fpage><lpage>15312</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1306309110</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24003123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redding</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Mooers</surname><given-names>A&#x000f8;</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating Evolutionary Measures into Conservation Prioritization</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><year>2006</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1670</fpage><lpage>1678</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.2006.00555.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17181802</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Harvey, P. &#x00026; Pagel, M. The Comparative Method in Evolutionary Biology. (1991).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Abouheif, E. A method for testing the assumption of phylogenetic independence in comparative data. <italic>Evolutionary Ecology Research</italic> 895_909 (1999).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>M&#x000fc;nkem&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>Tamara</given-names></name><name><surname>Lavergne</surname><given-names>S&#x000e9;bastien</given-names></name><name><surname>Bzeznik</surname><given-names>Bruno</given-names></name><name><surname>Dray</surname><given-names>St&#x000e9;phane</given-names></name><name><surname>Jombart</surname><given-names>Thibaut</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiffers</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><name><surname>Thuiller</surname><given-names>Wilfried</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How to measure and test phylogenetic signal</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2012</year><volume>3</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>756</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.2041-210X.2012.00196.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Molina-Venegas, R. &#x00026; Rodr&#x000ed;guez, M. &#x000c1;. Revisiting phylogenetic signal; strong or negligible impacts of polytomies and branch length information? BMC Evol. Biol. <bold>17</bold> (2017).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>