<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Compared with the reference period, the result show that precipitation was predicted a decrease under the future climate scenarios, while the T
 <sub class="sub">mean</sub>, T
 <sub class="sub">max</sub>, and T
 <sub class="sub">min</sub> all exhibited increasing trends. The increase of the T
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> was greater than that of the T
 <sub class="sub">mean</sub> and T
 <sub class="sub">min</sub>. Driven by the multi-GCM projections of climate change, the maize growth in the Gaotai and Ganzhou areas was simulated to obtain the yield, CWC, and WP. Compared with simulation results based on field experiments from 2012–2015, the WP in the two typical agricultural areas both exhibited an increasing trend, which was mainly attributed to decrease of crop water consumption. The water productivity under three RCP scenarios in the Gaotai area during 2021–2050 increased by 9.2%, 14.3%, and 11.8%, and which increased by 15.4%, 21.6%, 19.9% in the Ganzhou area, respectively, most of which were larger than 2 kg/m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>, indicating that water-heat-carbon projected under the RCP4.5 scenario in the middle irrigated areas of the HRB synergized the best for maize growth. Although the irrigation schedule in this study was unchanged, implications of the relevant water saving practices for the irrigated areas of the middle HRB could also be obtained from the perspective of the increase of efficiency in the process of field water application. The specific suggestions emphatically include: (1) improving traditional irrigation methods and concepts of field water use (using the modernized basin, prompting the water-saving education for farmers); (2) implementing water-saving irrigation technologies and equipment in areas with higher income or powerful financial support. The findings can provide useful information on the Hexi Corridor and the Belt and Road to policy-makers and stakeholders for sustainable development of the water-ecosystem-economy system.
</p>
