<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">We found that in the first half of the last century, the error in the 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">orientalis</italic> tree-ring δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C was relatively high, but it decreased gradually over time. It seems that saplings exhibited varying responses to environmental change; this, can be described as the “juvenile effect”. One reason for this age-related trend in δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C could be the recycling of respired air that has already been depleted of 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C by young trees growing close to the forest floor. Plant tissue δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C is significantly lower than that found in the atmosphere because atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> contains 98.9% of light-stable carbon isotope and 1.1% heavy-stable carbon isotope, and the light-stable carbon isotope is preferentially absorbed during photosynthesis, resulting in carbon isotope fractionation, which is known as the “carbon isotope effect”
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. This process may be influenced by biotic factors, such as tree age and height, as well as abiotic factors such as meteorological conditions (radiation regime, temperature, precipitation, atmospheric pressure, etc.), CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration, site conditions (water availability, nutritional constraints, elevation and slope exposure, etc.), and forest management and anthropogenic perturbations (fires, climate change, etc.)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>. Chen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup> suggested that altitudinal variation in δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C may be negative or unchanged for plants growing in arid and/or semiarid regions, and atmospheric pressure has a negative effect on plant δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C. Di Matteo 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup> conducted a replicated field trial to characterize the interacting effects of aspect and intensifying drought on foliar δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C and to quantify temporal variation in stomatal conductance. They found a significant reduction in stomatal conductance (p &lt; 0.01) as the drought increased along a sunny slope, and foliar δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C increased significantly (p &lt; 0.01). In this study, we selected 10 typical plots, for which the altitude ranged from 332 m to 562 m and located on two slope aspects, to carry out our study with the original intention of understanding the average conditions of iWUE and tree growth of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">orientalis</italic> in northern China. Therefore, we did not take into account the effect of differences in exposure and elevation on tree-ring δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C.
</p>
