<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At broad spatial scales, overall patterns and degree of size change in our study are similar to those found for several other terrestrial ectotherms examined so far (McCarthy, Masson, Thieme, Leimgruber, &amp; Gratwicke, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Tryjanowski, Sparks, Rybacki, &amp; Berger, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Wikelski &amp; Thom, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). Two species of European frogs, for example, increased in size from 1963 to 2003 (Tryjanowski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>) in conjunction with milder winters, and the authors suggest that warmer winters may have increased the number of insect prey, resulting in higher growth rates of these species. Size of marine iguanas and at least one population of salamanders are also known to be correlated with resource availability; both species were reported to have shrunk during periods of decreased food availability (Bendik &amp; Gluesenkamp, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Wikelski &amp; Thom, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). However, in our study, size increases were not greatest in areas with the highest increases in frost‐free days (a proxy for number of feeding days), nor in areas that were both warmer and wetter, which should lead to increased primary productivity. Thus, resource availability may not always be the driving mechanism for size changes in wood frogs, as has been suggested for other species (Yom‐Tov &amp; Yom‐Tov, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Yom‐Tov, Yom‐Tov, &amp; Jarrell, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), but explicit tests of stomach contents in museum specimens over time would help directly address this. It is possible that frost‐free days do not correlate directly with higher prey availability, so future studies should also examine changes in primary productivity with respect to body size, as suggested by Huston and Wolverton (
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and as examined in Gardner et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Studies that investigate the interrelationship between temperature and precipitation on resource availability would be informative because changes in rainfall will be less consistent and predictable than temperature, and may vary over even finer spatial and temporal scales (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
