<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study is the first of its kind to assess the way different plant communities in the subalpine and lower alpine belts of the European Alps reacted to climate changes over the last two to four decades. It demonstrates that reactions differ considerably between vegetation types, with the most important changes in those linked to long snow cover. The vulnerability of 
 <italic class="italic">Salicion herbaceae</italic> (typical snowbeds) was already suspected by Braun‐Blanquet (
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1975</xref>). Indeed, monitoring eastern Switzerland vegetation of a very late snowmelt patch dominated by the moss 
 <italic class="italic">Polytrichum sexangulare</italic> from 1921 to 1947, Braun‐Blanquet (
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1975</xref>) observed an increasing cover of snowbed plant species in response to shorter snow cover and warmer temperatures. Moreover, he hypothesized that snowbeds will be progressively invaded by species from the surrounding siliceous grasslands. Therefore, it is likely that, during the last few decades, some snowbed communities took refuge in 
 <italic class="italic">Polytrichum sexangulare</italic> communities, altering their species composition. Simultaneously, snowbed species colonized many summits and slopes, where, as a result of glacier and snow cover reductions, new snowbed areas were available for colonization (Grytnes et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Therefore, snowbed species can still find suitable areas in the coldest microhabitats, but with potential detrimental consequences for the communities currently present. This corroborates the theory of Scherrer and Körner (
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), who sustained that alpine terrain offers a variety of thermal microhabitats over very short distances, which will be suitable for the majority of species.
</p>
