<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39" class="p">In China, heat wave was nationwide defined as daily maximum temperature ≥35 °C with duration ≥3 days by Chinese Meteorological Administration (CMA). However, some studies indicated that it might be inappropriate for a large country like China to use an absolute temperature as the threshold for defining heat waves due to the variable vulnerability to heat waves in different regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>]. The health impact of heat wave under different definitions had been examined in two previous studies conducted in Beijing [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>] and Nanjing, China [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. Tian et al. compared 18 heat wave definitions by combining heat wave thresholds (87.5th, 90.0th, 92.5th, 95th, 97.5th, and 99th percentile of daily mean temperature) with different duration days (≥2 to ≥ 4 days) to assess the short-term impact of heat waves on CHD mortality, and found that heat wave definition using 97.5th percentile of daily mean temperature and duration ≥2 days produced the best model fit [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>] . Chen et al. reported that heat waves defined as ≥4 consecutive days with daily mean temperature &gt;98th percentile were the most appropriate to estimate the influence of the added effect of heat waves on cause-specific mortality in Nanjing among 15 heat wave definitions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. In our study, heat wave defined by HW14 (daily mean temperature &gt;99th percentile and duration ≥3 days) showed the best predictive ability in evaluating heat wave-mortality relationship, and using the CMA definition underestimated the mortality risks of heat waves in Wuhan. Therefore, region specific definitions based on relative temperature thresholds are needed to design effective local heat warning systems [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>]. In addition, our results showed that, with the same relative thresholds and durations, heat waves using daily maximum/minimum temperature metrics and daily mean temperature metric had similar estimates of mortality risks, which was consistent with previous studies focusing on temperature-mortality relationship [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>]. However, daily mean temperature can capture heat wave effects more completely in the present study, and mean temperature was most commonly used to assess the association between temperature and mortality since mean temperature can represent the exposure throughout the whole day and night and provide more easily interpreted results within a policy context [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>].
</p>
