<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation status</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds on the Scotian Shelf are located in traditional groundfish fishing grounds [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref036">36</a>], with the majority of activity occurring from the pollock, silver hake, redfish, and halibut bottom trawl fisheries. As a result, high bycatch of 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span>, with records upwards of 9000 kg, has been reported [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref038">38</a>]. Fisheries and Oceans Canada (DFO) took the first step towards elevating the conservation status of the population of 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> in 2004, when an area commonly referred to as ‘The Patch’ by local fisherman was recognized as an ecologically significant area. This recognition was based on the rarity/uniqueness of the 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds present in the area and their fragility/sensitivity to fishing impacts [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref039">39</a>]. Information from fishermen, bycatch records from commercial fisheries, and 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> scientific observations were used to delineate hotspots of 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> in The Patch and nearby areas in Emerald Basin and Sambro Bank [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref038">38</a>]. This ecologically significant area was later modified in its extent to encompass a larger portion of Emerald Basin and was formally identified as an Ecologically and Biologically Significant Area (EBSA) by DFO in 2006 [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref040">40</a>]. Under the directive of the United Nations General Assembly (UNGA) Resolution 61/105, this species also received status as a vulnerable marine ecosystem (VME) indicator in 2008 by the Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organization (NAFO; [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref041">41</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2009, DFO introduced the Policy for Managing the Impacts of Fishing on Sensitive Benthic Areas (SBA; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dfo-mpo.gc.ca/reports-rapports/regs/sff-cpd/benthi-eng.htm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.dfo-mpo.gc.ca/reports-rapports/regs/sff-cpd/benthi-eng.htm</span>) as part of the Sustainable Fisheries Framework policy suite, aimed at achieving a more ecosystem-based approach to fisheries management. The SBA Policy was created for the purpose of aiding DFO in “managing fisheries to mitigate impacts of fishing on sensitive benthic areas or avoid impacts of fishing that are likely to cause serious or irreversible harm to sensitive marine habitat, communities and species”, and is the main tool used by DFO to mirror in domestic waters its commitment under the UNGA 61/105 to identify and protect vulnerable marine ecosystems on the high seas from bottom-contact fishing. To assist with the identification and mapping of SBAs, DFO held a national advisory process (NAP) that included both scientists and stakeholders on the ‘Occurrence, Susceptibility to Fishing, and Ecological Function of Corals, Sponges, and Hydrothermal Vents in Canadian Waters’ [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref042">42</a>]. The uniqueness of the 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds on the Scotian Shelf, the biogenic habitat it forms, and its fragility and risk of serious or irreversible harm from fishing qualified it for protection under the SBA Policy, and as a result, the habitat occupied by 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> emerged during the 2010 NAP as a clear conservation priority for the Department. Through kernel density estimation (KDE) analysis of research vessel trawl catch this habitat was determined to occupy an area of ~8,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref043">43</a>]. This approach does not take into account environmental variables and is based solely on the co-location of catches with high sponge weights, and the transition between the area occupied by those catches and those surrounding catches outside of the sponge grounds (see [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref044">44</a>] for description). Following the NAP, the Groundfish Enterprise Allocation Council (GEAC) implemented a voluntary closure to protect the sponges from mobile gear (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dfo-mpo.gc.ca/oceans/publications/cs-ce/page09-eng.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.dfo-mpo.gc.ca/oceans/publications/cs-ce/page09-eng.html</span>). In 2013, two bottom fishery closure areas were designated by DFO to protect the significant concentrations of 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> in Emerald Basin, representing the first application of the SBA Policy in Canadian waters. The design of the conservation areas was informed by a working group that included fishing representatives of active fleets in the area. The Emerald Basin 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> Conservation Area is 197 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in size, and represents a modified version of the original boundaries of the voluntary closure implemented by GEAC in 2010. A second area 62 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in size, termed the Sambro Bank 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> Conservation Area, was implemented over a second significant concentration of 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> in order to protect the area from bottom contact fishing gears and to provide replication to aid population recovery. These two conservation areas protect only ~3% of the total 8,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> habitat occupied by the 
  <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds (as determined from KDE analysis).
 </p>
</sec>
