<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Vazella pourtalesi</span> response data
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> presence and absence data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205505.g002" href="#pone.0205505.g002">Fig 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0205505.s001" href="#pone.0205505.s001">S1 Table</a> in supplementary material) were obtained from several different sources: DFO’s multispecies trawl survey conducted in the Maritimes Region between 2007 to 2017 (presences and absences), DFO optical (in-house camera/video and remotely operated vehicle) benthic surveys conducted between 2001 and 2017 (presences only), and commercial bycatch records from the Fisheries Observer Program (FOP) from 1997 to 2007, and 2010 to 2015 (presences only). The DFO multispecies trawl survey is stratified random (by depth) and conducted using primarily Western IIA trawl gear. The average distance of these tows is ~ 3.17 km. Absence records were created from null (zero) catches that occurred in the same surveys. Commercial bycatch data between 1997 to 2007 from the Fisheries Observer Program was further post-processed and validated for accuracy (see [
  <a rid="pone.0205505.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref035">35</a>] for more details), while the data from 2010 to 2015 was extracted directly from the Maritimes Fishery Science Database managed by DFO. Commercial trawls are much longer in duration and may follow bottom contours and/or retrace their footprint through the course of a 10+ km tow. For both the DFO multispecies trawl survey and FOP data, start coordinates were used to represent the tow, whereas for the DFO benthic imagery survey data the actual location of the 
  <span class="italic">V</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> record 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> was used. A 1 x 1 km grid matching that of the environmental data was placed over the study area and the presence-absence data were reduced to one record per cell, with a presence taking precedence over an absence if both occurred in the same cell. This gave a total of 215 presences (102 from the DFO trawl surveys, 47 from DFO benthic science surveys, and 66 from the FOP) and 2867 absences for the model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inclusion of response data with different rates of detection or "catchability", spatial bias, and spatial resolution may introduce bias in species distribution models. For instance, the optical surveys used in this study were targeted towards areas of interest (i.e., areas of known sponge distribution), have a high rate of detection, low spatial coverage and high resolution, compared to the RV trawl survey and commercial bycatch data which aggregate the catch across larger areas (i.e., ~3 km and ~10+ km, respectively). Use of null data from the research vessel survey only will introduce another form of bias in terms of false negatives due to poor catchability, but as the absence data dominate the records and are generated from a random stratified survey, we consider any such biases to be negligible compared to those of the presence data. Ideally, models would be conducted with a single data type with random stratification across the study area (i.e. in this instance, using only those records from the RV trawl surveys). Given the scarcity of presences in the trawl survey data and differing spatial coverage from the optical surveys and commercial data, we chose to accept the biases incurred from combining all three datasets. We note however that the resulting predictive surfaces may be driven by such biases, particularly towards areas of aggregation of the optical survey and commercial bycatch data, which are not accompanied by absences records. Similarly, we caution against over-interpreting the boundaries of suitable and unsuitable habitat predicted by the model as a result of this spatial bias.</p>
</sec>
