<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For each species, the spatial pattern of observed responses was compared with that expected under each different GCM. To do this, we tested the level of agreement between observed and expected responses in the same sites by adopting a null-model approach [
 <xref rid="pone.0189468.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189468.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0189468.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. First, we defined the measured agreement (
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">obs</italic>
 </sub>) as the number of sites where the observed and the expected responses are spatially matching (i.e. both positive, both neutral, or both negative) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189468.g002" class="xref">Fig 2j</xref>). Second, we generated 30,000 random permutations of the expected responses and calculated the simulated agreement with the observed responses for each permutation (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">sim</italic>
 </sub>). Third, we calculated the probability of the null hypothesis (
 <italic class="italic">P{A</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">sim</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic class="italic">&gt; a</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">obs</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic class="italic">}</italic>) that the measured agreement was drawn at random from the distribution of the simulated agreements (Gotelli, 2000) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189468.g002" class="xref">Fig 2k</xref>). In other words, the null hypothesis is that the measured agreement is obtained by chance from a random geographic pattern of expected responses. This probability is a measure of the level to which the responses expected on the basis of a given GCM explains the actual responses observed in the sites. When the null hypothesis can be rejected (
 <italic class="italic">P{A</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">sim</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic class="italic">&gt; a</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">obs</italic>
 </sub>
 <italic class="italic">} &lt; 0</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">05</italic>), the specific GCM used for modelling explains the real pattern of tree growth variation occurring in Europe.
</p>
