<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two Field Experiments on Potential PFB Triggers</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Role of Fleas</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Foundational to the PFB hypothesis is the assumption that fleas are critical to plague transmission. Substantial evidence of this has accumulated for &gt;100 years and remains basically unchallenged (
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
   <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>, 
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>, 
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>, 
   <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>, 
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>). That said, fleas may not be particularly efficient at transmitting 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>, providing an explanation for evolution of high virulence of this pathogen (
   <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>); probability of transmission is positively correlated with high levels of host bacteremia that often become lethal. Importantly for the PFB hypothesis, flea inefficiency leads to the need for large numbers of fleas to further increase the probability of transmission and infection (
   <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>). Field evidence regarding flea abundance and plague transmission includes flea control experiments that increased rodent survival rates (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) and halted the progression of epizootic plague (
   <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>–
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>). Although less dramatic variation in flea densities may be more difficult to link to plague transmission rates (
   <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>), flea parasitism in one study was negatively correlated with PD survival (
   <span class="italic">Cynomys parvidens</span>; Eads and Biggins in preparation).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Below, we provide experimental evidence regarding the plausibility of recreational shooting and poisoning of PDs as potential triggers for the flea-plague PFB cycle. Recreational shooting (
   <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>) and poisoning (
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>) are episodic and cause high localized mortality in PD populations. These types of events occur at scales that would seem relevant for PFB triggering. For example, we observed &gt; 97 PDs shot during one morning on a colony of about 300 PDs in Montana (not the colony sampled for study below), and the rodenticide in our South Dakota study was distributed over a 20.6-ha portion of a 70.4-ha colony. Under the PFB hypothesis, episodic host mortality should cause fleas to abandon PD carcasses and flock to living hosts. If so, large numbers of fleas should be collected from burrows near PDs killed by recreational shooters and from burrows in portions of PD colonies that are poisoned.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flea Sampling and Data Analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On 22 June 2006, we conducted flea sampling in “active” burrows of a black-tailed PD (
   <span class="italic">Cynomys ludovicianus</span>) colony in Phillips County, Montana (Colony B-100) on which recreational shooting had occurred within the previous few days (judging from the condition of the PD carcasses found). Burrow activity was classified using the presence of fresh scat (
   <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>). Sampling consisted of inserting a plumber's snake tipped with a 15 × 15 cm flannel cloth into each active burrow opening as far as possible for about 30 s and removing the cloth for flea collection and counting (
   <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>). The flannel is a crude surrogate for a PD that is investigating the burrow. The insertion technique was done twice at each burrow with a delay between insertions to allow counting and removing fleas from the cloth. Total number of fleas was recorded for each burrow, along with the presence or absence of a dead PD within 1 m of the burrow opening. We graphically presented the data as prevalence (frequencies of burrows from which fleas were collected and not collected), but we used a non-parametric Mann-Whitney test on numbers of fleas collected from each burrow to evaluate the influence of presence or absence of a dead PD at or near the burrow.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zinc phosphide rodenticide was applied to a portion of a black-tailed PD colony (Cutbank) on the Buffalo Gap National Grassland in South Dakota as part of a “boundary control” effort on 12 December 2017. We sampled active burrows and recorded data as described above, except each burrow (of at least 0.5 m depth) was sampled three times (instead of twice). Sampling was conducted before (5 October) and after application of the rodenticide (13–14 December) on poisoned and non-poisoned portions of the colony. This before-after-control-impact design allowed assessment of treatment effect while controlling for the effect of time, a desirable feature when measuring flea abundance which can vary considerably from month to month (
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>, 
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>, 
   <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>–
   <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>). We evaluated flea abundance using logistic regression models that had time (before or after) and treatment (poisoned or non-poisoned) as predictor variables. A significant (α = 0.05) treatment by time interaction would suggest a treatment-related disproportionate change in fleas over time. Because fleas were much more abundant on this South Dakota colony than on the Montana colony, we used a binomial response variable that considered 6 fleas as the cutoff point (≤6 fleas = 0, &gt; 6 fleas = 1) rather than simple presence or absence (prevalence, as used to graphically illustrate the Montana data).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
