<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plague is a zoonotic disease (caused by the bacterium 
  <span class="italic">Yersinia pestis</span>) that has a long history of causing human suffering and massive death rates. 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> is a generalist vectored by a wide range of fleas (Siphonaptera) (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>) and infecting a wide range of mammalian species. The impact of plague on humans has motivated much research, but the complexities caused by the array of hosts and fleas as they interact with each other and their environments have left many ecological questions unanswered (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>). Plague has colonized North America, South America, and portions of Africa and southeast Asia, at least, but relatively little attention has been devoted to plague as an invasive disruptor of ecosystems or its effect on species of conservation concern (
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">3</a>–
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>). Recent studies of plague in the prairie dogs (
  <span class="italic">Cynomys</span> spp.) of North America and their critically endangered associated predator, the black-footed ferret (
  <span class="italic">Mustela nigripes</span>), have suggested that this disease played a pivotal role in the decline of these mammals and continues to heavily influence conservation activities for them, and associated species (
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>–
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>). More than half the species of rodents of conservation concern in North America occur within regions where plague is present (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>); perhaps the plight of ferrets and prairie dogs (PDs hereafter) represents a phenomenon that is more common than has been recognized. Thus, broad conservation and public health issues associated with plague make this disease a prime candidate for consideration within a One Health framework (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two questions that are highly relevant to One Health objectives of understanding and managing plague risk are (1) how is plague maintained as a sylvatic disease and (2) what factors lead to epizootic outbreaks? Gage and Kosoy (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>) summarized 4 hypotheses for plague maintenance in communities of free-ranging mammals and their fleas: (1) continued enzootic transmission within populations of susceptible hosts and fleas, (2) chronic infection of partially resistant hosts, (3) prolonged survival in fleas, and (4) prolonged survival in soil. Experimental and field evidence has not been able to eliminate any of these hypotheses from consideration, and the 4 ecological mechanisms are not mutually exclusive (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Highly susceptible species such as PDs have traditionally escaped notice as potential reservoirs for plague. The logic was, because PDs are “highly vulnerable to plague, they should not be long-term reservoirs of the disease” (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>), more dramatically stated as Gunnison's PDs (
  <span class="italic">C. gunnisoni</span>) “are clearly not the maintenance species for plague” (
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>). Historically, partially resistant species were thought to be probable reservoirs or maintenance hosts for 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>), with microtine or cricetid mice listed as candidates (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>–
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>). Barnes (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>) implied that plague was maintained in foothill foci in Colorado, only periodically expanding onto the plains of eastern Colorado and causing epizootics in PDs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presumption that PDs and other highly susceptible rodents (
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>) are not long-term reservoirs of plague implies 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> is a periodic invader from residency elsewhere. Recent field studies support the hypothesis of maintenance by susceptible species whose populations often suffer moderate and varying levels of plague-caused mortality during the process and may be periodically decimated by epizootic eruptions. A 5-year controlled study employing flea-control as the treatment to impede plague transmission in 3 PD species implied that there was persistent plague circulation at sub-epizootic levels (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>), although vector control effects cannot be unerringly equated to plague effects. In similar studies using vector control, but with experimental plague vaccines added as a second treatment, woodrat (
  <span class="italic">Neotoma mexicana</span>) survival in Colorado (2-year study) (Biggins et al. submitted manuscript) and New Mexico (3-year study) (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) was significantly improved by the plague management tools. Unlike vector control, plague vaccine is thought to be specific in its protective effect. In another multi-year study of woodrats (
  <span class="italic">N. albigula</span>) in New Mexico, Kosoy et al. (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>) collected nest occupancy evidence suggesting maintenance of plague by localized die-offs that shifted over space and time. Finally, either vector control or a plague vaccine improved black-footed ferret survival by &gt; 200% despite lack of epizootic plague during the 4-year experiment in Montana (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>). Studies of the genetics of 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> and detection of the bacterium during sub-epizootic periods provide additional support for the hypothesis that PDs help to maintain plague or that 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> is otherwise maintained locally in or near PD colonies (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>–
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>). New invasions and colonization events may characteristically begin with epizootic plague and later subside into enzootic plague (
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>) and disease maintenance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The notion that plague is resident in a geographic area allows for epizootic eruptions in place, without the need for invasion or reinvasion by the bacterium or its resurrection from a quiescent state in soil or elsewhere. Thus, the discussion should be about the scales of eruptions in place vs. movement and the relative importance of each. The parsimonious hypothesis that plague “circulates at much reduced rates among most, if not all, of the same hosts that commonly become infected during epizootics” (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>) facilitates a discussion of factors that might promote the transition from enzootic to epizootic transmission rates. One goal in the discussion that follows is to review the roles of flea density, host density, and 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> density in that transition, and to propose positive feedback (PFB, hereafter) cycles as definitive elements of epizootic plague. We define PFB as an exponential increase in an effect resulting when the cause is cyclically amplified by the effect such that cause and effect labels become interchangeable. A second goal is to introduce the concept of triggering mechanisms that might initiate runaway PFB.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the concept of local enzootic plague maintenance by highly susceptible mammalian hosts or their associates, a second influential factor facilitating the PFB cycle might be early phase transmission (EPT) by fleas. Recent evidence on EPT (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>–
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>) is compelling. The speed of the PFB cycle might be dramatically enhanced if infected fleas can immediately transmit 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> rather than being delayed 5 days to months while the biofilm-mediated blockage of the proventriculus develops. Also, most fleas die of starvation shortly after becoming fully blocked, ending their ability to contribute to a PFB cycle. These attributes build a strong case for considering EPT as an important contributor to epizootic plague. However, epizootics (as we define them—see below) may last up to several months, thus allowing for blocked fleas to contribute to plague transmission. Another consideration might be the seemingly more efficient transmission reported for blocked fleas (
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>). Proventricular blockage is not thought to occur in 
  <span class="italic">Oropsylla hirsuta</span> and 
  <span class="italic">O. tuberculata cynomuris</span> (
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>), two important PD fleas, but contradictory results from studies of flea blockage raise questions (
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>) about the relative involvement of the two forms of transmission in free-ranging rodents.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Definitions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before delving into the details of transitions from enzootic plague maintenance to epizootic eruptions, it seems essential to discuss and explicitly define the terms. If plague circulates within a host species at rates that vary along a continuum (
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>), binomial classification of those rates into epizootic and enzootic is artifactual. Nevertheless, at least two arguments support continued use of these terms. First, the terms and concepts have a long history and, at least at the both ends of the spectrum, convey a sense of real and observable phenomena. When one observes the nearly complete collapse of a PD colony in just a few weeks due to plague, the term epizootic seems intuitively apt. Second, and within the context of this paper, we might give more refined meaning to epizootic if we can associate it with runaway PFB.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Epizootic has been defined as “Pertaining to an epidemic in animals” and epidemic as “a disease affecting a high proportion of the population over a wide area” (
   <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>). There is no temporal component to this definition, and the vagueness of “high proportion” and “wide area” render such definitions inadequate for our purposes. Because the definitions might vary somewhat when considering different species and contexts, it is useful for authors to define these terms in each individual report. For example, Biggins et al. (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>) described epizootics as resulting in the deaths of &gt;90% of a PD population and enzootic plague as affecting lesser proportions, but they did not provide temporal or spatial criteria. Ramakrishnan (
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) used the 90% mortality cutoff but required the episode to occur within 3 months and over at least 10 ha of habitat. In both examples, “affecting” animals is narrowed to considering plague-caused deaths, which seems appropriate given the lethality of plague and the need for a metric that estimates demographic attributes of populations relevant to conservation. For this paper, we adopt the criteria of Ramakrishnan (
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) to distinguish between epizootic and enzootic transmission, with further discussion below about the relationship to PFB cycles.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What if an outbreak takes several years to decimate the population of hosts (a phenomenon we have observed)? Under our definition of enzootic plague, populations can either decline or grow over long periods. What about deaths of just a few PDs that comprise a territorial harem polygynous family, or so-called “coterie” occupying a few hectares? At some point on the scale of individual organism to sub-population to population to range-wide distribution of a species we must pick a defining limit for clarity of communication. Clearly, death of an individual PD cannot define an epizootic, nor should we need extinction of a PD species to define it. Coining phrases like “mini-epizootic” or “small-scale epizootic” captures a sense of the mechanism working at small spatial scales but are semantically inarticulate oxymorons because epizootic and epidemic are defined as large scale phenomena.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term enzootic may be used in a broad context that considers all forms of plague maintenance, not just the transmission of plague at sub-epizootic rates. It can include 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> residing in micro-organisms (
   <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>), soil (
   <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>), or fleas (
   <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
   <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>). Here, however, we limit our discussion to active enzootic plague transmission. If epizootic defines only one end of a broad spectrum, enzootic must encompass a truly large range of transmission rates and host mortality. The concept of plague maintenance by low rates of transmission dates back almost to the discovery of 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> by Yersin in 1894. Low (
   <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>) and Elton (
   <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>) used the term “smoldering” plague to describe what we might think of as the slow transmission end of the spectrum. That term has been more recently resurrected (
   <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>, 
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>), but it connotes a rather benign manifestation of the disease that does not seem to accurately depict the moderate rates of transmission and mortality that are common and can have substantial impacts on host populations (
   <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
   <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>, 
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PFB Cycle Components of Epizootic Plague</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fleas are a vital component of the PFB cycles discussed herein. An increase in flea parasitism accompanying epizootic plague was observed at least a half century ago when Shchekunova et al. (
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>) noted “The dying out of the original inhabitants of burrows was accompanied by a migration of fleas onto surviving rodents and onto new settlers. As a result the index of the abundance of fleas on 
   <span class="italic">O. mongolica</span> here in the beginning of summer amounted to 3.2 and in the autumn—to 8.5…” Pauli et al. (
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>) uses the term “swarming” of fleas onto hosts during epizootics. Tripp et al. (
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>) suggests “Concentration of infected fleas on surviving animals may account for the rapid spread of plague during epizootics.” Salkeld et al. (
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>) mentions that “transmission rates snowball” due to “increased abundance of fleas searching for meals” [see also (
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>)]. These descriptions seem to infer PFB cycles. The graphics and notes on feedbacks from Ray and Collinge (
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>), the graphic of Reijniers et al. (
   <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>), and the discussion on “vicious circles” of disease transmission by Beldomenico and Begon (
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>) articulate parts of the PFB cycles we emphasize herein.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Disruptive effects of plague on PD social systems may fortify the flocking of infectious fleas to PD hosts. The presence of kin within PD coteries encourages PDs to remain in coterie territories, affording them fitness benefits such as cooperative predator detection and allogrooming to remove ectoparasites (
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>). As plague transmission increases and kin disappear, PDs likely inspect vacated burrows (e.g., to entomb dead PDs) and risk acquiring infectious fleas (
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>). Moreover, as PD coteries become vacated, opportunities for cooperation are diminished or eliminated, and PDs can move among former territories (
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>, 
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>), allowing them to acquire and ferry infectious fleas (
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These two mutually reinforcing PFB loops were encapsulated in a general description by Gage (
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>):
  </p>
  <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <p>“The rate of plague transmission by fleas also could be influenced by increased contact rates between infectious vectors and susceptible host individuals, with increased contact resulting in a concomitant increase in secondary infections as the disease spreads from an initial focal infection… Transmission rates also have been suggested to increase during epizootics as a result of infectious fleas becoming more and more concentrated on the decreasing number of surviving hosts…”</p>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We summarize these PFB cycles during an epizootic in PDs (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>) as juxtaposed loops of increasing flea:host ratios (Cycle A) joining increasing host and flea contact due to altered PD social systems and behaviors (Cycle B). The interaction is critical; the 2 loops must be considered together. A triggering event might initiate the primary PFB loop involving altered flea:host ratios. In the short term, the population of plague bacteria rapidly increases, the host population declines, vector numbers remain high, and infections increase. This is soon followed by initiation of the secondary PFB loop as sufficient deaths within coteries cause territorial vacancies that enhance unimpeded PD movements. At that point, both feedback loops operate together to synergistically magnify the overall PFB cycle. As the two connected loops repeat themselves, and remaining PDs become more mobile, the hazard rate rapidly escalates for each remaining PD. Both loops feed into ever higher transmission rates and ultimately into plague-caused deaths that both loops have in common (hence heavier arrows for the central parts of both loops). Triggers are exemplified (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). A dramatic trigger may initiate an epizootic under less than optimal conditions, or the PFB cycle might spontaneously ignite without any trigger when host and flea densities are high and 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> is enzootically abundant in the focal host or associated species.
  </p>
  <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Schematic representation of two synergistic positive feedback cycles involved in epizootic plague eruptions, with emphasis herein on prairie dogs (PDs). Cycle A illustrates an increase in flea:host ratio, and Cycle B illustrates the breakdown of PD territoriality. As the two interconnected loops repeat themselves, and remaining PDs become more mobile, the hazard rate rapidly escalates for each remaining PD. Both loops feed into the transmission rates and ultimately into the plague-caused deaths that the two loops have in common (hence heavier arrows for the central parts of both loops).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="fvets-06-00075-g0001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weather and habitat conditions doubtless influence hosts, fleas, and 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> (
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>, 
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>), which we simplistically represent with a single input block (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). Changes in temperature can influence flea reproduction and survival (
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>), replication rates of 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> (
   <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>), and proventricular blockage in fleas (
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>), thereby influencing transmission rates. Although trophic responses of hosts to weather are likely over longer terms (
   <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>), we consider only short-term changes; host populations respond more slowly than populations of fleas or 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>. Barnes (
   <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>) captured the oversimplification risks of such conceptual models by saying “In this complex and shifting milieu, it is often difficult to determine if fleas or rodents are most important because their roles may change with time, space, and circumstance.” Regardless, an external trigger causing substantial mortality of a subpopulation of hosts, or otherwise optimal conditions for transmission, might initiate an explosive PFB-mediated plague epizootic.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The illustration of the two PFB cycles is representative of early to mid-stages. At some point, there are few PD movements because most PDs are dead, fleas perish from starvation (
   <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>), and populations of live 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> likely diminish as host carcasses deteriorate or are consumed by scavengers (
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>, 
   <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">59</a>). Little is known about demographics and plague-caused mortality of PD fleas (
   <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">60</a>, 
   <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">61</a>). However, the primary fleas that seem to be central to 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> transmission in PDs (
   <span class="italic">Oropsylla hirsuta and O. tuberculata cynomuris</span>) are able to transmit 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> before blocking occurs (EPT) (
   <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>, 
   <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>), are perhaps highly capable of blocked flea transmission (Hinnebusch, personal communication), and might clear some infections but become infected once again when feeding on an infectious host, the latter of which helps to perpetuate plague transmission until the density of hosts is insufficient to support fleas (
   <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>, 
   <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The combined PFB loops (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>) are described in a temporal context but also have an implied spatial component. As with a metaphoric forest fire PFB cycle, this PFB of fleas and 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> cannot erupt for long in one place without running out of PD fuel. It must keep moving. However, unlike fire which moves primarily with the wind, it can move equally well in all directions. In fact, maximizing the area affected per unit of time would involve a feedback cycle that gets triggered in the middle of suitable space, where the movement can be envisioned as expanding circles of impact. This dynamic of 
   <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> over time and space may reflect how it maintains itself in an enzootic state (
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potentially destructive nature of PFB is commonly illustrated by reference to nuclear weapons. The self-accelerating chain reaction of an atomic bomb releases enormous energy, but the system needs a trigger of conventional explosives (which themselves involve PFB) for activation. Similarly, but at a smaller scale, the bullet from a rifle is propelled down the bore by the self-amplifying explosion of gunpowder, also ignited by a chain of triggering actions. The first of these actions is the shooter physically pulling the rifle's trigger that slams its firing pin into a small, pressure sensitive primer; these actions are analogous to any sudden and localized reduction of PD hosts that increases the flea:host ratio. The primer explodes, triggering the larger PFB explosion in the gunpowder within the cartridge casing and unleashing the destructive power of a speeding bullet, which is analogous to the destructive power of an expanding PFB-powered plague epizootic. Ironically, the rifle and shooter exemplified above could serve as a trigger in our PFB example involving PDs, fleas, and plague.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
