<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PFB Cycles, Balancing Negative Feedback, and Source-Sink Dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are examples of PFB that build and sustain ecological systems (
  <a rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" href="#B97">97</a>, 
  <a rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98">98</a>). Nevertheless, “Positive feedback mechanisms are usually associated with instability in a system” (
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">99</a>) and are often considered to be destabilizing and deleterious. Examples are the self-reinforcing nitrogen dynamics of invasive cheat grass (
  <span class="italic">Bromus tectorum</span>) in the western U.S (
  <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">100</a>), the human-triggered algal and microbial feedback loops that threaten coral reefs (
  <a rid="B101" ref-type="bibr" href="#B101">101</a>), and even the postulated runaway greenhouse involved in the massive Permian extinction (
  <a rid="B102" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102">102</a>). PFB can be facilitative or disruptive (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>), depending in part on the status of a process over time, and on the scale of assessment. Taken alone, a PFB seems to be ultimately destructive, but working in concert with negative feedback and other complex interactions, it can contribute to overall stability (
  <a rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103">103</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not all PFB cycles are destructive in PDs. One of the more interesting aspects of these tradeoff phenomena in PDs is the balancing of negative feedback and PFB cycles prior to invasion of plague. Over much longer time spans than those for the flea-plague PFB of epizootics, PFB has been discussed in PDs in the context of Allee effect (a positive correlation between population density and average individual fitness) resulting from increased effectiveness of predator warning communications and higher individual survival rates at higher population densities (
  <a rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104">104</a>). PDs clip grasses and forbs seasonally to maintain unrestricted vision, and repeated clipping of shrubs results in declining shrub densities over periods of years to decades; increased PD densities facilitate this PFB loop (
  <a rid="B105" ref-type="bibr" href="#B105">105</a>). In addition to the increased survival rates accompanying this PFB, PDs might have higher birth rates at higher population densities (
  <a rid="B106" ref-type="bibr" href="#B106">106</a>). Historically, the slow process of PFB in shrub reduction and increasingly efficient anti-predator behaviors with PD population growth may have gradually come into balance with the negative feedback of coterie territoriality and limiting resources. However, the plague-flea PFB cycle is explosive, and runaway flea-plague PFB will curb other processes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plague epizootics may occur in multispecies communities of hosts because 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> is a generalist parasite. It might be a mistake to single out a particular host species as the driver of these phenomena, although outbreaks are characteristic in various species of ground squirrels (including PDs). Even within the 
  <span class="italic">Cynomys</span> genus, manifestations of plague epizootics appear to vary among species. White-tailed PDs (
  <span class="italic">C. leucurus</span>) and other species within the 
  <span class="italic">Leucocrossuromys</span> subgenus may no longer reach peak densities in preferred habitat (grass-dominated sites with few shrubs) because epizootics repeatedly decimate populations that reach reasonable densities (
  <a rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" href="#B107">107</a>). From a source-sink perspective, the source has become the poor, shrub-dominated, habitats that maintain enzootic plague, which may have been considered the sinks for these PDs historically. An indirect effect of this phenomenon is failure of white-tailed PDs to create optimum habitat by clipping shrubs and killing them. This is not a true source-sink reversal. A source (prime PD grassland patch) can become a sink because of plague, but the sink (in this case shrubby habitat) was probably not a true sink in the sense of PD mortality exceeding natality. Nevertheless, this reversal in the overall flow of dispersing animals again illustrates the potential for 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> to be a “transformer species” in the western U.S. (
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
