<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plague, PFB Cycles, Conservation, and One Health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we emphasize the transition of plague activity from enzootic to epizootic explosions due to PFB. Our intent herein has been to focus primarily on the PFB loops that likely occur during an epizootic outbreak of plague, and to propose that those expanding cycles are a central element of epizootics as we narrowly define them (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). For an epizootic with PFB to occur, there must be adequate (although sometimes relatively low) densities of PDs distributed sufficiently uniformly to allow the rapid expansion of PFB to occur. There also needs to be adequate densities of fleas at the starting point.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The change in flea:host ratios during epizootics have been recognized and repeatedly mentioned for more than 50 years, and the recognition of plague as an enzootic phenomenon (smoldering), as well as exploding into epizootics, is also historic. We suggest these phenomena, coupled with the relatively inefficient transmission of 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> by fleas, as pivotal to understanding both the evolution of 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> and the ecological manifestations of plague. In PDs at least, the breakdown of territories during epizootics likely contributes substantially as a second reinforcing PFB loop. Our synthesis is a recasting of earlier discussions and observations into a theme that emphasizes sustained transmission and mortality caused by enzootic plague as a common starting point for epizootics, and centering on PFB as the amplifying centerpiece. PFB loops might be initiated by triggers; we speculated on anthropogenic triggers for the plague-flea epizootic loop and provided some supporting evidence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This reevaluation seemed useful because the history surrounding plague has tended to dampen such thinking. Plague initially received most attention as a series of human epidemics, and public health investigators later recognized epizootic outbreaks of sylvatic plague as elevating the risk to human health (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>). The focus on epizootics and epidemics motivated conversations (at least) about how such cycles could be adaptive and diverted attention from thinking about the more common conditions under which natural selection likely molded the life history attributes of 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If epizootics are not a necessary component of plague maintenance, and 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> evolved a lifestyle that requires high vector loads and high levels of bacteremia to persist (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>), we might expect host mortalities to be chronically high even without epizootics, especially in ecosystems where plague is not native. Mammalian species that can persist with sustained high population losses (e.g., PDs) may serve as reservoirs for 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>, but plague spillover into associated bystander species, even during enzootic periods, might result in their extirpation or extinction (e.g., as exemplified by black-footed ferrets). There may be mammal communities where epizootics, as we define them, are rare or absent (e.g., due to consistently low flea parasitism or intense territoriality). Lack of noticeable epizootic outbreaks should not be equated with lack of ecological impact of plague.
 </p>
</sec>
