<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ramifications of PFB Cycles for Plague Transmission</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intuitively, high host death rates will initiate an increase in flea densities beyond the threshold for epizootic plague (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>). Rates of flea collection [e.g., (
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>, 
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>)] and flea infection [e.g., (
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>, 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>)] are commonly higher from PD burrows after or during an epizootic than under non-epizootic. Some investigators emphasize the increase in flea abundance and infection as predictors or causes of epizootic plague [e.g., (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>)] and others as responses to epizootics [e.g., (
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>, 
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>)]. Under the PFB hypothesis, burgeoning flea numbers and infections are both cause and consequence after a cycle begins (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to PD social structure and territoriality, flea-plague PFB cycles may occur in a patchy manner (i.e., multiple “explosions” of feedback at the coterie level and slower transmission of 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span> between coteries). Group deaths within coteries seem likely because coterie members may share burrows as nesting environments (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>) and probably share the same sub-population of fleas in their burrows (similar to great gerbils, 
  <span class="italic">Rhombomys opimus</span>, in Central Asia) (
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">80</a>). After death of the primary coterie defenders, adjustment by members of adjacent coteries is likely (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>) and exposure rates of neighbors would be enhanced (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>). As epizootic activity increases and plague spreads among coteries, PFB cycles can become self-amplifying until nearly all hosts are parasitized by fleas and succumb to the disease.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our representation of change in flea:host ratio (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>) as hosts die may be oversimplified due to unequal susceptibility of individuals to flea parasitism and interactions among biotic and abiotic factors. For example, as the flea:host ratio increases during rapid plague transmission, the most susceptible individuals may take the initial brunt of the parasite shift and plague mortality. Adult male PDs could play an especially important role (
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>); they have much higher flea loads than adult females just after breeding season and often harbor the most fleas in summer and fall (
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>, 
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>). Adult male PDs might be the primary initiators of the PRB cycle because of their higher flea loads and because they are the primary coterie defenders (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>) and may be the first PDs to explore newly unoccupied territories and thus the first to accumulate newly questing, plague-positive fleas.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another potential PFB cycle that is intertwined with the flea-plague PFB is mediated by drought. It can be simplistically described as: poor forage (due to drought) leads to water balance and/or energetic limitations (
  <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">83</a>) that lead to poor host body condition (
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>) that leads to increased flea loads (
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>, 
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>, 
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">84</a>) that lead to even poorer host body condition (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>), and so on. This cycle might promote increased circulation of plague due to higher flea loads and perhaps initiate a flea-plague PFB eruption (
  <a rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85">85</a>). Under sub-optimal conditions for transmission, the developing epizootic may be self-limiting at the point where relatively flea-resistant individuals (e.g., PDs in good body condition) are remaining. Lending support to this hypothesis, Pauli et al. (
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>) found that PDs surviving an epizootic exhibited improved body condition compared to PDs before the epizootic. In many cases, however, a rapid change in flea:host ratio might overwhelm the entire population, resistant and susceptible alike.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recreational shooting of PDs might trigger PFB cycles by shifting fleas to the dwindling number of PDs and by affecting PD body condition. During a before-after-control-impact experiment involving shooting of PDs in Wyoming, surviving PDs on shot colonies increased vigilance 8-fold and reduced time spent foraging by 66% relative to PDs on control colonies protected from shooting (
  <a rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" href="#B86">86</a>), contributing to a 35% reduction in PD condition. Reductions in PD condition and hypothesized (
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>) increases in flea parasitism may trigger PFB. Moreover, the significant stresses of recreational shooting (
  <a rid="B86" ref-type="bibr" href="#B86">86</a>) may compromise the immune systems of some PDs, causing increases in flea parasitism (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>) and mortality in PDs that fail to overwinter, thereby further concentrating fleas on PDs. Although recreational shooting could potentially trigger several types of deleterious PFB cycles, a short-term epizootic cycle (if it developed) would overpower other cycles.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interactions among a wide array of variables could influence the change in flea:host ratio of the proposed PFB cycles. Flea populations are influenced by many factors that are beyond the scope of detailed discussion here (
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>, 
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>, 
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">84</a>, 
  <a rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" href="#B87">87</a>–
  <a rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89">89</a>). Weather and climate at spatial and temporal scales from microsites to El Niño patterns are influential (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>) (
  <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">90</a>–
  <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">92</a>) and, as noted above, recent studies suggest precipitation lag effects and host body condition further increase the complexity. Recreational shooting, poisoning, and other sources of host mortality may interact with weather and season. For example, shooting or poisoning after optimal weather conditions for plague transmission may be more likely to trigger an epizootic than shooting or poisoning that follows moisture and temperature conditions that are less favorable for fleas or 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several factors might serve to counter the initiation of epizootic PFB cycles. First, the flea density threshold concept of Lorange et al. (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>) is assumed to be critical, although the necessary levels of flea parasitism are unknown for wild, free-ranging hosts such as PDs. Second, intraspecific and interspecific competition among both fleas and hosts could provide negative feedback that impedes the initiation of the flea-plague PFB cycle (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>, 
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">93</a>). These phenomena could become interactively complex in systems involving multiple hosts and multiple flea species, but in situations where a single host is primarily responsible for plague circulation, host territoriality could limit transmission to enzootic rates (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>). Third, disease transmission rates in general are assumed to be at least somewhat dependent on host densities (
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">94</a>). However, for PDs, it seems that flea densities are more important. An epizootic eruption of plague occurred in Utah PDs when densities (from adjusted visual counts) (
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>) were just 2.3 PDs ha
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Biggins unpublished data). Flea parasitism was an important predictor of Utah PD annual survival during a 4-year study; epizootic plague was suspected in many cases, despite low PD densities (Eads and Biggins unpublished data). Thus, it is unsurprising that large rodent control campaigns have failed to eradicate plague in sylvatic systems and that tactic has been abandoned in Russia (
  <a rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95">95</a>). More localized control of peridomestic rodents, however, can reduce risk of plague exposure in humans (
  <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">96</a>). We emphasize highly plague-susceptible North American PDs in this treatise, but other species with proportions of populations that are immune to plague would be expected to exhibit much different population dynamics when challenged by plague.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In keeping with the idea that any significant cause of mortality might initiate a PFB cycle (increasing ectoparasite:host ratios), other vector-borne diseases (e.g., tularemia) should also be considered. Triggers might result in secondary interactions between diseases, transforming diseases that might characteristically have a moderate effect (which probably include some diseases native to North America, like tularemia) into triggers for the flea-plague PFB cycle. Conversely, we might consider that plague, operating within its own PFB cycle, might exacerbate the effect of native disease by altering the parasite:host ratio.</p>
</sec>
