<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Role of Fleas</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Foundational to the PFB hypothesis is the assumption that fleas are critical to plague transmission. Substantial evidence of this has accumulated for &gt;100 years and remains basically unchallenged (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>, 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>, 
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>, 
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>, 
  <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>). That said, fleas may not be particularly efficient at transmitting 
  <span class="italic">Y. pestis</span>, providing an explanation for evolution of high virulence of this pathogen (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>); probability of transmission is positively correlated with high levels of host bacteremia that often become lethal. Importantly for the PFB hypothesis, flea inefficiency leads to the need for large numbers of fleas to further increase the probability of transmission and infection (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>). Field evidence regarding flea abundance and plague transmission includes flea control experiments that increased rodent survival rates (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>) and halted the progression of epizootic plague (
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>–
  <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>). Although less dramatic variation in flea densities may be more difficult to link to plague transmission rates (
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>), flea parasitism in one study was negatively correlated with PD survival (
  <span class="italic">Cynomys parvidens</span>; Eads and Biggins in preparation).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Below, we provide experimental evidence regarding the plausibility of recreational shooting and poisoning of PDs as potential triggers for the flea-plague PFB cycle. Recreational shooting (
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>) and poisoning (
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>) are episodic and cause high localized mortality in PD populations. These types of events occur at scales that would seem relevant for PFB triggering. For example, we observed &gt; 97 PDs shot during one morning on a colony of about 300 PDs in Montana (not the colony sampled for study below), and the rodenticide in our South Dakota study was distributed over a 20.6-ha portion of a 70.4-ha colony. Under the PFB hypothesis, episodic host mortality should cause fleas to abandon PD carcasses and flock to living hosts. If so, large numbers of fleas should be collected from burrows near PDs killed by recreational shooters and from burrows in portions of PD colonies that are poisoned.
 </p>
</sec>
