<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">The polewards dispersion of larvae is projected to intensify gradually over the next decades along the east coast of Australia
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>, likely facilitating the population connectivity between historical and range extension zones. However, the accelerated warming along the east coast of Australia is anticipated to shorten the paralarval phase of 
 <italic class="italic">O. tetricus</italic>. A shorter paralarval phase may reduce dispersal capacity, population connectivity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>, and recovery of genetic diversity in the range extension area. Effects of ocean warming on reproductive seasons, frequency of paralarvae releases, swimming capabilities, paralarvae settlement windows, habitat suitability, and paralarvae mortality may also influence the connectivity of populations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore ‘seascape genetics’ studies must include oceanographic, life history, ecological and physiological data, in the context of ocean warming and changes in oceanic circulation into the examination of the population connectivity. This approach may provide better understanding of the structure, connectivity, genetic diversity, and capacity of populations to prevail in the new sections of their geographic distribution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic class="italic">Octopus tetricus</italic> has a life-span of 11 months
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> and allele frequencies could change between years of collection. To strengthen the robustness of our conclusions, future research should include larger samples sizes and from consecutive years within sites to assess stability of allele frequencies through time.
</p>
