<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Accounting for uncertainty in projected future flood hazards</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining probabilistic projections of local SLR with storm surge analysis more accurately assesses flood risk (details in Methods; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). The combined SLR and storm surge projections increase estimates of future flood risk (see also the discussion in
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a> versus Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Despite evaluating multiple studies, only the SLR projections from Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, Sweet 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, and Rasmussen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> provide enough information (i.e., full probability distributions) to account for interactions between uncertainties. Likewise our study and Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> are the only studies in this analysis that provide full probability distributions of storm surge estimates. To reduce complexity, we show four cases of the combined SLR and storm surge projections accounting for uncertainty. These cases depict how fast dynamics and non-stationarity impact storm surge estimates (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). In particular, there is a roughly 0.87 ft difference between stationary and non-stationary combined storm surge and SLR estimates. Additionally, combined storm surge and SLR estimates increase as ice-cliff and ice shelf feedback processes are triggered in the year 2065, which are triggered in high emissions scenarios (i.e., a roughly 0.14 ft increase when triggered using RCP8.5; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Moreover, these few cases highlight the complexity of estimating a single point when there are multiple uncertainties to consider.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of the 100-yr combined storm surge and sea-level rise in the year 2065 accounting for uncertainty. Note that larger values cannot be excluded (for example in the event of compound flooding).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47587_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1353" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
