<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining sea-level and storm surge projections</div>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Accounting for the interactions between SLR and storm surge is a crucial step in the assessment of coastal flood vulnerability. Specifically, it is necessary to account for the uncertainties surrounding SLR (see, for example, the discussion in
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>). Similar to the approach in Ruckert 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>, we account for uncertainty in both SLR and storm surge by combining the distributions. Following this approach, we combine the Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> no FD SLR distribution for the year 2065 with the ensemble of stationary storm surge values obtained in Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Because the distributions differ in ensemble size, we draw an ensemble size of 10,000 simulations of storm surge (each simulation projecting out to the 1000-yr return period) from the full distribution to correspond to the SLR ensemble size. We then approximate the 100-yr storm surge following the steps outlined in Ruckert 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span> (see paper for details). Following the same procedure, we also combine (1) Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> FD SLR distribution with the stationary storm surge in Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, (2) Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> no FD SLR distribution with the non-stationary BMA storm surge in Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, and (3) Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> FD SLR distribution with the non-stationary BMA storm surge in Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. It is also possible to use the sea-level distributions from Sweet 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, and Rasmussen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, as well as the other non-stationary storm surge ensembles presented in Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>; however, we choose to show the four cases stated above to make clear the differences between SLR with and without fast dynamics and stationary versus non-stationary storm surge.
 </p>
</sec>
