<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of information about storm surge analysis can lead to surprises</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Areas prone to storm surge like Norfolk also require information about the frequency of extreme water-level events when defining coastal vulnerability. In particular, analyses resolving these extreme events, especially long return periods, require long records of data (70+ years) to stabilize estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>. Our results are consistent with this conclusion. For example, the projections based on a 49 year record in Tebaldi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> produce a low bias for long return periods in comparison to the observations, our model, and other studies, which are all based on records of 80 to 90 years in length
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of different assumptions between storm surge projections. Panel (a) compares stationary storm surge levels with their associated return periods (inverse flood probability). Panel (b) compares the median 100-yr storm surge values based on stationary models to those based on non-stationary models in the year 2065.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47587_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1172" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on historical events, additionally it is important to resolve and assess extreme water-level events that have a low probability of occurring such as those with return periods greater than the 100-yr event. This is especially important because the Federal Emergency Management Agency and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers highly recommend that critical infrastructure or structures protecting critical infrastructure (e.g., levees and floodwalls) are built to withstand the 500-yr event plus freeboard
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Critical infrastructure are facilities that provide essential services to the community, protect the community, and are intended to remain open during and after major disasters. Such facilities include health care facilities, schools and higher education buildings, facilities storing hazardous material, and emergency response facilities (e.g., fire stations, police stations, and emergency operation centers)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. For example, in collaboration with the City of Norfolk’s resilience initiative and the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers, the Sentara Norfolk General Hospital (a level one trauma center located in the current 100-yr and 500-yr floodplains) is currently implementing measures to protect the hospital against SLR and storm surge in its five-year project (construction to be completed in 2020) to expand and modernize the hospital, in addition to a proposed storm surge barrier that would help protect the hospital and other nearby critical infrastructure
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite a very low probability of occurring, these events do occur (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). Over the course of 70 years (the potential useful lifetime of a building), a 500-yr event has an 18% probability of occurring
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. When these events occur, they are often considered high-impact disasters. Consider, for example, the storm surge of Hurricane Sandy, a roughly 400-yr event at the Battery in New York City
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. More importantly, consider the lesser known (in modern history), but violent Norfolk-Long Island Hurricane of 1821 and Storm of 1749. The Norfolk-Long Island Hurricane made landfall on September 3rd, 1821, hitting Norfolk, VA, among other major cities along the Mid-Atlantic and East Coast
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The hurricane is estimated to have caused a storm surge of roughly 10 ft in some areas of the Virginia coastline
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). This is an approximately 285-yr storm surge event (approximated using a method to calculate the median probability return period; see Methods). Based on historical records, we can reasonably constrain the uncertainty bounds between the 279- and 306-yr storm surge event as a larger storm surge event may have occurred during a hurricane in 1825 and less documentation exists for storm surges prior to 1806
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. A study by the reinsurance company Swiss Re estimates that the Norfolk-Long Island Hurricane of 1821 would cause 50% more damage than Hurricane Sandy and more than 100 billion U.S. dollars in damages if it were to occur today
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The Storm of 1749 (a hurricane) hit the Mid-Atlantic coast during October of 1749 causing roughly 30 thousand pounds in damages in Norfolk at that time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. During this storm, a 15 ft storm surge and subsequent flooding of the lower Chesapeake Bay area was reported
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). Moreover this storm was largely responsible for forming Willoughby Spit, 2 mile long and 1/4 mile wide peninsula of land at Sewell’s point
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. The storm surge of the Storm of 1749 is approximately a 389-yr storm surge event (approximated using a method to calculate the median probability return period; see Methods). Despite the potential high impact of low probability events and their importance in resilience planning, our model and Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> are the only models in this analysis to resolve return periods past the 100-yr event (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important also to note that storm surges may not be stationary (i.e., the statistics are not constant over time). While decision makers typically use stationary flood hazard information, neglecting non-stationary information can result in a low bias (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). In the year 2065, all non-stationary 100-yr storm surge values are greater than the storm surge values based on stationary models with a difference of up to a foot (with the exception of the non-stationary case based on the NAO index covariate time series; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). To put this into context, a difference of less than a foot in storm surge values can be the difference of millions of dollars in potential damages to the Norfolk area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. Despite the importance of considering the non-stationary behavior of storm surge projections, it is still an area of active research. In particular, there is an active debate on how best to account for and constrain potential non-stationary coastal surge behavior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. For example, a recent study by Wong
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> analyzes how different climate variable time series (e.g., temperature, sea level, NAO index, and time) impact non-stationary storm surge values. Although non-stationary storm surge is an area of active research, non-stationary flood hazard information is available and can be used by decision makers.
 </p>
</sec>
