<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Probabilistic projections</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, and Rasmussen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> are examples of probabilistic projections of SLR, which can be localized to the Sewell’s Point tide gauge. These studies are all based on the framework from Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> with the exception of Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. As such, understanding the method and framework behind Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> is of great importance to flood risk management strategies. Although Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> provides a valuable step forward in developing local probabilistic projections based on individual SLR components, it faces limitations with respect to the projection of the complex behaviors of the ice sheets, as well as the consideration of stabilization targets. Relevant studies that expand on these aspects include Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>, Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, and Rasmussen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> defines a set of probabilistic global and local SLR projections constructed with RCP scenarios by modeling individual processes that contribute to local SLR. The individual components include oceanic processes, ice sheet melt, glacier and ice cap surface mass balance, land-water storage, and long-term, local, non-climatic sea-level change. To calculate global sea-level probability distributions, Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> employs 10,000 Latin hypercube samples from cumulative SLR contributions. Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> then localizes these projections (i.e., at tide gauge locations) by applying sea-level fingerprints
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> employs the same framework as Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, except that it replaces the Antarctic ice sheet (AIS) projections with those based on DeConto and Pollard
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. The original AIS projections used in Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> account for simple assumptions of constant acceleration that underlies expert-judgement-based projections. Instead, the new approach influences buttressing ice shelves and hence accounts for marine ice cliff instability and hydrofracturing (for more details see
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>). However, the ensemble of AIS projections were developed using a simplified approach of sampling key physical parameters from a set of values and integrating paleo-observations with a pass/fail test rather than producing a probability distribution. Because Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> directly uses these AIS projections, the resulting SLR projections are potentially more conservative with respect to low probability AIS projections.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> employ two sets of simulated sea-level scenarios. One scenario assumes that there is no contribution of fast Antarctic ice sheet dynamics (e.g., ice cliff instability and hydrofracturing), while the other assumes that the fast dynamics is triggered. Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> emulate fast dynamics with a simplified approach that assumes a constant rate of disintegration once a critical temperature threshold is passed. For this study, we differentiate the scenarios as Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> FD and Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> no FD, respectively assuming fast dynamics is triggered and assuming fast dynamics is not triggered. Specifically, we use the results based on prior gamma distributions for the parameters that control the uncertain rate of disintegration and the threshold temperature that triggers fast dynamical disintegration.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> use a simple mechanistically motivated emulator to project coastal flooding hazards (BRICK: Building Blocks for Relevant Ice and Climate Knowledge model v0.2)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. The BRICK model simulates global mean surface temperature, ocean heat uptake, thermal expansion, changes in land-water storage, and ice melt from the AIS, Greenland ice sheet, and glaciers and ice caps. Wong and Keller
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> calibrate this model to observational records (paleoclimate and instrumental data) using a Bayesian approach. We use this model to extend and derive localized sea-level projections to the Sewell’s Point tide gauge (see details in Methods).
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rasmussen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> models local relative sea level using the Kopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> framework (as described above). The authors construct alternative ensembles that meet global mean surface temperature (GMST; relative to 2000) stabilization target scenarios. These scenarios stabilize warming at 1.5, 2.0, and 2.5 °C above pre-industrial levels, coinciding with targets identified in the Paris Agreement
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. To ensure each scenario meets the stabilization target criteria, only the models that have a 21st century increase in GMST (extrapolated from the 2070 to 2090 trend) of 1.5, 2.0, and 2.5 °C (±0.25 °C) are used to create the ensembles. Scenarios beyond 2100 are ensembles that undershoot the target temperature with the exception of the 2.5 °C scenario.
 </p>
</sec>
