<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The deposition of particles in the respiratory tract is size-dependent and deposited particles are removed by a number of physical, chemical, and biological clearance processes, including mucociliary movement, endo- and phagocytosis, dissolution, leaching, and protein binding.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref201" class="xref">201</xref>
 </sup> Thus, the first step of an inhaled allergen-carrying particle is evading the mechanical defenses of the respiratory tract and passing, for example, alveolar macrophages, which prevent inappropriate immune activation by removing inhaled allergens via phagocytosis.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref392" class="xref">392</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref394" class="xref">394</xref>
 </sup> The epithelial surface is a protective barrier, which protects the underlying tissue from many inhaled substances. The epithelial cells are covered by a viscous mucosal lining rich in immune cells and soluble components, such as antioxidants, complement proteins, and surfactant proteins.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref201" class="xref">201</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref395" class="xref">395</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref396" class="xref">396</xref>
 </sup> As the epithelium is more than a passive protective barrier, it recruits and activates more specialized immune cells and promotes inflammatory responses,
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref397" class="xref">397</xref>
 </sup> allergy is also discussed to be an epithelial barrier disease.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref131" class="xref">131</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref398" class="xref">398</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref400" class="xref">400</xref>
 </sup> For example, nasal epithelium is clearly different between healthy and allergic subjects and only in allergic subjects the transport of Bet v 1 is caveolar-mediated.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref401" class="xref">401</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
