<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A wide variety of commensal, symbiotic, and pathogenic microorganisms are found on the epithelial surfaces of the human body, such as the skin, lungs, and the gastrointestinal tract. Recent research suggests that the human microbiome is important to maintain physiological functions and to induce immune regulation by balancing the activities of Th1 and Th2 cells.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref430" class="xref">430</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref433" class="xref">433</xref>
 </sup> Normal microbial colonization in early life can promote tolerance to aeroallergens via induced regulatory T cells.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref434" class="xref">434</xref>
 </sup> The development and composition of the human microbiome are influenced by many factors such as diet, infections, medical treatment, and also environmental factors.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref435" class="xref">435</xref>
 </sup> For example, air pollutants and climatic stress factors may disturb microbial communities through oxidative stress, inflammation, and changes in environmental biodiversity.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> Modifications in the composition of the gastrointestinal and lung microbiome can in turn affect the development of allergies in accordance with the “hygiene hypothesis”
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref436" class="xref">436</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref440" class="xref">440</xref>
 </sup> and may also promote pathogenic species that can contribute to these diseases.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref441" class="xref">441</xref>−
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref443" class="xref">443</xref>
 </sup> Recent studies revealed differences in the structure and composition of microbiota in the lower airways of healthy and asthmatic people: 
 <italic class="italic">Bacteroidetes</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Firmicutes</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Proteobacteria</italic> are the most common phyla found in airways of healthy subjects, whereas increased concentrations of pathogenic Proteobacteria, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Haemophilus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Moraxella</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Neisseria</italic> spp., were found in asthma patients.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref442" class="xref">442</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref443" class="xref">443</xref>
 </sup> Moreover, viral infections can exacerbate allergies.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> It is still unclear, however, if these changes are a cause or a consequence of the disease. Moreover, it has been suggested that air pollutants, especially air particulate matter, ingested together with food can trigger and accelerate the development of gastrointestinal inflammatory diseases by altering the gastrointestinal microbiome and immune functions.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref444" class="xref">444</xref>
 </sup> Besides the human microbiome, also microbes associated with allergenic pollen (pollen microbiome) and other aeroallergens may act as adjuvants when deposited on epithelial surfaces.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref235" class="xref">235</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="ref445" class="xref">445</xref>
 </sup>
</p>
