<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P29" class="p">Among the main strengths of our study is the fact that the analysis was of a globally representative sample of cities and so reflects variation of urban populations with regard to region, city size, and economic development. Its results were also based on an ensemble of 18 global climate models, though here we show only mean values rather than presenting the suite of individual model results to show the diversity of their results. On the other hand, the analysis was of change in (dry bulb) temperatures alone, taking no account humidity, or evidence on the precise form of the distribution of daily temperatures. Moreover, the analyses did not attempt to incorporate the urban heat island (UHI) effect—the name given to the occurrence of higher outdoor temperatures in metropolitan areas compared with those of the surrounding countryside caused by the thermal properties (heat absorption, capacity, conductance, and albedo) of the surfaces and materials found in urban landscapes, the reduced evapotranspiration from reduced natural vegetation, and the waste heat production from anthropogenic activities [
 <xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The UHI effect may add to the more general effect of increasing temperatures, especially in larger cities, though the implications for personal exposure and health are more complex [
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] and surface temperature effects may in part be offset by overshadowing by high rise buildings in urban centres [
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. A further limitation was the relatively coarse resolution of the GCMs, resulting in an inability to distinguish some cities from neighbouring cities and potential biases for coastal cities. However, our focus on changes in temperatures (rather than absolute values) should have minimized these effects.
</p>
