<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and Recommendations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study has developed work by previous researchers and has furthered understanding of dormouse nestbox selection. It indicates that dormice select nestboxes based on a combination of factors. While views on the importance of nestboxes for dormouse conservation differ, many, but not all of the results of this study are likely to be relevant for natural nest selection too. Large scale features, such as distance to the edge of the wood, or combinations of plant species in the nearby vicinity are likely to apply equally to natural nests and nestboxes. Some localised factors may differ, as nestboxes provide shelter that may be absent on thin trees with low structural complexity, which would prevent dormice from building natural nests on these trees. Nevertheless, these results are important in informing conservation management decisions where nestboxes are used, and, in combination with other studies, in understanding the broad principles of dormouse habitat selection in any woodland.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monitoring dormice using volunteers can provide an adequate quantity of analysable data, and useful information can be extracted from data that might usually be considered less reliable compared to rigourous scientific data, as shown in other studies (e.g. [
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>,
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]). Volunteer schemes with large historical datasets are irreplaceable and invaluable as they can produce important ecological information and can help identify important sites and management strategies [
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>,
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. NDMP records vary greatly in quantity and quality between sites and years (S. Sharafi, PTES, pers. comm.), so it would be useful to determine the reasons behind this variation in order to uncover ways in which to reduce it, thus improving the national database. Volunteers should be informed of the importance of completing forms consistently and of collecting regular habitat data, and guidance on this matter should be given to the leaders of monitoring groups. Volunteer schemes would undoubtedly benefit from scientific input to improve data collection, thereby facilitating scientific study of those data and allowing the results to be of maximum usefulness for applied ecology and conservation.
 </p>
</sec>
