<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether actual nestbox occupation data showed significant departures from a random distribution, as expected if nestboxes were actively chosen but not if they were randomly selected, the frequency of dormouse occupation in each nestbox over the 18 years was compared to a hypothetical Poisson distribution. This was done using a Kolmogorov-Smirnov test (as per [
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All percentage variables were converted to proportions and arcsine transformed. Given that the circumference of trees would have increased over the study period, values in this variable were ranked (1 = smallest circumference) rather than using absolute values. The age of coppice, angle of nestbox floor and height of nestbox were not included in the analysis because coppice dates were not known for all sections of the wood, and the height and angle of the nestbox would have changed during the monthly surveys as the volunteers monitored the contents of the nestboxes.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A stepwise regression was used to determine which independent variables were predictors of dormouse nestbox selection, using both forward and backward procedures (the default for the ‘step’ command in the R statistical software package) and Akaike’s Information Criterion (AIC) as a method of model reduction. This allows the optimal (sub) set of predictors to be identified and maximum parsimony to be achieved. This analysis used the percentage of dormouse occupancy over the 18-year period as the dependent variable. Standardised residuals of the final regression were normally distributed, as verified by a Lilliefors test for normality (D = 0.08, p = 0.12) (as per [
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To remove any bias that could have arisen from dormice reselecting nestboxes in which nests remained from one year to another, a stepwise binary logistic regression was run (1 = nestbox containing a nest sometime during the 18-year period; 0 = never occupied by dormice). Note that the number of nestboxes each year remained the same (n = 97). The independent variables of small mammal nests and bird nests were still percentages (as above) because these nests were always cleared out from year to year, thus removing any confounding effects. The logistic regression was more robust to the assumptions of the data than the use of percentage occupancy over 18 years. This conversion to simple presence or absence of a nest in the entire 18 year period also lost valuable information on the preference of nestboxes, i.e. a box occupied once in 18 years was given the same value as a box occupied in most years. Given that our aim was to understand factors influencing nestbox selection, this detail of preference was useful. Similar results from both analyses would strengthen the evidence that significant factors were of biological importance.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To further investigate the relationship between bird nests and dormouse occupancy within years (this was found to be significant in the first stepwise model – see Results), a Spearman’s Rank correlation was run comparing the percentage of dormouse occupancy and bird nests for all nestboxes together over each individual year. Finally, possible competitive effects between dormice and birds were examined between individual nestboxes, in each individual year. The percentage of cases where dormouse and bird nests were found (along with percentage of cases where only bird nests, only dormouse nests, or neither of these, were found) were compared against expected values calculated by the equation:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">p(D|B) = p(B|D) = B * D, </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where the probability of dormice being found when bird nests were present is equal to the probability of bird nests being found when dormice were present at any point during the year (i.e. when no facilitation or competition is occurring), and B is the average percentage of bird nests found in all nestboxes over all years, and D is the average percentage of dormice found in all nestboxes over all years. Differences between expected and observed values were tested with a chi-squared test.</p>
</sec>
