<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">We used ENM analyses to model range dynamics between the LIG, LGM and Present. Raw occurrence records for each of the 11 species (see details in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>), following the taxonomy in the 
 <italic class="italic">Handbook of the Birds of the World (HBW)</italic> series, were compiled from the eBird Basic Dataset (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ebird.org/content/ebird" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ebird.org/content/ebird</ext-link>, accessed Aug 2015) and China Bird Report (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.birdreport.cn" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.birdreport.cn</ext-link>, accessed Aug 2015), and outliers from their known distributions were removed. To avoid spatial autocorrelation, the retained records were then rarefied at a 5-km spatial resolution under a south Asian continent equidistant conic projection in SDMtoolbox 1.1c [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>] (see dataset in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>), roughly equivalent to the resolution of climatic layers (e.g. 2.5 arc-minute resolution). Climate grids for the present and LGM (under the Community Climate System Model) were downloaded from the WorldClim website [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>] (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org</ext-link>) with 2.5 arc-minute resolutions. The LIG model was initially obtained with a 30 arc-second resolution and then resampled to 2.5 arc-minute using a “NEAREST” algorithm using SDMtoolbox. The reasonability of study area extent is crucial for accuracy of ENM analyses and is difficult to determine [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. Given present distributions, we set an enlarged area exceeding the mainland Oriental Region [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>], sufficiency of which was verified by whether or not embracing the species’ distribution changes across historical climate changes.
</p>
