<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">To reduce model overfitting associated with factor autocorrelation, highly correlated (
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> &gt; 0.90) bioclimatic variables were identified and finally 10 variables were reserved, namely Bio_2 (mean diurnal range in temperature), Bio_3 (isothermality, monthly/ annual temperature range), Bio_5 (maximum temperature of warmest month), Bio_7 (temperature annual range), Bio_11 (mean temperature of coldest quarter), Bio_14 (precipitation of driest month), Bio_15 (precipitation seasonality, coefficient variation), Bio_16 (precipitation of wettest quarter), Bio_18 (precipitation of warmest quarter) and Bio_19 (precipitation of coldest quarter). In addition, winter records for species with significant seasonal migration (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">S. semitorques</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">C. fortipes</italic>, see details in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>: Table S1) were excluded from the downstream analyses to improve prediction accuracy. The present-day ENM for each species was created and then extrapolated to palaeoclimatic layers at the LGM and LIG in MAXENT 3.3.3 k [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>]. Model parameters were trained with 75% of the occurrence records randomly sampled for each species and test by the other 25%, except that for species (
 <italic class="italic">F. ruficapilla</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">L. chrysotis</italic>) with fewer occurrence records (e.g. &lt;100) all data were used to train the models (see details in Additional file 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>: Table S3). Two options in MAXENT were applied to reduce model over-prediction, with the maximum training sensitivity plus specificity (MTSS) threshold and the fade-by-clamping (i.e. to mitigate clamping issues during extrapolation among nonanalogous climates) procedure. Model performance was evaluated with the statistics of the area under the receiver operating characteristic curve (AUC).
</p>
