<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Africa is far from self‐sufficient in rice and this situation is projected to worsen in the future (Balasubramanian, Sie, Hijmans, &amp; Otsuka, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Van Ittersum et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Van Oort, Saito et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Keeping up with growing population and per‐capita rice consumption will require substantial yield gap closure and area expansion, or continued import dependency. Projections in these self‐sufficiency studies did not include climate change effects, which are still quite uncertain for rice in Africa. Possible climate change impacts on rice productivity have been simulated previously extensively for Asia (Aggarwal &amp; Mall, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Matthews, Kropff, &amp; Bachelet, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Matthews, Kropff, Horie, &amp; Bachelet, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>; Tao, Hayashi, Zhang, Sakamoto, &amp; Yokozawa, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). These studies suggested that future rice yield declines would be caused mainly by two factors: (i) increased heat induced sterility and (ii) shortening of the growing season. On both factors, significant advances have been made since the seminal works by Matthews in the 1990s. Earlier studies (Dingkuhn, Sow, Samb, Diack, &amp; Asch, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>) and later studies (Gaydon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Van Oort, De Vries, Yoshida, &amp; Saito, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) cast doubt on the general validity of the heat sterility model in the ORYZA000 model version used by (Matthews et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>), suggesting that the original heat sterility model overestimates heat sterility in hot (semi) arid climates. This led to the development of new canopy temperature models and heat sterility models for rice (Julia &amp; Dingkuhn, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Van Oort, Saito, Zwart, &amp; Shrestha, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) and for other crops (Eyshi Rezaei, Webber, Gaiser, Naab, &amp; Ewert, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Webber et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The Julia and Dingkuhn (
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) heat sterility model was incorporated in an improved version of ORYZA2000 (Van Oort, De Vries et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This improved version predicted yields more accurately and with less bias in a hot (semi) arid region in Senegal (Van Oort, De Vries et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This finding is highly relevant for Africa with a large area of irrigated rice cultivated along the Senegal river, the Niger river and the Benue river systems in the hot (semi) arid Sudanian and Sahel zone. This new heat sterility submodel generally predicts lower heat sterility and simulates two adaptive mechanisms of the rice plant to cope with heat: increased transpirational cooling at higher temperatures and earlier flowering (earlier in the morning, when it is cooler) to avoid heat. On the second major cause of future yield decline reported by Matthews et al., shorting of the growing season, significant and relevant advances have been made in rice phenology modelling. The ORYZA000 model version used by Matthews et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>) assumed slower development above the optimum temperature of 30°C, while more recent experimental and modelling work suggests no delay in development rate above the optimum temperature (Van Oort, Zhang, De Vries, Heinemann, &amp; Meinke, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Zhang, Li, Yang, &amp; Simelton, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Zhang, Zhu, &amp; Yang, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Newer phenology models predict a stronger shortening of the growing season in the hotter climates and therefore more negative effects of climate change. These scientific developments on heat sterility modelling and phenology modelling call for new climate change studies with an improved crop growth model.
</p>
