<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Decreasing temperatures, especially winter temperatures, dominated the trend of climate change from the LIG to the LGM. As expected, the marked decrease in winter temperature caused min temperature of coldest month (MTCM) to be the main limiting factor accounting for the northern contraction of 
 <italic class="italic">P. amabilis</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">Fig. 4A</xref>), which is a thermophilic tree according to its physiological tolerance of MTCM (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-5" class="xref">Fig. S5</xref>). Low temperatures affect the survival of plants by impacting their transition from vegetative to reproductive development (
 <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gallagher, 1986</xref>) as well as their assimilation of soil water and nutrients for cell division, differentiation and tissue growth (
 <xref rid="ref-108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thuiller et al., 2005</xref>). Extremely cold winters can even result in frost kill (
 <xref rid="ref-88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pearson et al., 2002</xref>). Therefore, the significance of minimum temperatures in determining the world distributions of species, especially the northern boundary of their ranges, has been long recognized (
 <xref rid="ref-97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raison et al., 1979</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Woodward, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ashcroft, Chisholm &amp; French, 2008</xref>). Moreover, a recent evaluation via ENMs of environmental factors affecting species distributions indicated that winter minimum temperature contributes the most to model predictions (
 <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ashcroft, French &amp; Chisholm, 2011</xref>). In contrast, temperature seasonality (TS) and annual precipitation (AP) were important factors for the observed southern contraction of 
 <italic class="italic">P. amabilis</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">Fig. 4A</xref>). Notably, the change in TS was a main factor leading to the expansion in the Sichuan Basin (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" class="xref">Fig. 4A</xref>). The contrasting role played by the same climate variable against the same climate background may result from heterogeneity among regional climate conditions and differences in the variation of climate variables.
</p>
