<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health concerns</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change is broadly defined as a change in the distribution of weather patterns when that change lasts for an extended period of time such as decades to millions of years. Referred to as “global warming”, climate change basically means the extreme weather events. The scientific consensus is that climate is changing and that these changes are in large part caused by human activities and are largely irreversible. The primary contributor to climate change is the dramatic increase in fossil fuel emissions since the industrial revolution, contributed historically by the industrialised countries such as US, and Europe.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change affects health directly and indirectly. The rise in temperature and heat waves can lead to increased incidence of heat stroke and to melting of glaciers, resulting thereby to formation of glacial lakes. Bursting of these lakes and flooding downstream can spell disaster of unprecedented scale including death, injury and devastation, for the people living in Himalayan and sub-Himalayan region. The sea level rise on the other hand, is a matter of concern to island nations such as Maldives and Republic of Kiribati as well as to coastal regions of Bangladesh and India
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">4</a>. Climate change can also cause intensive drought conditions leading to crop failures, compromise food security, and contribute to malnutrition. Populations displaced or forced to migrate undergo stress, trauma and mental disorders. Air pollution associated with climate change is a major risk factor for increase in asthma and respiratory problems especially among children in urban areas
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">5</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The changes in physical and biological conditions, and ecosystem associated with climate change create an environment conducive for transmission of diseases, in particular diarrhoeal diseases, vector-borne diseases and animal-associated diseases. For example, increasing temperatures may provide opportunities for disease vectors to change their geographic range or to replicate faster, or survive for longer periods of time, leading thereby to increased disease transmission or their emergence in newer areas, placing more people at risk of malaria and other vector-borne diseases
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">6</a>. Dengue and chikungunya are, therefore, expected not only to expand geographically but occur in explosive outbreaks. The supercyclone in Odisha (1999)
  <a rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref7">7</a> and floods in Mumbai (2005)
  <a rid="ref8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref8">8</a> were followed by outbreaks of leptospirosis. The 1994 plague outbreak in Surat was preceded by intense heat wave followed by heavy rainfall
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">9</a>. Similarly, rise in sea surface temperature has been shown to increase proliferation of cholera bacilli followed by cholera outbreaks
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>. Climate change due to El Niño can lead to increase in hospital admissions for diarrhoeal diseases
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emergence and re-emergence of these climate sensitive diseases and their further spread are, therefore, an unprecedented challenge to public health. Many public health leaders and advocates including the Director-General of the World Health Organisation acknowledge that climate change is the defining public health issue in the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century that needs to be tackled without any delay
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extent to which health impacts occur will depend on many factors including the risk and vulnerability of the populations and the institutional capacity to detect emerging diseases early and respond rapidly. Geographically, populations most at risk are the rural poor, or those living in big cities, mountain areas such as foothills of Himalayas, and in water-stressed coastal areas. Paradoxically, these are also the populations least able to cope with the health effects. According to the UNICEF, as many as two billion children in the world are at risk of climate change
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a> and it will push more than 100 million into poverty over the next 15 years. And the poorest regions of the world - Sub-Saharan Africa and South Asia - will be hit the hardest
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
