<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of drought on livestock production</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drought knows no size of farming; it affects both smallholder and large-scale farming. This was confirmed by Swart in 2016 who presented in the AGRA (Agricultural forum consisting of role players called to discuss drought situation) dialogue on drought, who reported that all categories of farmers were affected by climate change. There was not sufficient fodder for their livestock within the commercial farming sector, and livestock were given potato seedlings to graze on because they were not being sold because of the drought (Swart 
  <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2016</a>). While it is argued that climate change is causing havoc in livestock, Rust and Rust (
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>) observed that some of the problems in livestock cooperatives were caused by conflicts resulting from poor leadership or the development of opportunistic ideas by individual members of the cooperatives. It is important that leadership should take advantage when policies are pronounced to help the farmers. Experience showed that selfishness does not help. Farmers need to be organised to fight the scourge of drought as a team rather than by competing with each other.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change will affect animal production in different ways. Rust and Rust (
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>) identified four ways: changes in livestock feed, grain availability and price challenges, the impact on livestock pastures and forage crop production and quality of feed changes in livestock diseases and pests, and the direct effects of extreme weather events on animal health, growth and reproduction. Furthermore, the indirect effects of climate-driven change in animal production may result mainly from alterations in the nutritional environment. Research indicates that changes in climate, to a large extent, will affect the quality and quantity of forage (Topp &amp; Doyle 
  <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">1996</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of climate change may result in the deterioration of pasture, towards lesser quality, which, in turn, will affect the quality of animals; hence, the meat quality will also be affected. Sometimes the quality of meat may be affected by infected feed that the animals eat (Rust &amp; Rust 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>). Changes in temperature and rainfall may result in the spread of disease and parasites creeping into new regions, or an increase in the incidence of pests and diseases. Pests and diseases reduce animal productivity and increase animal mortality (Baker &amp; Viglizzo 
  <a rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0004">1998</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other changes include heat stress which, according to Fuquay (
  <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">1981</a>), has various detrimental effects on livestock. In the dairy herd, climate change will result in a decrease in fodder production from dry land and irrigated pastures, resulting in the rise in feed costs (Rust &amp; Rust 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As far as monogastric animals are concerned, they emit gases that if not managed will go into the atmosphere and destroy the layer that protects the intense heat from destroying the environment and human beings. Poultry meat and egg production are the most efficient animal protein production systems (Rust &amp; Rust 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>). Poultry meat production is the most environmentally efficient (smallest carbon footprint per unit product produced), followed by pork and mutton (primarily lamb) with beef the least efficient (Williams, Audsley &amp; Sandars 
  <a rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0036">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the emissions can be reduced by using various housing techniques that have been developed to reduce emissions. A combination of housing and feeding measures seems most promising to achieve a substantial reduction in emissions at a relatively low cost (Van der Peet-Schwering et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0027">1999</a>). As far as the Western Cape is concerned, livestock farmers are among the hardest hit by the drought. An estimated 30 000 cattle have been sold as farmers were unable to feed their herds. The impacts of the drought in the summer rainfall region on beef cattle herds, with high numbers of animals slaughtered, have been reported (Government of Western Cape 2017).
 </p>
</sec>
