<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction and background</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is considered to be one of the biggest challenges that communities are facing locally and internationally (IPCC 2006). The reason why climate change is interpreted as a crisis is that it affects the very sources of human livelihood that are agriculture and the environment. Any disturbance in either agriculture or the environment affects the sources of livelihood of communities. Agriculture plays a major role in food production that feeds nations. The estimated population growth of 1.5 billion in the sub-Saharan countries will expect agriculture to feed them by 2050 (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0013">2007</a>). The projected situation of sub-Saharan countries is that they will experience challenges of climate change (Cohen et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0006">2008</a>). However, the situation has changed, with extreme heat especially in the subtropics and changes in the rainfall pattern (Serdeczny et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0023">2015</a>). Evidence suggests that the climate change is already affecting the sub-Saharan countries. In a study documented by 350 Africa.org (
  <a rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0001">n.d</a>.), it showed eight ways in which the impact of climate change affects Africa and the sub-Saharan countries. It was confirmed that livestock such as goats and sheep were dying because of a lack of grazing, and water sources were drying up, causing a serious conflict among the users. The impact of climate change also affects South Africa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Benhin (
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2006</a>) asserted that as far as agriculture in South Africa is concerned, it is a highly sophisticated and successful sector that is made up of medium- to large-scale farms. These farms are commercially oriented, capital intensive and generally produce a surplus, which account for 90% of the value added and cover 86% of the agricultural land (NDA 
  <a rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0020">2000</a>). The availability of water has become the most limiting factor when it comes to agricultural production in South Africa, especially when one considers rainfall pattern because rainfall is unevenly distributed across the country. According to DWAF (
  <a rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0010">2004</a>), South Africa receives an annual rainfall of 450 mm, which is low when compared with the world’s average of 860 mm, and it has high levels of evaporation; on the contrary, South Africa has only 10% of its area that receives more than 750 mm, of which 50% is used for agriculture.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Western Cape is one of the nine provinces of South Africa. It lies in the Mediterranean climate zone receiving winter rainfall as opposed to the rest of the provinces. It is located on the southern tip of the African continent between the Indian and Atlantic oceans. It is bordered by the Northern Cape and Eastern Cape provinces; the region is topographic and climatically diverse (Western Cape Municipalities 
  <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">2017</a>). The Western Cape covers an area of 129 462 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. It is the fourth largest province in South Africa by surface area and also ranks fourth in population. The Western Cape is rich in agriculture and fisheries. It is an ideal place for grape cultivation. Other fruits and vegetables are also grown here. The province is divided into one metropolitan municipality, five district municipalities, and 24 local municipalities (Western Cape Municipalities 
  <a rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0035">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agriculture plays an important role by providing food and earning foreign currency (Hoffman &amp; Harrison 
  <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">n.d.</a>). According to Pienaar (
  <a rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0021">2017</a>), the Western Cape is one of the provinces which export agricultural products to both other provinces and other countries in the world; different industries such as the deciduous fruit, wine and citrus are found in the Western Cape, which contribute significantly to the overall agri-economy of South Africa. It contributes 2% of the gross domestic product (GDP). Apart from crops, the Western Cape has livestock. It is estimated that the Western Cape contributes 24% of the GDP in South Africa. The total contribution of agriculture to the GDP of the Western Cape is around 4% (Hoffman &amp; Harrison 
  <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">n.d.</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What motivated this study was the fact that the Western Cape used to supply the other provinces with fodder; however, the situation started to change in 2014 and 2015. The water situation started to deteriorate, leading to negative performance and strict measures of controlling irrigation water. The Western Cape Department of Agriculture organised annual symposiums and speaker after speaker spoke about the need to contain the drought by capacitating the extension advisory services.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The author being one of the speakers in one of the annual symposia noticed that the adverse effect of climate change on agriculture would have severe implications in ensuring food for the region. According to Benhin (
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2006</a>), South Africa and the Western Cape contribute 50% of maize as the staple diet of the South African Development Community (SADC). The author undertook this study to establish what impact the 3-year drought has had on to the primary agriculture. Of greater interest was the fact that when the inland provinces, such as Limpopo, were affected by drought in 1981–1984 and subsequent years (Maponya &amp; Mpandeli 
  <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">2016</a>), the Western Cape was the life blood of the nation, as it would supply livestock products, food and fruits to the rest of the provinces. However, with the changes in climate, the Western Cape Province has experienced severe drought since 2015. It is the only province that enjoys a Mediterranean climate; therefore, it was imperative for the writer to explore their strategies in dealing with their primary agriculture in the wake of climate change in order to provide lessons that could be adapted for other provinces in South Africa.
 </p>
</sec>
