<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation for livestock production</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is understood that mitigation is associated with reducing risk of loss from the occurrence of any undesirable event. In general, mitigation means to minimise the degree of any loss or harm (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/mitigation" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/mitigation</span>). According to the response policy on climate change, mitigation factors imply that steps have to be taken to lessen the impact of climate change (Davies 
  <a rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0008">2014</a>; Western Cape Department of Agriculture 
  <a rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0030">2014</a>). The Western Cape’s response strategy is a two-pronged process consisting of mitigation and adaptation. In terms of mitigation, it aims at making some contribution to national and global efforts to significantly reduce greenhouse gas emissions and build a sustainable low carbon economy in the Western Cape, while simultaneously addressing the need for economic growth, job creation and improving socio-economic conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second strategy, namely adaptation, aims to reduce climate vulnerability and develop the adaptive capacity of the Western Cape’s economy, its people, its ecosystems and its critical infrastructure in a manner that simultaneously addresses the province’s socioeconomic and environmental goals. Beef and dairy cattle can contribute to climate change through the greenhouse gasses they emit. On the contrary, beef and dairy cattle are tolerant to heat stress (Rust &amp; Rust 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, in the case of dairy and monogastric animals, the following need to be considered: lowering the concentrations of urea and ammonia in the slurry; lowering the temperature of the slurry; reducing the emitting surface area; and reducing the pH of the slurry (Rust &amp; Rust 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2013</a>). It is important that we need to be seen taking steps to deal with climate change and not to promote it but to adopt mitigation steps. The Western Cape will need to work and ensure that natural resources are well managed to reduce climate vulnerability. The other area to work on would be to improve resilience and coping capacity within the various communities that are also vulnerable. The other step would be to actively adapt some of the practices to climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
