<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To maintain consistency with the total (wet plus dry) N deposition estimates used to develop the Thomas et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) growth and survival relationships, all three deposition scenarios in this current study used the 800‐m grid resolution 2000–2004 average National Atmospheric Deposition Program (NADP) wet deposition and the Clean Air Status and Trends Network (CASTNet) dry deposition data set used by Thomas et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) as the “base” deposition data set. Capturing variation in N deposition within each 800‐m grid, for example, due to variation in elevation, is beyond the scope of this study. Dry deposition estimates from CASTNet are known to be lower than more contemporary deposition estimates such as those from Community Multiscale Air Quality (CMAQ; Bash et al. 
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) or total deposition (TDEP; Schwede and Lear 
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Therefore, to prevent the over or under estimation of tree growth and survival responses the three deposition scenarios in this current study were determined by percent change scaling factors applied to the Thomas et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) “baseline” deposition. Fig. 
 <xref rid="ecm1345-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> presents N deposition from 2005–2100 according to the three deposition scenarios summarized across the study area. The Constant deposition scenario consisted of the 2000–2004 average baseline deposition rate from Thomas et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) repeated for each year from 2005–2100, representing a period when deposition has declined from peak levels in the 1980s and 1990s, but remained 16.5 times higher than pre‐European settlement levels over the study area. A map of baseline N deposition levels (in 2005) is shown in Appendix 
 <xref rid="ecm1345-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>: Fig. S1. The CAA2025 and Return to PE deposition scenarios both started from this same baseline deposition rate (in 2002 for consistency with the CAA2025 deposition data sets), but then declined until 2025 and remained constant until 2100. The 2025 target year was selected for consistency with the time frame of the CAA2025 deposition estimates.
</p>
