<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In LHT, behaviour is guided by the costs and benefits of investing energy into ‘competing’ life functions of growth, development, maintenance, repair (i.e. somatic or embodied effort) and reproduction [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. As resources invested into one life function cannot be devoted to another, a set of trade-offs arises [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The trade-off between current and future reproduction underlies 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>- and 
 <italic class="italic">K-</italic>strategies [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">K-</italic>strategies are typified by protracted periods of investment in somatic effort and delayed onset and pace of reproduction, which allow individuals to produce relatively few ‘high-quality’ offspring. In the context of high-income and industrialized countries, the pursuit of 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>-strategies results in large 
 <italic class="italic">per capita</italic> emissions per offspring. By contrast, 
 <italic class="italic">r-</italic>strategies include earlier and more frequent reproduction, and reduced per child investments [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], and so should be associated with smaller emissions 
 <italic class="italic">per capita</italic>. In sum, our use of 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic> captures some of the density-dependent dynamics of early models [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] and more generally refers to later LH paradigms [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Unlike 
 <italic class="italic">K-</italic>selection as originally conceived for density-dependent regimes as populations reach equilibrium, which globally humanity does not yet exhibit [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], we assume focus on 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic> is also relevant to human adaptation when equilibrium assumptions are relaxed. Generally, attention to non-equilibrium dynamics appears to be a promising avenue for human evolutionary and social ecology [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
