<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SM-P feedback is crucial for climate studies. Positive feedback has been widely noted in previous studies, while negative feedback has been given less attention. In this study, we identified the sign of the feedback based on satellite remote sensing and ground observation data sets. Then, we investigated the physical mechanism of the feedback through Koster’s framework. Methodologically, the feedback is represented by the correlation between monthly soil moisture and next-month precipitation. Although the index is simple, the correlation coefficient (r) helps to capture the causal relationship. Through Koster’s framework, the physical mechanism of SM-P feedback was identified based on the interactions between soil moisture, evapotranspiration and precipitation.</p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results demonstrate that both positive and negative SM-P feedbacks occur simultaneously over land. Specifically, positive feedback mainly occurs in transitional regions, while negative feedback occurs in extreme dry and wet regions. Negative SM-P feedback mainly depends on the SM-E correlation. We further reveal that negative SM-E correlation is mainly attributed to decreasing soil moisture in arid regions and increasing evapotranspiration in wet regions. Our results have profound meaning for global water research. For example, the negative SM-P feedback in humid regions reflects the increased risk of drought in wet areas, which has been confirmed in several previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. The hotspots presented in our study allow researchers and decision makers to devote more attention to high-risk regions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results demonstrate that the SM-E correlation is the dominant factor for the sign of SM-P feedback. Therefore, comprehending the variability in the SM-E correlation is critical for understanding the physical mechanism of SM-P feedback. However, the effect of soil moisture on evapotranspiration varies with the environment and climate, leading to significant uncertainty regarding evapotranspiration estimation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Therefore, the response of the SM-P correlation to global change should be fully investigated. Climate change has intensified the global water cycle in recent decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, which has unavoidably altered SM-P feedback. Thus, the relationship between the water cycle and SM-P feedback must be taken into consideration in future studies.
 </p>
</sec>
