<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials</div>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global water cycle has intensified in recent decades. We select data from 1982–2011 to capture global water and climate change. Data sets of satellite remote sensing and ground observations are used to investigate the SM-P feedback in this study. Global soil moisture data from the Climate Change Initiative (CCI) and global precipitation data from the Global Precipitation Climatology Centre (GPCC) are adopted to identify the feedback. The evapotranspiration data from FLUXNET and near-surface temperature from the University of Delaware Air Temperature &amp; Precipitation data set are used to estimate the physical mechanism and the climate conditions associated with the feedback. To analyze the spatial patterns, we evaluate the feedback in different climate zones. The zones are defined using the updated classification of Koppen-Geiger
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span> and then classified as humid, arid or transitional zones
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. The data sets are introduced as follows.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil moisture data</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Satellite remote sensing provides global soil moisture information over a large spatial view. CCI provides the longest time series of global satellite soil moisture from 1979–2013, which is used in this study. The data are combined by active and passive microwave satellite observations. The active data sets are generated by the University of Vienna and are based on observations from the C-band scatterometer of the European Remote Sensing satellites (ERS-1 and ERS-2) and the Meteorological Operational Satellite (MetOp-A). The passive data sets are based on observations from the Scanning Multichannel Microwave Radiometer (SMMR), the Special Sensor Microwave/Imager (SSM/I), the Tropical Rainfall Measuring Mission microwave imager (TRMM TMI) and the Advanced Microwave Scanning Radiometer-Earth Observing System (AMSR-E). The accuracy of the CCI data is acceptable when validated using global ground-based observations, and the mean correlation coefficient (
   <span class="italic">r</span>) and root mean square error (RMSE) are 0.46 and 0.04 cm
   <span class="sup">3</span>/cm
   <span class="sup">−3</span>, respectively
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Precipitation data</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GPCC precipitation data are used in this study and were obtained from the Deutscher Wetterdienst of Germany’s National Meteorological Service. The data include precipitation climatology for global land areas based on objective analyses of climatological norms, and the database includes information from approximately 67,200 rain gauge stations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span>. The relative sampling error of gridded monthly precipitation ranges from ± 7–40% of the true mean. The Full Data Reanalysis V.7 (1901–2013) data set is adopted in this study. The spatial resolution was resampled to 25 km to match the soil moisture data used in this study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evapotranspiration data</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evapotranspiration data are adopted to investigate the mechanism of SM-P feedback. The data are calculated from FLUXNET eddy covariance-based latent heat and then upscaled to the global scale
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>. Validation results showed that the RMSE of latent heat is approximately 0.7
   <span class="italic">MJ</span>/
   <span class="italic">m</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>/
   <span class="italic">day</span>, and the correlation coefficient 
   <span class="italic">r</span> is approximately 0.9. The data were obtained from (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.bgc-jena.mpg.de/geodb/projects/FileDetails.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.bgc-jena.mpg.de/geodb/projects/FileDetails.php</span>). We then transform the latent heat (
   <span class="italic">LE</span>) to evapotranspiration (
   <span class="italic">ET</span>) by the relationship 
   <div id="IEq1" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$LE=\lambda \cdot ET$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" class="math">
      <span class="mi">L</span>
      <span class="mi">E</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mi">λ</span>
      <span class="mo">⋅</span>
      <span class="mi">E</span>
      <span class="mi">T</span>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41598_2018_22394_Article_IEq1.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> (where 
   <div id="IEq2" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\lambda =2.45MJ/kg$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M4" class="math">
      <span class="mi">λ</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">2.45</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">M</span>
        <span class="mi">J</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">/</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">k</span>
        <span class="mi">g</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41598_2018_22394_Article_IEq2.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> is the latent heat of vaporization).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global surface temperature data are used to understand the climate condition of the SM-P feedback. The University of Delaware Air Temperature &amp; Precipitation data are used in this study (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/gridded/</span>). To investigate the spatial pattern of the feedback, the climate zones are classified based on the work of Koppen-Geiger. The classification defines the zones based on a combination of precipitation and air temperature. Peel 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span> updated the classification based on long-term monthly data sets of precipitation and temperature. Polar regions cover large areas of ice and snow, which are excluded from our study. Meanwhile, we re-classify arid regions as defined by Peel 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>. Humid regions are zones without a dry season, and transitional regions are the final type of climate zone
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>. The three climate regions (arid, humid and transitional) cover 30.39%, 42.83% and 26.78% of the global land area, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
