<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General pattern of SM-P feedback</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial variability in hydrological variables (soil moisture, precipitation and evapotranspiration) results in significant complexity regarding SM-P feedback. Global average statistics, although useful, result in overestimation in some regions and underestimation in others. Since SM-P feedback is a local process
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, we evaluate the feedback in at the pixel scale spatially. The correlation analysis shows that significant SM-P feedback occurs in 47.10% of the total land area (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). As expected, a positive correlation dominates the feedback. However, non-negligible negative feedback also exists in some areas. Statistically, 87.09% of the feedback is positive, and 12.91% is negative. Spatially, the positive feedback is mainly located in central and southern Africa and southwestern and northern Asia. By contrast, the hotspots of negative feedback are located in southern South America, northern Africa, western Europe, and eastern Asia.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The correlation between monthly soil moisture and next-month precipitation (only significant results are presented at p &lt; 0.05) (Created by ArcGIS, version 10.1, 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esri.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esri.com/</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_22394_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e551" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SM-P feedback is strongly correlated with the environment and climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Thus, we estimate the spatial patterns of feedback in different soils and climate zones. As shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4(a)</a>, positive feedback occurs in transitional soils (0.05 &lt; 
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">v</span>
  </sub> &lt; 0.40 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>/cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>), while negative feedbacks occur in extreme dry (
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">v</span>
  </sub> &lt; 0.05 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>/cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>) and wet (
  <span class="italic">θ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">v</span>
  </sub> &lt; 0.40 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>/cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>) soils. At the climate zone scale (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4(b)</a>), 27.73%, 37.49% and 34.78% of the positive feedbacks occur in arid, humid and transitional zones, respectively, and cover 45.16%, 43.31% and 65.43% area of each climate zone. The negative feedbacks are mainly located in arid and humid zones, which account for 43.75% and 40.16% of all negative feedback, respectively, and cover 10.73% and 6.99% of the climate zones. Previous studies have provided numerous examples of positive SM-P feedback in transitional zones
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. The results of this study demonstrate that negative feedback can occur in dry and wet regions, which could clarify the climate conditions associated with the feedback sign.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The spatial pattern of SM-P feedback over different soils: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) The average correlation with a soil moisture interval of 0.0005 cm
     <span class="sup">3</span>/cm
     <span class="sup">3</span>; (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Negative feedback in different climate zones. The first letter (A to D) refers to the broad climate type: tropical, arid, temperate or cold. The second letter (f, m, w/W and s/S) represents the subsequent precipitation conditions. The third letter (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">d</span>,
     <span class="bold">h</span> and 
     <span class="bold">k</span>) refers to the temperature classification. The definitions of the climate zones can be found in Peel 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
     </span>. Each pixel represents an area of 0.25 × 0.25 degrees.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_22394_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e667" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Koster’s framework is then used to explore the physical mechanism of SM-P feedback. According to the framework, one or three negative correlations of P-E, SM-E and E-P would result in negative SM-P feedback, and positive P-SM correlation has been observed in previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. It is also upstream of the SM-P feedback loop. Therefore, only the SM-E and E-P correlations are adopted to estimate the physical mechanism of SM-P feedback (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). The positive and negative SM-E correlations cover 50.77% and 24.74% of the total land area (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5(a)</a>). Seneviratne 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> presented probable reasons for the complex SM-E correlation. In transitional climate zones, evapotranspiration exhibits an approximately linear relationship with soil moisture. However, the correlation is weakened in dry soil because of high soil suction (soil moisture limited) and in wet soil because of potential evapotranspiration (energy limited). Spatially, the negative SM-E correlation covers 72.81% area of the negative SM-P feedback, which is concentrated in southern North America, northern South America and western Asia. According to Koster’s framework, the spatial inconsistence between the SM-E and E-P correlations generates the negative SM-P feedback. Since the positive E-P correlation is observed over land (84.38% of the total land area) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5(b)</a>), the negative SM-E correlation might be the dominant force associated with negative SM-P feedback.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Correlations of (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) SM-E and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) E-P (only significant results are presented at p &lt; 0.05) (Created by ArcGIS, version 10.1, 
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esri.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esri.com/</span>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_22394_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e713" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
