<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35145-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capturing buffalo and tracking movement</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In June/July and October of 2008, we captured 200 female buffalo, 100 each from two sections in the southern KNP: LS and CB. Age ranges in this dataset at first capture varied from 17 to 156 months of age (
  <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
   <div class="mover">
    <span class="mi">x</span>
    <span class="mo">-</span>
   </div>
  </div> = 48 months; 
  <span class="italic">σ</span> = 23.2) in the LS herd, and from 21 to 168 months (
  <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
   <div class="mover">
    <span class="mi">x</span>
    <span class="mo">-</span>
   </div>
  </div> = 54 months; 
  <span class="italic">σ</span> = 24.6) for the CB herds. Sinclair (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0080">1977</a>) classed African buffalo age classes as follows: calves (&lt;1 year), two‐year olds (2–3 years of age), subadults (3–5 years of age), and adults (&gt;5 years of age). Mean age of calving in the Serengeti is 4.8 years of age, although individuals as young as 3.5 years have been recorded calving (Sinclair, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0080">1977</a>). Captures were conducted from helicopters with a dart gun using a combination of etorphine hydrochloride, azaperone, and ketamine. Effects of the opioids on immobilized buffalo were reversed using a combination of naltrexone and diprenorphine. Buffalo were fitted with either a GPS (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 7) or a VHF collar (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 193) as part of a study investigating bovine tuberculosis and gastrointestinal helminth (GI) interactions (Table 
  <a rid="ece35145-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#ece35145-tbl-0002">2</a>). As part of this study, 100 randomly selected animals (50 from each section) received a long‐acting anthelmintic bolus (Panacur bolus (Intervet, UK)).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We recaptured all buffalo biannually. The timing of the initial captures allowed us to alternate between the two areas twice per year. All LS animals came from one large buffalo herd, while CB buffalo were distributed among two main herds, the Mountain and Power Line herds (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35145-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35145-fig-0001">1</a>). Any animals that died throughout the study period were replaced with similar‐aged animals from the same herd. Captures were conducted using the same immobilization method as the initial captures, except that buffalo were darted from the ground using 4 x 4 vehicles. Satellite collars provided 2 locations daily (06:00 and 18:00 local time) to establish the general location of each buffalo herd. Once a herd was located, we verified presence/absence of collared individuals and recorded date, time, and GPS location. All VHF collar frequencies for the entire study area were checked in each herd to detect individuals that dispersed between herds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Buffalo in the LS herd were monitored throughout the duration of the project. However, with the CB herds (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35145-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35145-fig-0001">1</a>) this was not always possible due to a greater distance from our base location at Skukuza and terrain that was difficult to navigate during the wet season. Thus, sample distribution for collar locations in the LS herd was more even throughout the year than sample distribution for the CB herds (Supporting information Figure 
  <a rid="ece35145-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece35145-sup-0001">S2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Eleven collared buffalo left the confines of KNP; when possible, those individuals were recaptured, brought back into KNP, and placed in the herd closest to the point of exit. When individuals left KNP to unfenced adjoining private reserves, relocation was not possible, so collars were removed. If buffalo crossed the fence on KNP's eastern boundary into the part of Mozambique, collars could not be retrieved.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LS herd contained satellite collars throughout the entire duration of the project (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 4, with 1 replaced in November 2009 due to predation), but lost 2 to dispersal to different herds during the course of the study. The CB herd had 3 satellite collars throughout the project (Mountain herd, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 2; Power Line herd, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1).
 </p>
</sec>
