<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35145-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dispersal is an essential life‐history trait in animals, which functions as a mechanism for avoiding inbreeding and finding usable habitats (Bowler &amp; Benton, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0015">2005</a>; Clobert, Danchin, Dhondt, &amp; Nichols, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0022">2001</a>; Kokko &amp; López‐Supulcre, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0057">2006</a>). Most studies of dispersal have explored natal dispersal, which is typically a permanent movement of juveniles, prior to their first mating, away from their natal area (Greenwood, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0042">1980</a>). Natal dispersal is typically restricted to one sex within a particular species, for example, male red‐backed salamanders (
  <span class="italic">Plethedon cinereus</span>) (Liebgold, Brodie, &amp; Cabe, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0060">2011</a>), and female Siberian flying squirrels (Hanski &amp; Selonen, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0047">2009</a>); however, an equal proportion of male and female European roe deer (
  <span class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</span>) nataly disperse (Gaillard et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0036">2008</a>). For some long‐lived species, adults of either sex may make permanent or long‐term movements to different populations, habitat patches, or herds, for example, desert bighorn sheep (
  <span class="italic">Ovis canadensis nelsoni</span>) (Epps, Wehausen, Bleich, Torres, &amp; Brashares, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0030">2007</a>), bison (
  <span class="italic">Bison bison</span>) (Plumb, White, Coughenour, &amp; Wallen, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0070">2009</a>), and mountain caribou (
  <span class="italic">Rangifer tarandus caribou</span>) (van Oort, McLellan, &amp; Serrouya, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0083">2011</a>). Adult dispersal like natal dispersal is typically sexually biased, with female‐biased dispersal more common in bird species, and male‐biased dispersal more common in mammals (Clobert et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0022">2001</a>; Greenwood, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0042">1980</a>). Both natal and adult dispersal are considered important in management and conservation of wild populations as they allow for recolonization of empty habitat patches (Abbott, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0001">2011</a>; Epps, Wehausen, Palsbøll, &amp; McCullough, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0031">2010</a>), demographic rescue (Forester, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0035">2011</a>; van Oort et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0083">2011</a>), and maintenance of genetic diversity through gene flow (Bowler &amp; Benton, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0015">2005</a>; Clark, Brown, Stechert, &amp; Zamudio, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0021">2010</a>; Epps et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0029">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adult dispersal is poorly understood compared to natal dispersal, but in some cases may vary widely at the individual level compared to species with strong natal dispersal behaviors. Factors hypothesized to drive adult dispersal include density dependence, often manifesting as a lack of food, interspecific interactions, relatedness of potential mates in the current home range (Bowler &amp; Benton, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0015">2005</a>), or potential for improving social status (Clutton‐Brock &amp; Lukas, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0023">2012</a>). In moose, high population density and resource limitation are correlated with higher adult dispersal rates (Labonté, Ouellet, Courtois, &amp; Bélisle, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0058">1998</a>). Similarly, dispersal of bison in Yellowstone National Park is density dependent and more common as bison populations reach carrying capacity (Plumb et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0070">2009</a>), a trend also seen in the fast‐growing population of wood bison in northern Canada (Gates &amp; Larter, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0037">1990</a>; Larter, Sinclair, Ellsworth, Nishi, &amp; Gates, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0059">2000</a>). Thus, changes in animal condition may be a trigger for such movements (Bonte &amp; De La Peña, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0011">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Infectious diseases have been hypothesized as a potential influence on dispersal behavior in animals (Boulinier, McCoy, &amp; Sorci, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0014">2001</a>), through direct impacts on animal behavior (Bowler &amp; Benton, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0015">2005</a>) or indirectly by affecting body condition (Armsworth, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0003">2009</a>; Belthoff &amp; Dufty, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0009">1998</a>; Debeffe et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0025">2012</a>). For example, body mass of European roe deer is correlated with dispersal likelihood and dispersal distance, with individuals with a body mass less than 14 kg not dispersing and distance dispersed increasing with body mass (Debeffe et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0025">2012</a>). In the same population of European roe deer, dispersal propensity decreases with nematode parasite burden, which is associated with a decrease in body mass (Debeffe et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0026">2014</a>). Heeb et al. (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0048">1999</a>) observed a similar pattern in the great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), where male fledglings from nests infested with hen fleas (
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus gallinae)</span> were likely to disperse shorter distances than fledglings from uninfested nests. However, Brown and Brown (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0016">1992</a>) found that higher hematophagous flea (
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus celsus</span>) and swallow bug (
  <span class="italic">Oeciacus vicarious</span>) burdens led to natal dispersal in American cliff swallows (
  <span class="italic">Petrochelidon pyrrhonota</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">African buffalo offer a unique opportunity to examine the influences of extrinsic and intrinsic factors, including infectious diseases, on adult dispersal. Buffalo are long‐lived, wide‐ranging, and gregarious, with adult dispersal observed in both sexes (Olff, Ritchie, &amp; Prins, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0068">2002</a>). African buffalo have the weakest genetic structure of all African ungulates studied to date (Lorenzen, Arctander, &amp; Siegismund, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0062">2008</a>) and significant differentiation only at the continental scale (Simonsen, Siegismund, &amp; Arctander, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0079">1998</a>), suggesting that buffalo are less philopatric than other African ungulates (Metzger, Sinclair, Hilborn, Hopcraft, &amp; Mduma, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0064">2010</a>). However, as populations are increasingly restricted by loss of habitat, habitat fragmentation, and human‐made barriers, gene flow among some populations may be decreasing (Epps et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0028">2013</a>; Heller, Okello, &amp; Siegismund, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0049">2010</a>), and thus, dispersal, gene flow, and connectivity have become conservation priorities for buffalo management (van Hooft, Groen, &amp; Prins, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0082">2003</a>; Simonsen et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0079">1998</a>). Moreover, infectious disease and possible interactions with dispersal are particularly important for this species given the potential for disease interactions with livestock and resulting human‐wildlife conflict. Macroparasites, such as bovine tuberculosis and brucellosis may influence individual condition (Caron, Cross, &amp; du Toit, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0020">2003</a>; Gorsich, Ezenwa, Cross, Bengis, &amp; Jolles, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0040">2015</a>), leading to indirect effects on dispersal behavior. Moreover, African buffalo carry diseases that are of economic concern such as bovine tuberculosis (Renwick, White, &amp; Bengis, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0075">2007</a>), brucellosis (Gorsich, Ezenwa, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0040">2015</a>), and foot‐and‐mouth disease (Dion, Van Schalkwyk, &amp; Lambin, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0027">2011</a>). Thus understanding buffalo ranging behavior (Ryan, Knechtel, &amp; Getz, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0077">2006</a>) can help to inform management decision regarding their potential to cause spillover of disease into both wildlife populations (Bastos, Boshoff, Keet, Bengis, &amp; Thompson, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0005">2000</a>), domestic livestock (Michel et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0065">2006</a>) and people in the case of zoonotic infections (Michel et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0065">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although male African buffalo could be regarded as natal dispersers, given that observational and genetic studies suggest that almost all male buffalo disperse away from their natal herds (van Hooft et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0082">2003</a>; Prins, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0072">1996</a>; Sinclair, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0080">1977</a>), behavior of females differs. Foundational studies described female African buffalo forming discrete herds with limited interherd movements (Prins, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0072">1996</a>; Sinclair, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0080">1977</a>); but more recent observational and genetic work suggests that dispersal by adult female buffalo is not uncommon (Halley, Vandewalle, Mari, &amp; Taolo, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0046">2002</a>; van Hooft et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0082">2003</a>). Epps et al. (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0028">2013</a>) also recorded partial migration of both female and male African buffalo, which they defined as seasonal movements. Genetic evidence also suggests female dispersal is common, as Simonsen et al. (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0079">1998</a>) found little genetic structure in either maternally inherited mitochondrial DNA or microsatellite (nuclear) loci among buffalo populations across 11 localities in eastern and southern Africa. Furthermore, van Hooft et al. (
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0082">2003</a>) estimated that 5‐20% of female buffalo older than two years of age dispersed per generation (7 years) based on mitochondrial DNA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite abundant evidence that dispersal is a common feature of the adult African buffalo behavioral repertoire, the social and ecological factors underlying decisions to disperse are not well understood in adult male or female buffalo (Halley et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0046">2002</a>; Winnie, Cross, &amp; Getz, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0085">2008</a>). Here, we used telemetry and observation to quantify dispersal behaviors for 304 female African buffalo over a 4‐year period. We hypothesized that female dispersal would be influenced by animal traits, environmental conditions, and disease status. We predicted that likelihood of female dispersal would vary with (1) individual condition, age, pregnancy and lactation status, (2) herd identity, (3) season and year, (4) individual macroparasite burdens, including strongyle nematodes, coccidia and schistosomes. Finally, although we had no clear a priori reason to predict that individual infections like microparasites, including 
  <span class="italic">Mycobacterium bovis</span> (causative agent of bovine tuberculosis) and 
  <span class="italic">Brucella abortus</span> (causative agent of brucellosis) would influence dispersal, we evaluated those relationships due to the critical implications of dispersal‐disease interactions for wildlife‐livestock relationships.
 </p>
</sec>
