<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35145-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study took place in the Kruger National Park (KNP), South Africa, which lies between 22.5 and 25.5°S, 31.0 and 31.6°E and is ~19,485 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in extent (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35145-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35145-fig-0001">1</a>). The park has one wet season per year with summer rainfall (October–March) ranging north to south from 400 to 700 mm per year. KNP is located at an average altitude of 250 m (range 200–900 m) above sea level with granitic soils in the west succeeded by Ecca shale, basalt, and rhyolites. The variation in moisture between seasons and soil types, as well as the variation in water holding capacity, gives rise to large regional variations in food availability. The main study area spans the landscape types of the Lebombo mountain bushveld, marula (
  <span class="italic">Sclerocarya birrea subsp. caffra</span>)/knobthorn (
  <span class="italic">Vachellia nigrescens</span>) savannah, Delagoa thorn (
  <span class="italic">Vachellia welwitschii</span>) thickets, Sabie and Crocodile River thickets, and thornveld (Venter, Scholes, &amp; Eckhardt, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0084">2003</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece35145-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>General (black line) and focal study areas (Lower Sabie herd, brown polygon; Mountain herd, black polygon; Power Line herd, gray polygon) for study of dispersal of female African buffalo (
    <span class="italic">Syncerus caffer</span>) in Kruger National Park in southern Africa (inset). Initial mass capture of 200 female African buffalo was from the Lower Sabie, Mountain, and Power Line herds in June/July and October of 2008, but females dispersed throughout much of the park during the course of the 4‐year study
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-5651-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Lower Sabie (LS) and Crocodile Bridge (CB) herds, although genetically panmictic (Tavalire et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0081">2018</a>), utilize distinct areas within KNP with different underlying geological features, which give rise to different soils and associated vegetation (Venter et al., 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0084">2003</a>). Water distribution (both natural and artificial) within the areas used by the herds also varies (Gaylard, Owen‐Smith, &amp; Redfern, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0038">2003</a>). This is important since buffalo are water dependent and herd densities are associated with distance to water (Redfern, Grant, Biggs, &amp; Getz, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0074">2003</a>). Opportunities for dispersal also varied for the study herds, due to their position with respect to the park's boundary fence. The fence restricted movement of LS animals to the east, while the CB animals were restricted to both the south and east (Picket, Cadenasso, &amp; Benning, 
  <a rid="ece35145-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35145-bib-0069">2003</a>). The CB animals consisted of two herds—Mountain and Power Line herds. We initially considered this a single herd, but after observing the buffalo and inspecting spatial data, we concluded that there were two separate herds. This led to a 4‐way categorical factor with LS_herd, CB_herd1, CB_herd2, and CB_herd1 and 2 combined (CB herd 1 and 2 were combined for the first three out of nine captures).
 </p>
</sec>
