<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">Our analysis calculated climate change velocity since the 1950s and estimates the rate of climate change that organisms will have to respond to
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. The results show higher values of climate change velocity in Germany than previous studies that used coarser data. Different results may be due to the different datasets and higher data resolution we used and to our approach in calculating the main constituents of climate velocities. Using the Mann-Kendall trend analysis instead of linear regression and medians instead of means of the spatial gradients decreases the sensitivity to a potentially skewed distribution of data. The highest velocity rates across Germany were calculated for lowland areas and the lowest rates in the mountain regions. Similar results were found for California by Loarie 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. This is because the spatial gradient of temperature change is the highest on mountain slopes and no large movements up or down the slope are required, thus resulting in a large change in temperature but low velocity. The opposite is true for the lowland areas, where large movements are required across geographical areas requiring higher velocity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>. Precipitation change velocity is also lowest in the mountain areas due to the orographic effect
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Although the limitation of this method is that it can underestimate constant climate conditions in the mountain areas, it has nevertheless been accepted as a baseline method and it could be complemented with other climate change velocity metrics (i.e. biotic velocity)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, climate change velocity results could, to some extent, depend on climatic variables that are used, spatial resolution of the data and to the parameter that defines analogue climates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
