<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Sanitation/Hygiene</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Water plays a key role in maintaining hygiene, which is directly associated with preventing disease [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>,
  <a rid="B60-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-12-08359">60</a>,
  <a rid="B98-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98-ijerph-12-08359">98</a>]. Health care facilities may depend heavily on water to protect the health of patients and workers [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>]. Studies outside of Canada suggest strong linkages between changes in precipitation, drought and diarrheal disease [
  <a rid="B99-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99-ijerph-12-08359">99</a>,
  <a rid="B100-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100-ijerph-12-08359">100</a>]. The World Health Organization has estimated that globally, the risk factor “water, sanitation and hygiene” accounted for 4% of all deaths [
  <a rid="B101-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B101-ijerph-12-08359">101</a>]. A global cross-sectional study found the incidence of diarrhoea in children under the age of five years increased 4% with each 10mm per month decrease in precipitation [
  <a rid="B102-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102-ijerph-12-08359">102</a>]. Modeling done on a global scale by Motoshita 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B103-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103-ijerph-12-08359">103</a>] based on recent historical data suggested that health damage from infectious diseases resulting from domestic water scarcity would be relatively low in the U.S. compared with other regions, although the health damage could not be modeled for Canada. However, in England and Wales, both low and excessive rainfall over the short-term was linked to a rise in the incidence of diarrhoea related to 
  <span class="italic">Giardia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cryptosporidium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E.coli</span>, 
  <span class="italic">S. typhi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">S. paratyphi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Campylobacter</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Streptobacillus moniliformis</span> (This is not a reportable disease in Canada and infections are thought to be lower in Canada and other Western countries than in the US; close to 200 cases of “rat bite fever” from 
  <span class="italic">Streptobacillus moniliformis</span> had been documented in the U.S. at the time of a 2007 publication [
  <a rid="B333-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B333-ijerph-12-08359">333</a>]) [
  <a rid="B104-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B104-ijerph-12-08359">104</a>]. Furthermore, people displaced by drought are considered likely to experience loss of sanitation and routine hygiene [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-08359">45</a>]. Human behavior may play a role, since the relaxing of hygiene practices could lead to an increase in diarrheal illnesses during drought [
  <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>]. As described above, 
  <span class="italic">Giardia</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Cryptosporidium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E. coli</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> cause a considerable number of disease cases in Canada each year. Alteration of the rates of such diseases by drought could have implications for public health.
 </p>
</sec>
