<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.6. Fungal Diseases</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drought may encourage the growth of various fungi associated with health impacts. Warmer, drier summers may have contributed to the establishment of 
  <span class="italic">Cryptococcus gattii</span> in Canada [
  <a rid="B142-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-ijerph-12-08359">142</a>]. Low moisture has been associated with 
  <span class="italic">C. gattii</span> soil colonization [
  <a rid="B143-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B143-ijerph-12-08359">143</a>]. The fungus was first detected on Vancouver Island in 1999, with more than 100 human cases identified [
  <a rid="B142-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-ijerph-12-08359">142</a>]. Between 1999 and 2007, there were 218 reported cases of 
  <span class="italic">C. gattii</span> in British Columbia, the region with the largest 
  <span class="italic">C. gattii</span> infected population in Canada and the world [
  <a rid="B144-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144-ijerph-12-08359">144</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drought may also positively affect the growth and dissemination of 
  <span class="italic">coccidioidomycosis</span> (Valley fever). Rainfall patterns and timing (including length of the drought) have been identified as modifiers of the incidence of this disease [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>,
  <a rid="B142-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-ijerph-12-08359">142</a>,
  <a rid="B145-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145-ijerph-12-08359">145</a>,
  <a rid="B146-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B146-ijerph-12-08359">146</a>,
  <a rid="B147-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B147-ijerph-12-08359">147</a>,
  <a rid="B148-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B148-ijerph-12-08359">148</a>]. Although the fungus is concentrated in the Southwestern U.S., recent cases that appeared to originate in Washington State (U.S.) suggest that it may be capable of moving to other areas [
  <a rid="B149-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B149-ijerph-12-08359">149</a>]. Valley fever is presently rare in Canada but climate change may impact the incidence of the disease among Canadian travelers [
  <a rid="B150-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B150-ijerph-12-08359">150</a>]. Since 1952, there have been a total of 128 cases of 
  <span class="italic">coccidiodomycosis</span> in Canada. These Canadian cases were acquired during travel outside Canada [
  <a rid="B150-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B150-ijerph-12-08359">150</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although associated with warming rather than drought, projections of increased precipitation in the winter months followed by reduced precipitation in the summer months for North America are thought to favor the dispersal of 
  <span class="italic">Blastomyces dermatitidis</span> spores, which causes 
  <span class="italic">blastomycosis</span> [
  <a rid="B142-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-ijerph-12-08359">142</a>]. Currently, this fungus occurs mainly in northwestern Ontario [
  <a rid="B142-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B142-ijerph-12-08359">142</a>]. Between 1994 and 2003, there were 309 cases of 
  <span class="italic">blastomycosis</span> in Ontario with more than half of the cases occurring between 2001 and 2003 [
  <a rid="B151-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151-ijerph-12-08359">151</a>]. Geographically, northern Ontario accounted for 61% of the cases, followed by 21% from the Toronto region [
  <a rid="B151-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B151-ijerph-12-08359">151</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
