<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.7.1. Dust, Particulates and Allergens</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drought is often accompanied by dry, dusty conditions and dust storms, which can impact health [
  <a rid="B83-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83-ijerph-12-08359">83</a>,
  <a rid="B152-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B152-ijerph-12-08359">152</a>,
  <a rid="B153-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B153-ijerph-12-08359">153</a>]. Climate change can lead to an increase in fine particulate matter, allergen and dust concentrations in the air in drought-prone areas [
  <a rid="B154-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B154-ijerph-12-08359">154</a>] which can have significant health impacts. A study of a lake desiccated through persistent drought in Saskatchewan found a greater prevalence of coughing, wheezing and eye and nasal irritation among residents living near the lake than among those in a control group [
  <a rid="B155-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B155-ijerph-12-08359">155</a>]. PM
  <sub>10</sub> (air particle) increases during and following dust storms have also been found to cause small increases in emergency room visits for bronchitis and sinusitis in the U.S. [
  <a rid="B156-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B156-ijerph-12-08359">156</a>] although dust storms were not associated with an increased risk of mortality [
  <a rid="B157-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B157-ijerph-12-08359">157</a>]. Air-borne toxins from algal blooms, which can be increased due to drought conditions, can also irritate the respiratory system, nose and eyes [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>,
  <a rid="B153-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B153-ijerph-12-08359">153</a>,
  <a rid="B155-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B155-ijerph-12-08359">155</a>]. It has been anecdotally suggested that there were numerous deaths from “dust pneumonia” related to dust inhalation during the drought of the 1930s in the U.S. [
  <a rid="B152-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B152-ijerph-12-08359">152</a>]. In Ontario, Charron 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-08359">52</a>] noted the possibility that drought with strong winds could lead to the transmission of Rickettsial diseases to humans from infected livestock.
 </p>
</sec>
