<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is now considered to be one of the major threats facing public health in the coming decades [
  <a rid="B231-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B231-ijerph-12-08359">231</a>]. Research on the health impacts of climate change (e.g., extreme heat events, vector-borne diseases) is increasing in Canada and internationally. However, health risks associated with drought and the implications of climate change have been less investigated. To our knowledge, this is the first comprehensive study of the health effects of drought on Canadians and of possible adaptation measures. The direct and indirect health impacts are potentially quite broad and serious given that drought is an important pathway for increased exposure to injuries, air pollution, food, water and vector-borne diseases. Evidence also suggests that a wide range of populations may be at higher risk for these impacts including infants and children, elderly people, the socially and economically disadvantaged, pregnant women, people who spend time outdoors and those with chronic diseases and compromised immune systems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possible health impacts of drought on Canadians are of concern because drought is a regular occurrence in some communities. Evidence suggests that the incidences of drought increased over most of the country between 1950 and 2002. Several long duration and severe droughts have affected the southern Canadian Prairies and interior valleys of British Columbia over the last century. Available studies mainly suggest that future droughts will likely be more frequent, longer lasting and more severe in those regions that already experience these events (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, more southern and interior areas of the country).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased adaptation to drought impacts will be needed at local and regional levels to protect health and to support vibrant and resilient communities. A range of measures exist to address the direct impacts of drought on health or that indirectly modify the ecological or socioeconomic pathways through which health is affected. The nature of individual droughts is expected to influence health impacts. However, there is a paucity of information concerning the effectiveness of many of the health adaptations. Efforts to protect the health of Canadians from future droughts will benefit by increased surveillance and monitoring of health impacts and greater investigation of health risks, vulnerable populations and measures to increase resilience at both the individual and community levels.The results of additional research to address current gaps and support future monitoring and surveillance will be key to inform adaptation and planning for future drought-related health impacts.</p>
</sec>
