<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13. Adaptation to the Human Health Impacts of Drought (Direct)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A broad range of adaptation strategies are available that help reduce the health impacts of drought. They generally attempt to reduce the impacts directly or they modify the environmental services or socioeconomic pathways through which drought affects health (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-12-08359-t002" href="#ijerph-12-08359-t002">Table 2</a>). However, there has been little evaluation of the effectiveness of many of these adaptations [
  <a rid="B183-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B183-ijerph-12-08359">183</a>,
  <a rid="B240-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B240-ijerph-12-08359">240</a>]. Limited knowledge of the effectiveness of current measures to reduce health risks from drought increases the possibility of “maladaptation” as communities and individuals prepare for climate change. Ensuring that adaptation strategies are developed with evidence-based information and through consultation with a wide range of partners mitigates the risk of maladaptation. 
 </p>
 <div id="ijerph-12-08359-t002" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="pii" class="object-id">ijerph-12-08359-t002_Table 2</span>
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Examples of adaptations to reduce the health impacts of drought.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Adaptations to the human health impacts</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water quality and water treatment monitoring</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disease surveillance and monitoring</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air quality monitoring and warnings</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Public education and outreach</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mental health prevention and awareness programs</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Adaptations to address changes to environmental services or socioeconomic pathways</span>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mainstreaming climate change into source water protection planning</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enhancing water service delivery and watershed management</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water capture and storage</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Increasing water use efficiency and water conservation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Modifying or adopting new agricultural practices, such as increasing reliance on crop irrigation</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introducing drought-resistant crops and diversifying crops and income sources</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using seasonal climate outlooks for crop planning</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Developing watershed management and climate change adaptation plans</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Insurance and other financial assistance programs</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irrigation and altering the timing and use of water</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.1. Monitoring Water Quality and Water Treatment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to monitoring indicators for drought itself [
   <a rid="B47-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-12-08359">47</a>] or drought-related drivers of health impacts [
   <a rid="B241-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B241-ijerph-12-08359">241</a>], increased water quality testing and monitoring of drinking water and/or recreational water during droughts can help safeguard health [
   <a rid="B43-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-12-08359">43</a>,
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>,
   <a rid="B65-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-ijerph-12-08359">65</a>,
   <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>,
   <a rid="B92-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92-ijerph-12-08359">92</a>]. For example, the province of Quebec has begun to adapt by increasing the monitoring of surface water and adopting more stringent standards for water quality surveillance. Water treatment is also an important adaptation to protect against water-borne disease [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>] and boil-water advisories may be a supportive tool, although they are designed to address fecal and not algal or chemical contamination. During the 2001 drought within the Kanai Blood Indian Reserve in Alberta (Canada), there was an increase in the number of boil water advisories called to protect residents against potential contamination [
   <a rid="B174-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-ijerph-12-08359">174</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.2. Disease Surveillance and Monitoring</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Surveillance and monitoring of diseases sensitive to drought such as those caused by 
   <span class="italic">E. coli</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C. perfringens</span> and WNV are important adaptations [
   <a rid="B43-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-12-08359">43</a>,
   <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-08359">52</a>,
   <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-08359">53</a>,
   <a rid="B56-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-12-08359">56</a>,
   <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>,
   <a rid="B94-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94-ijerph-12-08359">94</a>,
   <a rid="B242-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B242-ijerph-12-08359">242</a>,
   <a rid="B243-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B243-ijerph-12-08359">243</a>,
   <a rid="B244-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B244-ijerph-12-08359">244</a>]. Surveillance and monitoring can help to direct the provision of medical services and the development of needed vaccines to reduce risks to health [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>,
   <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>,
   <a rid="B94-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94-ijerph-12-08359">94</a>,
   <a rid="B242-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B242-ijerph-12-08359">242</a>,
   <a rid="B243-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B243-ijerph-12-08359">243</a>]. Modeling could play a role alongside surveillance [
   <a rid="B125-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B125-ijerph-12-08359">125</a>]. Control of disease vectors may also be implemented [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>]. Primary care physicians can be part of monitoring efforts and help identify and address cases of malnutrition during drought episodes [
   <a rid="B207-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B207-ijerph-12-08359">207</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.3. Air Quality Monitoring and Warnings</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When drought threatens air quality, for example by increasing particulate matter, air quality monitoring and warnings for the public can help reduce health risks [
   <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-08359">51</a>]. In over 60 communities and 10 provinces across Canada, the Air Quality Health Index (AQHI) provides individuals with information on the immediate health risks associated with local air quality [
   <a rid="B245-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B245-ijerph-12-08359">245</a>]. The AQHI includes information on how to reduce exposure to air pollution that is tailored to the general public and to vulnerable populations (e.g., parents with children and infants, seniors and those with cardiovascular and respiratory diseases). It is regularly updated and accessible through the Internet [
   <a rid="B246-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B246-ijerph-12-08359">246</a>]. However, it may be challenging to capture a quickly-developing event such as a forest fire smoke episode through the Index. Environment Canada informs the public of severe weather by providing special weather statements, advisories and watches [
   <a rid="B247-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B247-ijerph-12-08359">247</a>]. In responding to wildfires in western Canada in 2014, Environment Canada issued alerts through wildfire smoke warnings and special air quality statements [
   <a rid="B248-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B248-ijerph-12-08359">248</a>]. Provincial and community-level agencies further monitor events such as forest fires and provide information to those affected through a number of platforms, including websites and social media [
   <a rid="B249-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B249-ijerph-12-08359">249</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.4. Public Education and Outreach</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Public education is a key adaptation to protect health from drought. Personal protection measures that can be promoted by public health officials can include reducing water- and vector-borne disease exposures [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>], wearing respiratory masks on days when ambient air quality could impact health [
   <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-08359">51</a>], and the promotion of hand washing [
   <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>]. Education for travelers to and from Canada can raise awareness about diseases such as malaria [
   <a rid="B80-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80-ijerph-12-08359">80</a>], or tuberculosis, which may be increasingly transmitted under social conditions created by drought in developing countries [
   <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-08359">52</a>]. To prevent spinal cord injuries resulting from diving in shallow waters, some jurisdictions have implemented public education, including the posting of notices where diving is not safe [
   <a rid="B170-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B170-ijerph-12-08359">170</a>]. For example, brain and spinal cord injury prevention programs have been carried out in Saskatchewan and Ontario (Canada) and in Washington State (U.S.) [
   <a rid="B250-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B250-ijerph-12-08359">250</a>,
   <a rid="B251-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B251-ijerph-12-08359">251</a>,
   <a rid="B252-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B252-ijerph-12-08359">252</a>]. However, evaluations of these programs suggest that program delivery needs to be well designed and robust to be effective. Although the initiative in Saskatchewan was found to change knowledge among students, in the Toronto (Ontario) case only 16% of students in schools where the program video was distributed viewed the information [
   <a rid="B250-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B250-ijerph-12-08359">250</a>]. The one time intervention in Washington State, where students attended a session which included a video, lecture and personal testimony around traumatic brain and spinal cord injury, had little impact on knowledge or behavior [
   <a rid="B252-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B252-ijerph-12-08359">252</a>]. Similarly, evidence suggests that boil water advisories may not be adhered to by everyone. During the gastroenteritis outbreak in Walkerton, Ontario (Canada), some residents under the boil water advisory continued to use and occasionally drink the water without boiling it [
   <a rid="B85-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-ijerph-12-08359">85</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The link between water and hygienic practices should be considered when developing drought adaptation measures. Conservation should take into consideration on-farm agricultural practices, regional water management and treatment and allow for and encourage individual hygienic practices such as hand washing [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>]. In the later example, homes and businesses could also promote both water conservation and hand washing by installing low-flow faucet aerators [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>]. Education of health care providers can also benefit efforts to address drought impacts on health [
   <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-08359">53</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.5. Addressing Mental Health Impacts</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive actions may be taken by individuals and professionals within primary care and community services settings to reduce the mental health impacts of drought. Personal hopefulness and positive attitudes towards the rural lifestyle have been highlighted as useful adaptations to drought [
   <a rid="B218-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B218-ijerph-12-08359">218</a>,
   <a rid="B253-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B253-ijerph-12-08359">253</a>]. According to Caldwell and Boyd [
   <a rid="B254-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B254-ijerph-12-08359">254</a>] rural Australian families used a combination of both positive (e.g., problem-focused coping, optimism and positive appraisal) and less beneficial strategies (e.g., cognitive dissonance, denial and avoidance of negative social influences) in their response to drought. Primary care practitioners can provide support to reduce symptoms of mental illness exacerbated by drought and ineffective coping mechanisms such as substance abuse. They may also provide information about financial support resources or community drought support groups [
   <a rid="B207-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B207-ijerph-12-08359">207</a>,
   <a rid="B255-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B255-ijerph-12-08359">255</a>]. Mental health programs in schools and in occupational settings and suicide prevention and awareness programs have also been identified as possible adaptation measures [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>,
   <a rid="B216-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B216-ijerph-12-08359">216</a>,
   <a rid="B222-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B222-ijerph-12-08359">222</a>,
   <a rid="B256-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B256-ijerph-12-08359">256</a>,
   <a rid="B257-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B257-ijerph-12-08359">257</a>]. Newspapers may be another pathway to communicate broadly about mental health during drought [
   <a rid="B258-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B258-ijerph-12-08359">258</a>].In Australia rural support workers help traditional mental health professionals identify farmers experiencing mental distress and refer them to support services [
   <a rid="B259-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B259-ijerph-12-08359">259</a>]. Training in mental health first aid can also increase the capacity of rural support workers to address mental health needs in drought-affected rural areas [
   <a rid="B260-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B260-ijerph-12-08359">260</a>]. One study suggested that the Rural Adversity Mental Health Program (RAMHP), which is based on a community development model, is effective in building capacity and resiliency to cope with the impacts of drought in rural New South Wales (Australia) [
   <a rid="B261-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B261-ijerph-12-08359">261</a>]. Linking the services and programs focused on mental health, community or social needs with those on practical assistance for farming communities is considered key for addressing mental health concerns associated with or exacerbated by drought [
   <a rid="B262-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B262-ijerph-12-08359">262</a>]. Access to support services for older individuals is another consideration [
   <a rid="B256-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B256-ijerph-12-08359">256</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Community-building [
   <a rid="B263-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B263-ijerph-12-08359">263</a>] and events which increase social capital can further help decrease psychological stress [
   <a rid="B254-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B254-ijerph-12-08359">254</a>]. High levels of social capital in many Canadian (Prairie) rural communities [
   <a rid="B176-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-ijerph-12-08359">176</a>,
   <a rid="B264-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B264-ijerph-12-08359">264</a>], based upon high levels of trust, networking and participation in organizations help reduce stress associated with drought [
   <a rid="B176-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-ijerph-12-08359">176</a>,
   <a rid="B264-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B264-ijerph-12-08359">264</a>]. However, Australian farm families faced heavier workloads during the drought of 2002–2003, which left less time for community participation, volunteer activities and hence could negatively impact social capital and the community [
   <a rid="B201-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B201-ijerph-12-08359">201</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
