<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Species that are affected by climate change may alter their distribution and adapt through changes in morphology, physiology, behavior, and life history (Smith, Murray, Harding, Lease, &amp; Martin, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Smith et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Small mammals appear to be able to adapt morphology and life history to environmental shifts within one to three generations (Crews &amp; Gore, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Mifsud et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). However, the adaptive responses of large mammals to climate change are poorly understood. In comparison with small mammals, large species can better avoid harsh environments by moving long distances, tolerate austere conditions with large bodies, and recover over multiple seasons to reproduce over long lifespans (Barboza, Parker, &amp; Hume, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Impacts of climate change on animals are twofold: direct effects of temperature on the animal (i.e., energetic load as heat) and indirect effects of temperature on the animal's food supply (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34019-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). Warm temperatures advance the seasonal growth of grasses to reduce the availability of nitrogen for growth of cattle and bison (Craine, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Craine, Elmore, Olson, &amp; Tolleson, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Craine, Towne, Joern, &amp; Hamilton, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Craine et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Ambient air temperature directly affects the costs of thermoregulation of the animal in cold winters and the ability to lose excess heat in warm summers (Long et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Speakman &amp; Król, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Seasonal patterns of air temperature affect the onset, duration, and intensity of plant production that sets the quantity and quality of food for growth and reproduction of herbivores from spring through autumn (Albon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Huston &amp; Wolverton, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
