<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At least four biological concepts attempt to explain the phenomenon of changing body size. Cope's rule recognizes the tendency of vertebrate animals to increase body size over geological time scales (Stanley, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1973</xref>). Bergmann's rule emphasizes the positive relationship between body size and latitude, which suggests that the ability to retain body heat favors larger bodies at cooler temperatures as long as net primary production is adequate for animals of large size (Bergmann, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1847</xref>; Huston &amp; Wolverton, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Watt, Mitchell, &amp; Salewski, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). The Metabolic Theory of Ecology emphasizes the allometric scaling of body size and the underlying relationships between the volume of animals and the surfaces that are exposed to the environment (Brown &amp; Sibly, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The Heat Dissipation Limit Theory emphasizes heat load as a driver of body size because metabolism can produce excess energy (heat), which may be more difficult to dissipate as body size and metabolic work increase (Speakman &amp; Król, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). However, these relationships alone are not sufficient to accurately project the effect of climate change on the body size of large species. Although the fossil record provides abundant evidence of changes in the body size of vertebrate animals (i.e., dinosaurs, proboscideans) that have been linked to global shifts in climate (Sander et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), taxa differ in the direction, rate, and extent of response to warming and cooling (Lovegrove &amp; Mowoe, 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Among large mammals, changes in body size at a continental scale declined quickly with rising temperature but rose more slowly with cooling over the past 100 million years (Evans et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34019-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
