<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28" class="p">Moreover, shifts in forest disturbances such as wind, pests, and fire may adversely affect forest productivity under future climate change. The productivity of and carbon storage in Europe’s forests is likely to decrease as climate change and forest disturbances intensify
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>, though both increasing and decreasing trends have been found in the growth and productivity across Europe
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">83</xref>
 </sup>. For example, the growth of European beech was observed to have declined because of droughts over the past 20th century
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>, and its NPP and water-use efficiency was predicted to reduce under future climate conditions (A1B scenario) due to aggravated water shortage and droughts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">84</xref>
 </sup>. As the risks from forest fire are predicted to become increasingly serious in China, mainly because of an increase in fire weather in central and southeastern China
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>
 </sup>, measures should be implemented to reduce the negative impacts of fire disturbance on forest productivity. The sensitivity of NPP to climate change is also the key to understanding how risk develops and evolves. Piao 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup> found that the inter-annual correlation between terrestrial productivity and temperature decreased in temperate regions because of an increase in drought over the past decade, while Heyder 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> reported that strong warming could amplify the sensitivity to declining precipitation in temperate and tropical ecosystems.
</p>
