<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To test for an effect of selection treatment and ambient salinity on fecundity, we placed mate‐guarding pairs from each of the selection lines and controls (
 <italic class="italic">N</italic> = 6–8 per line × salinity treatment) in 15‐mL six‐well plates filled with artificial seawater at one of three test salinities: 20 ppt (low), 35 ppt (ambient), and 50 ppt (high) and maintained them at 19°C under 12‐h L: 12‐h D conditions. All adults and larvae in this experiment were fed ground spirulina fish food 
 <italic class="italic">ad libitum</italic>. We followed each female until she produced three broods, or for 21 days, whichever came first. We recorded the day the female of each pair first became gravid and the dates of her first three broods. Each time a new brood hatched, the female was moved to a new well in the plate. Offspring from each brood were counted by individually pipetting larvae to a new dish. We calculated larvae produced per day for each female as the total number of larvae in the first three broods, divided by the number of days required to produce the first three broods, from the day she first became gravid. For females that produced fewer than three broods, we divided the total number of offspring produced in 21 days by 21. About 20% of females in each treatment failed to produce any larvae. We expected some level of brood failure, as crosses among populations of 
 <italic class="italic">T. californicus</italic> experience substantial outbreeding depression (Edmands 
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>), and even seven generations after the initial cross, these lines have likely not been completely purged incompatibilities leading to reproductive failure. A logistic regression indicated no differences between selection treatments or rearing salinities in the probability of brood failure, so females producing zero larvae were removed from further analysis. We tested for an effect of selection treatment and rearing salinity on larvae produced per day in a two‐way ANOVA in the statistical program R, with individual selection lines + salinity treatments as replicates.
</p>
