<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Researchers have conducted extensive researches focusing on the 1.5 °C warming target. However, these studies were mainly based on simulations under Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) scenarios, for example, using datasets from global climate system models of the 5th phase of the Coupled Model Inter-comparison Project (CMIP5). RCP scenarios are devoted to projecting the transient response of climate to specific radiative forcing conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Researchers usually choose a period centered at the year of 1.5 °C or 2.0 °C global warming above pre-industrial levels to analyze climate responses for the two specific warming targets. During this time the global mean surface temperature keeps increasing, due to the transient feature of the simulations. Results based on transient simulations show that mean temperature increases mostly in mid-high latitudes of the Northern Hemisphere under 1.5 °C global warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. Compared to the change of mean temperature, response of extreme events to global warming varies from region to region
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. Extreme high temperature increases in most parts of the Northern Hemisphere and southern Africa under 2.0 °C global warming, while the magnitude of increase reduces under 1.5 °C warmer world
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Limiting global warming at 1.5 °C can effectively reduce the population size affected by extreme climate compared to 2.0 °C global warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
