<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Exhortations to act decisively and in an extraordinary fashion in the face of potentially disastrous global warming are common (
 <xref rid="bibr18-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brzoska, 2009</xref>), but so far efforts to securitize climate change have arguably been unsuccessful. Armed conflicts and strains on cooperation and international organizations are sometimes envisaged to follow from climate change and its effects (e.g. mass migration and food price spikes) (
 <xref rid="bibr19-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burke et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr82-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Podesta and Ogden, 2008</xref>), although this thesis has been challenged vigorously (
 <xref rid="bibr98-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Selby, 2014</xref>). The subject of climate change as a threat has been picked up on by security institutions, including the Pentagon, which in a recent directive instructs US military leaders to ‘address climate change-related risks and opportunities across the full range of military operations, including steady-state campaign planning and operations and contingency planning’ (
 <xref rid="bibr95-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Scarborough, 2016</xref>). However, the climate is not the threat that the Pentagon is gearing up to combat. Rather, the climate is deemed to be a 
 <italic class="italic">facilitator</italic> of things that threaten more traditional referent objects such as state sovereignty and international stability: insurgency, conflict, instability, and migration are the existential threats, merely compounded by climate change (
 <xref rid="bibr20-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Busby, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr25-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">CNA Corporation, 2007</xref>). In any case, climate change remains a patchy concern in military planning and scenario-building (
 <xref rid="bibr33-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Depledge, 2010</xref>).
</p>
