<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tensile strength</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Preliminary tests showed that newly collected fishing lines did not adhere well to the metal bar and had to be wrapped several times around it to ensure reasonable “clamping”. However, these lines could not be wrapped around the lower bar without stretching them unintentionally so they were anchored using a magnet.</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements with single newly collected fishing lines gave a tensile strength of 1.9 MPa (maximum force = 0.1 mN) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>) that should be sufficient to catch and support one or more prey items as 
  <span class="italic">Anatopynia debilis</span> (weight between 1 and 10 mg). Although not tested in this study, it could be assumed that the thread type used to attach the “hammock” to the rocky substrate displays higher tensile strength values than the fishing lines used for prey capture. Weight measurements yield for the 20 mm long larva 30 mg and for the larger, 40 mm long ones a weight of 100 mg, ten times heavier than the maximum load derived from the tensile strength values for a single fishing line.
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Boxplot diagram of the tensile strength values of 
     <span class="italic">Arachnocampa</span> fishing lines. In general, threads (singular or triplet arranged) dried in the desiccator cabinet (60% RH, 20 °C) display higher tensile strength values than the wet ones, however show no bonding ability. The single wet threads are able to hold the load up to two average prey items (mean weight of 
     <span class="italic">Anatopynia debilis</span> = 5 mg), while more/or heavier preys could be held by tangled up threads. Differences between tensile strength for the triple-arranged threads (wet/dry) and the single ones (wet/dry) are highly significant (P &lt; 0.001).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39098_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1839" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Triplet-combined fishing lines only doubled the tensile strength to 3.5 MPa (maximum force = 0.17 mN), indicating that these lines interact slightly and do not break simultaneously. However, as the moving prey during catch often comes in contact with several fishing lines and tangles them up, this multi-thread effect would provide weight relief for each thread and support larger or more prey items.</p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time-lapse imaging of single threads freshly collected (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8A</a>) and dried (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8B</a>) showing that the lines shorten and the droplets leave a residue as they evaporate. When threads were removed from a snare and immediately exposed to dry air, they shortened to approx. 80% after 60 min and 59.1% of their original lengths after 100 min, respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig8">8C</a>). As the threads dry and lose droplet mass, they tend to drift in the slightest air movement and could possibly become statically charged.
  <div id="Fig8" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 8</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Fishing line of 
     <span class="italic">Arachnocampa flava</span> at (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) start and (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) after 60 min of dry air exposure. Beyond the thread shortening also a droplet mass loss could be observed. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Time-course analyses of the thread shortening during dry air exposure. Scale bar for A and B = 2 mm.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39098_Fig8_HTML" id="d29e1873" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dried fishing lines have a much higher tensile strength than wet ones, e.g., 4.6 MPa (maximum force = 0.23 mN) for single fishing lines and 9.8 MPa (maximum force = 0.49 mN) for three combined (P &lt; 0.001) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7B</a>). Moreover, drying of the fishing lines under low humidity (&lt;80% RH) resulted in dehydration of the droplet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> and only a small remnant comprising the central core remained visible. The dried fishing lines also appeared stiffer and could not be smoothly wrapped around the upper bar in the same way as fresh threads. The silk thread of dry fishing lines also showed no adhesion to the probe holder, whereas the dry remnants of the droplets attached firmly to the metal surfaces (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig9">9</a>) of the upper bar and pin under tension.
  <div id="Fig9" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 9</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Attachment of the dried fishing line to the metal bar for the tensile strength measurements. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Higher magnification shows that the droplet core (yellow arrow) firmly attached to the metal when loaded, while the silk thread (yellow arrowhead) shows no sign of bonding.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39098_Fig9_HTML" id="d29e1900" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
