<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Past research has examined the many predictors of climate change concern and belief [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], with a recent meta-analysis demonstrating that political affiliation and political ideology are the main predictors of climate change belief [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Consistent with this finding, previous research in New Zealand identifies a latent profile of respondents (“climate skeptics”) with low agreement levels in both climate change reality and its human causation that had the highest levels of self-reported political conservatism [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Since distrust in the reality of climate change and its human cause is associated with a more conservative political orientation, it is likely that change in climate change belief will differ for distinct groups in a given society. That is to say, we predict that the observed increase in climate change beliefs might be greatest among politically liberal individuals, while small or null for their politically conservative counterparts. Due to power considerations we cannot test this prediction at present [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], but the New Zealand Attitudes and Values Study is ongoing and this is something we aim to address in the years to come. Similar to public opinion polls showing that perception of climate change threat fluctuates over time [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>] and [
 <xref rid="pone.0174246.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], we also expect that climate change beliefs would fluctuate over time. The ongoing nature of this longitudinal project means we will be able to pinpoint whether fluctuations on climate change beliefs is a direct result of particular socio-economic circumstances.
</p>
