<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">Bioclimatic variables play an integral part in the life-cycle of 
   <italic class="italic">Ctenocephalides felis</italic>, the most common flea found on companion animals. It is essential that we understand the effects of climate on 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> distribution as fleas are a major veterinary and public health concern. This study investigated the current distribution of 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> in Australia and future projections based on climate modelling.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">Typing of 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> was undertaken using the cytochrome 
   <italic class="italic">c</italic> oxidase subunit 1 (
   <italic class="italic">cox</italic>1) mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) region and current distribution of haplotypes was mapped by Maximum Entropy (Maxent) niche modelling. All 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> haplotypes have been predicted to persist in environments along the eastern and southern coastlines of Australia and distinct ecological niches were observed for two 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> haplogroups. Clade ‘Cairns’ haplogroup thrives under the northern coastal tropical conditions whilst Clade ‘Sydney’ haplogroup persists in temperate climates along the eastern and southern coasts. The model was then used to predict areas that are projected to have suitable climatic conditions for these haplogroups in 2050 and 2070 under the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) climate change scenarios. Under all IPCC Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) climate change scenarios, the geographical range of all haplotypes was reduced by 5.59–42.21% in 2050 and 27.08–58.82% by 2070. The ranges of all clades were predicted to shift south along the eastern coastline.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p id="Par3" class="p">As future temperatures exceed critical threshold temperatures for 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> development in the northern tropical areas, Clade ‘Cairns’ haplogroup is predicted to shift south along the coastline and possibly outcompete the temperate haplogroup in these areas. If 
   <italic class="italic">C. felis</italic> haplogroups possess distinct climatic niches it suggests a potential for these to be biologically distinct and have differing developmental rates and vector capabilities.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Electronic supplementary material</title>
  <p class="p">The online version of this article (10.1186/s13071-019-3399-6) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
