<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To manage missing data (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0155137.s009" class="xref">S4 Table</xref>), we used questions about strengths of belief in the local effects of climate change and having experienced effects of climate change (which were taken to represent the perception of risk from climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]), preferences clustered into value profiles, and educational level as variables to infer five complete data sets (n = 766) using maximum likelihood methodology [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0155137.s004" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>). After ensuring that the tentative variables passed a test for collinearity based on the variance inflation factor [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], we applied multinomial logistic regression to all five datasets in each country to test for differences between the groups that were differentiated by level of education and value profile with regard to their stated strength of belief in the local effects of climate change and having experienced the effects of climate change. The best and most parsimonious models were chosen by backward selection after adding all variables using Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) as a performance indicator. The expected probabilities of the respondents' strengths of belief in the local effects of climate change and in having experienced the effects of climate change were estimated from 25,000 simulations drawn from the posterior distribution for each model. All analyses were conducted using the R Project for Statistical Computing packages v2.14.1 and v3.1.2 [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], and in particular by applying the libraries "vcd" for visualizing categorical data [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], "Aspect" for optimal scaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], "NMF" for nonnegative matrix factorization [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], "APCluster" for Affinity Propagation Clustering [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], "Amelia II" for multiple imputation [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], and "Zelig" for multinomial logistic regression modelling [
 <xref rid="pone.0155137.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>].
</p>
