<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results reported do not provide a full description of the dynamics of gene expression, and the conclusions derived are limited to conditions tested. Nevertheless, they open a series of questions that are worthy of further research.</p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of different sowing events, under natural increasing photoperiod corroborate that 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> transcript levels are always present in absence of a cold-effective induction, and that the level of expression of 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> is highly dependent on day-length. We provide evidence that the plants exhibit a shift in the pattern of expression of genes from the vernalization and photoperiod pathways, when day-length reaches around 12 h 30 min. To isolate these effects from genetic background, additional research with isogenic lines will be needed. In particular, future experiments combining sequential sowings in natural photoperiod with gradual vernalization treatments would shed light on possible effects on plant development and potential agronomic consequences of the expression shift observed, when vernalization is not complete. Further research to ascertain these possible agronomic effects with segregating populations and isogenic lines for 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> is underway.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other repressors appear to be acting in the process of vernalization. 
  <span class="italic">HvOS2</span> is a suitable candidate, given the evidence accumulating in other grasses, and the genotypic differences found in our study. This hypothesis should be tested with plant materials sharing genetic background, to avoid confounding effects of other segregating genes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span>, a central gene for winter barley performance in Southern Europe, is not induced just by short days. In winter cultivars, it must receive additional induction through LD, and/or a cold period, to be effective in reducing time to flowering.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The photoperiod conditions of the experiments here described correspond to a wide range of late spring sowings for winter barley in the Mediterranean area. The genetic mechanisms and the environmental controls investigated in this study will be useful to define both varieties and agronomics of winter cereals best suited for current and future climate conditions.</p>
</sec>
