<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant materials</div>
  <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two winter cultivars, representative of barleys grown in Spain, with adaptation patterns likely related to differences in vernalization requirement [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>], were studied. ‘Barberousse’ (six-rowed, (‘Hauter’ x (‘Hatif de Grignon’ x ‘Ares’)) x ‘Ager’) is an old French cultivar developed by Ringot and registered in 1977, well adapted to the coldest areas of Spain. ‘Hispanic’ (two-rowed, ‘Mosar’ x (‘Flika’ x ‘Lada’)) is a French commercial cultivar developed by Florimond Desprez and registered in 1993, showing broad adaptation in Spain, and even acceptable agronomics in the Nile delta [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Both cultivars were multiplied in isolation at the EEAD-CSIC farm, collected from bagged spikes, from original seed provided by the companies. They have the same allelic combination in 
   <span class="italic">HvVRN1</span> (winter allele), 
   <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">PPD-H1</span>, but differ in 
   <span class="italic">HvFT1</span> and 
   <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> (
   <span class="italic">PPD-H2</span>, present in ‘Hispanic’, defective allele in ‘Barberousse’) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant growth, phenotyping and sampling</div>
  <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiment 1 – sowings under increasing natural photoperiod</div>
   <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each variety, we used two 1 L-pots at each sowing time (standard substrate made of peat, fine sand and perlite, from a mix with 46 kg, 150 kg and 1 L, respectively). Pots were sown with 7 seeds once a week, sequentially, from Feb 11th until April 8th 2015, in a glasshouse in Zaragoza (41°43′N, 00°49′W) under natural photoperiod (Fig. 
    <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) and controlled temperature (22 ± 1 °C day / 18 ± 1 °C night). Unless specified, plants were not vernalized (NV). Spatial homogeneity in irradiance was obtained rotating the plants each week. As vernalized control, three pots of each variety were sown on Feb 11th. They were grown during 7 days (until germination) under glasshouse conditions, and then were vernalized (VER) under short photoperiod (8 h light) and 6 ± 2 °C for 49 days. After the cold treatment, plants were transferred to the same glasshouse on April 8th, when natural photoperiod was 13 h. Duration of daylight at sowing and sampling dates was gathered from 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.timeanddate.com/sun" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.timeanddate.com/sun</span>, taking sunrise and sunset as the times when the upper edge of the Sun’s disc touches the horizon.
   </p>
   <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For gene expression, the last expanded leaf of three 21-day-old plants (3-leaf stage) was sampled 8 h after dawn, frozen in liquid nitrogen, homogenized (Mixer Mill model MM301, Retsch) and conserved at − 80 °C until RNA isolation.</p>
   <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On a fixed date (19th May, day-length 15 h, 97 days after the first sowing), we took a cross-sectional sample across sowing events. The last expanded leaf of each weekly-sown plant was sampled 12 h after dawn for RNA isolation. Then, dissection of the plants (all stems of each plant) was made in order to determine the development of the apex (with naked eye, reproductive apex was equivalent to more than 3 mm).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiment 2 – growth chamber, 12 h light</div>
   <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seventy-two seeds of each variety were sown in 12-well trays (650 cc) and allowed to germinate during 7 days in a growth chamber at 12 h light, 20 °C/12 h dark, 16 °C, 65% HR and light intensity of 300 μmol m
    <span class="sup">− 2</span> s
    <span class="sup">− 1</span> PAR. Then, the trays were divided in three groups that received the following treatments: (A) NV, (B) 14-days VER and (C) 28-days VER. Group A stayed at the growth chamber while B and C were transferred to a vernalization chamber, 8 h light/16 h night and constant temperature (6 ± 2 °C). Groups B and C were returned to the growth chamber after 14 and 28 days of cold treatment, respectively. After forty days at the growth chamber, three plants of each variety and treatment were transferred to a 1 L pots to let them grow until flowering. Development according to the Zadoks scale (first node, DEV31, and awn appearance DEV49) [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>] was recorded along the experiment every 3–5 days. In addition, apex dissections were carried out at selected time points to establish the Waddington developmental stage [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>]. The experiment ended 136 days after sowing.
   </p>
   <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For gene expression, the last expanded leaf of four plants was sampled 14, 28, 35 or 49 days after germination (A) or after the end of the VER treatment (B and C), 10 h into the light period (2 h before the end of the day, as in [
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]).
   </p>
   <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though a single point may not be reflective of expression at other times during the day, in all the experiments, sampling times were chosen to capture high expression of the genes involved, taking into account the period and amplitude of their circadian rhythms. 
    <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> expression was tested in leaf samples, taken at different times along the light period in ‘Barberousse’ plants (28 days old, and 16 h light) (Additional file 
    <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S5), with high and comparable expression levels throughout the day.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vernalization response of ‘Hispanic’ and ‘Barberousse’</div>
  <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the course of earlier experiments, carried out in the Phytotron of Martonvásár (Hungary), both varieties were exposed to different VER treatments (0, 15, 30 or 45 days, 5 ± 2 °C, 8 h light), and then transferred to a growth chamber with 16 h day-length, 18 °C and light intensity of 340 μmol m
   <span class="sup">− 2</span> s
   <span class="sup">− 1</span>. Flowering date was recorded at each treatment (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S1).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gene expression analysis</div>
  <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RNA extraction was carried out using NucleoSpin RNA Plant Kit (Macherey-Nagel) following manufacturer instructions. Total RNA (1 μg) was employed for cDNA synthesis using SuperScript III Reverse Transcriptase (Invitrogen) and oligo (dT)
   <sub>20</sub> primer (Invitrogen). Real-time PCR quantification (ABI 7500, Applied Biosystems) was performed for samples from each time point from NV plants and for VER plants as control treatment. Three biological replicates and two technical replicates were performed per sample and pair of primers (
   <span class="italic">HvVRN1</span>, 
   <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span>, 
   <span class="italic">PPD-H1</span>, 
   <span class="italic">HvCO2</span>, 
   <span class="italic">HvCO9</span>, 
   <span class="italic">HvOS2, HvFT1</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">HvFT3</span>). Primer sequences and conditions are specified in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S5. Expression levels were normalized to 
   <span class="italic">Actin</span> expression, taking into account primer efficiencies.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gene sequencing</div>
  <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polymorphisms in 
   <span class="italic">HvCO2</span>, 
   <span class="italic">HvCO9</span> and 
   <span class="italic">HvOS2</span> were identified by sequencing genomic DNA PCR-amplified overlapping fragments. Primers were designed to amplify each gene (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S5). The resulting sequences have been deposited at the European Nucleotide Archive as part of project PRJEB27962. BLASTN sequence comparisons [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>] were carried out against the barley Morex reference genome [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>], and Morex, Barke and Bowman whole genome barley sequences [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>] at the IPK (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webblast.ipk-gatersleben.de/barley_ibsc/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://webblast.ipk-gatersleben.de/barley_ibsc/</span>) web server. Sequence comparisons against NCBI nucleotide database, cv. Haruna Nijo [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>] and cv. Zangqing320 genomic sequences [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>] were also performed. Sequence alignments were carried out in MEGA-X v.10.0.4 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. Predicted protein alignments were carried out in ClustalW [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>]. Protein domains were annotated according to Cockram et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], Greenup et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>] and Prosite v20.79 (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://prosite.expasy.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://prosite.expasy.org/</span>). The online tool SIFT (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sift.bii.a-star.edu.sg" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sift.bii.a-star.edu.sg</span>) was used to predict the likely impact of amino acid substitutions on protein function, using as reference Morex [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. Scores below 0.05 are predicted to affect protein function. Putative VRN1 regulatory elements were predicted by scanning a motif compiled from ChIP-seq peaks reported in Deng et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>] and annotated in 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://floresta.eead.csic.es/footprintdb/index.php?motif=VRN1&amp;db=EEADannot" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://floresta.eead.csic.es/footprintdb/index.php?motif=VRN1&amp;db=EEADannot</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. Briefly, upstream sequences of target barley genes were retrieved from the RSAT plant mirror (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://plants.rsat.eu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://plants.rsat.eu</span>, [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]) and 
   <span class="italic">matrix-scan-quick</span> used to scan the motif using a genomic Markov model of order 2 (upstream-noorf_Hordeum_vulgare.IBSCv2.37). Only sites with weight &gt; = 3.7 were considered.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses were carried out with R software [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. For gene expression results, the mean of two technical replications of ∆Ct (Ct actin – Ct target) was used as unit. Analyses of variance for phenotypes or gene expression data were performed considering all factors (genotype, sampling time, vernalization treatment) as fixed. Multiple comparisons were obtained by Fisher’s protected Least Significant Differences (LSD) with the R package ‘agricolae’ [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. Pearson correlations were carried out with ‘cor’ function.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
