<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> expression is not constitutive in winter cultivars, it needs induction by cold and plant development
 </div>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found differences in responsiveness to SD between the genotypes. ‘Hispanic’ developed faster than ‘Barberousse’ and flowered without vernalization. It also flowered earlier in the natural photoperiod experiment, when day-lengths increased from SD to LD (72 days in the first sowing event, without vernalization), than under SD conditions only (126 days at 12 h, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). The two varieties differ (among others) in the presence/absence of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3.</span> We hypothesized that this could be a key factor differentiating their response to insufficient vernalization. This gene bears particular agronomic relevance for Mediterranean environments, as it stands at the peak of flowering time QTL and grain yield QTL x Environment peaks in several populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. A supporting role for promotion to flowering in winter cultivars, receiving less than full vernalization under field conditions, was proposed for 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Its expression is usually reported in SD, although it is also found in LD conditions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. In our experiments, 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> transcripts were only detected: (a) after full or partial vernalization, in early-medium development (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), and (b) in absence of vernalization, in rather late developmental stages, and only in plants sown under shortest day-lengths (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). We expected expression of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span>, the “short photoperiod” gene, at least in the earliest sowings in the experiment with natural photoperiods. Instead, it was effectively repressed, either by the low but always present 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span>, or by other repressors. Under constant photoperiod of 12 h, 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> was detected in ‘Hispanic’ only after four weeks VER (2 weeks were insufficient) and 5 weeks in growth chamber (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). Thus, 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> was expressed in a winter cultivar only after some cold exposure, and increasingly with plant age. It is particularly remarkable that the expression of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> was correlated with earlier flowering, although it was detected only after the transition from vegetative to reproductive apex had occurred (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). This late effect on development is consistent with findings in spring wheat varieties [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>], and in barley [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. This last study evidenced that genotypes with 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> accelerated the initiation of spikelet primordia and the early reproductive development but required LD to flower.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The induction of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> in sowing event 2 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), together with the progressive increase of the transcripts after 28-days VER, when 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> is not detected, are consistent with the antagonistic role between 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> and 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> revealed by Casao et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN2</span> absence allows induction of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3,</span> although it would not ensure 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> expression, hinting at the possible involvement of other repressors. In this respect, a possible relationship of 
  <span class="italic">HvOS2</span> with 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> was suggested in the literature [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>]. Future research on this possible role would shed light on the control of 
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">HvFT3</span> expression occurred in samplings coincident with that of 
  <span class="italic">HvVRN1</span> and 
  <span class="italic">HvFT1</span>. Parallel expression of 
  <span class="italic">FT</span> genes has been found in grasses. Lv et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>] reported that developmental changes regulated by 
  <span class="italic">FT1</span> were related to transcript levels of other 
  <span class="italic">FT</span>-like genes, such as 
  <span class="italic">FT3,</span> in 
  <span class="italic">Brachypodium</span> and wheat. Under LD, these authors only found upregulation of 
  <span class="italic">FT3</span> when 
  <span class="italic">FT1</span> was upregulated, as in our findings with 12 h day-length. Their concurrent expression could be related to the interactions between FT1 and other FT-like proteins, including FT3, with proteins FD-like and 14–3-3, all components of the florigen activation complex (FAC), in wheat and barley [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
