<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Grain yield across trials was primarily and significantly affected by rainfall and Tm as shown by the significant correlations between GY and the former weather variables. As described in Section “Introduction,” 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer and Wood (1979)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mitchell et al. (1996)</xref> highlighted the discrimination against long-duration genotypes in poor-yielding environments, and the resulting confounding effects hindering the discovery of genotypes with drought avoidance and resistance. While these confounding effects have been reported and cited in the literature, the mechanisms associated with this response are poorly understood in the context of winter wheat rain fed regions of Turkey and Iran. When comparing different wheat genotypes (particularly with variable phenology) in one specific field trial, it is assumed that all genotypes are exposed to the same environmental conditions. While this is correct if an average of all environmental traits is taken from sowing to harvest, it may not be when temperature and rainfall are determined at specific developmental stages. Since different genotypes attain a certain developmental stage at different points in time, weather data were collected and calculated for each genotype at key developmental stages. Specifically, temperature and rainfall were quantified and evaluated for the period 20 days before and after heading in a series of genotypes. The results presented here show that genotypes differing in their phenology were exposed to different temperatures and rainfall 20 days before and after heading. Primarily, DH positively correlated with temperature TA, TM, and Tm 20 days before and after heading. On average across locations and years, the effect of delaying heading by 1 day resulted in an increase of 0.16 and 0.14°C in temperature 20 days before and after heading, respectively (as shown by the regression line in 
 <bold class="bold">Figures 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1A,B</xref>
 </bold>). This means that two genotypes with a 10-day difference in heading may be exposed to a difference in temperature of up to 1.6 and 1.4°C (on average across locations and years) 20 days before or after heading. This increase in temperature of late genotypes led to shorter grain filling duration (
 <bold class="bold">Figures 
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1A,B</xref>
 </bold>) as shown by a negative correlation of temperature with GFD and DH with GFD. This is in agreement with 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bruckner and Frohberg (1987)</xref> where increasing temperature during grain filling in different genotypes tended to stop grain growth prematurely and to hasten physiological maturity.
</p>
