<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-ijerph-15-01547" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The method used in this study was collaborative conceptual modelling (CCM), which is a systems approach developed by Newell and Proust that has been explained elsewhere in greater detail [
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-15-01547">36</a>,
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-15-01547">42</a>]. This approach captures different viewpoints to create a shared understanding of the issue of interest, culminating in ‘dynamic hypotheses’ that describe simple feedback structures with the potential to dominate system behaviour. This understanding can be used as a basis for decision-making within the issue of interest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCM consists of a series of six co-evolving activities that can be tailored to suit the characteristics and objectives of the particular research. The activities conducted in this project were:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• What is the Challenge?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The step defines the key challenge faced in a particular situation and requires the input of a range of stakeholders. This activity was guided by a pre-existing conceptual model that was developed as part of the broader cluster and previously described by Proust el al [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-15-01547">42</a>]. The model, called the ‘Co-Effects Template’ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-01547-f001" href="#ijerph-15-01547-f001">Figure 1</a>), was developed after several individual project workshops, and a final integrative workshop with nine participants from projects cutting across topics of thermal stress, urban food systems, and climate change adaptation. The template captures a high-level view of the urban climate–health system that can be applied to multiple challenges.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• What is the Story?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second step considered the effect of past and current policies on trees in urban Perth. An existing review of the impact of historical planning policy and legislation on trees in Perth provided an assessment of previous policies. Content analysis of current planning policy documents was undertaken using a coding scheme based on key words related to vegetation, climate, and health. Similar approaches have been used in a textual analysis of the extent to which health is incorporated into the planning strategies of major Australian cities [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-15-01547">43</a>]. The policies reviewed were: Directions 2031; State Planning Policies of Urban Growth and Settlement and Residential Design Codes; Liveable Neighbourhoods; Capital City Planning Framework; and Climate Change Management Draft Guidelines (WA Local Government Association). A review of the State Emergency Response Plan for Heatwaves (WESTPLAN Heatwave) and the State Planning Policy for Natural Hazards and Disaster was also undertaken as part of this activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Can I see how you think?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This CCM activity reflects the need to share different perspectives (or mental models) of a particular issue to enhance understanding of the system, and was conducted as a half-day workshop. Key stakeholders with a clear connection to the issue were identified, including the state government (Departments of Health, Planning, Environment and Conservation and Water, the Environmental Protection Authority and the Building Commission), local government, private developers, academics, and professional institutes. A total of 32 representatives from the health, planning, development, and environment sectors across state and local government and the private sector attended the workshop. The key focus of the workshop was the level of tree canopy in areas targeted for urban infill. Each participant was provided with basic instructions on how to construct a simple model called an influence diagram. Influence diagrams are a simple qualitative systems model designed to capture the key interactions, including the feedback structure, of the topic of interest, and have been used to investigate health issues such as obesity, safety, and healthy eating habits [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-15-01547">38</a>,
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-15-01547">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-15-01547">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants were given 15 minutes to draw an individual influence diagram depicting their viewpoint of the issue, including: three to four key variables that have the largest influence on tree canopy levels in Perth; three to four of the most important effects of tree canopy; and feedback links between these variables. Each participant was then allocated a partner from a different sector and asked to explain their influence diagram. Each pair had 15 minutes to construct a ‘pair-blended’ diagram that integrated both viewpoints. The diagrams were presented and discussed at table groups, and were also displayed around the room for participants to review. The importance of how those involved in collaborative modelling articulate their own views and then develop a common understanding has been highlighted by Oppl [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-15-01547">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants were then divided into six groups and used the pair-blended influence diagrams to guide the selection of eight key variables influencing tree canopy management in urban infill areas. The involvement of people with relevant knowledge and expertise to construct models is likely to produce models that are more useful for informing work processes [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-15-01547">46</a>,
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-15-01547">47</a>]. A simple scoring system was utilized with each participant provided with three coloured stickers worth one, two, or three points that were assigned to the three most important variables. The scores were combined and the variables were ranked. Each group then discussed one of the top six variables. The discussion was guided by key categories of: opportunities, barriers, potential conflict or synergies with other activities or sectors, and the identification of key stakeholder groups. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• What drives system behaviour?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information from the policy review and workshop was analysed to identify key feedback structures and consider which elements of the system currently have the greatest level of influence over tree canopy levels. This informed the development of additional models that depict key system characteristics such as feedback loops and delays that typically drive system behaviour. As well as updated influence diagrams, other typical qualitative systems models such as stock-and-flow maps and system archetypes were developed [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-15-01547">30</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-15-01547">32</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-15-01547">37</a>,
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-15-01547">42</a>,
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-15-01547">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• What are the leverage points?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leverage points are places within a complex system where a small shift in one thing can produce significant and enduring changes in the system. Identification of these points was facilitated by a consideration of Meadows’ [
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-15-01547">49</a>] classification, which includes the mindset and goals of the system, the rules and who controls them, information and materials flows, feedback loops, and numbers such as subsidies and taxes. System archetypes, which are generic feedback structures with characteristic behaviour that occur in a wide range of situations, were also used in this step. An understanding of these structures and their behaviour can facilitate the identification of effective management strategies [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-15-01547">30</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-15-01547">32</a>,
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-15-01547">34</a>,
  <a rid="B50-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-15-01547">50</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">• Can we have new eyes?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The final activity of CCM reconsiders the original challenge defined in the first activity. The understanding gained from the CCM process supports new mental models or ‘new eyes’ that can help develop more effective management strategies to the challenge.</p>
</sec>
