<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-15-01547" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. What Is the Challenge?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first activity, ‘What is the Challenge?’, a variation of the Co-Effects Template was developed focusing on the selected challenges of temperature, urban form, and public health. The resulting conceptual model was named the Global–Local Model (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-01547-f002" href="#ijerph-15-01547-f002">Figure 2</a>), and highlights that the interaction between urban areas, temperature, and health occurs at the global and local scale.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The two loops of the model reflect the considerable differences in the spatial and temporal scales of the interactions between urban form and climate. The ‘Global Loop’ is relatively unresponsive to changes in local urban form due to the small fraction of global greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions from Perth, and the inertia of the climate system. This inertia results in a delay between GHG emissions and a change to the climate represented by the parallel lines on the link between ‘Urban form’ and ‘Global climate’. In contrast, the influence of the UHI effect in the ‘Local Loop’ is more immediate and determined by the natural and built characteristics of Perth. In terms of exposure to heat, strategies targeting the Local Loop represent the best opportunity at the local level to progress towards a more climate-resilient city. </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between urban form and local climate within the context of climate change is depicted in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-01547-f003" href="#ijerph-15-01547-f003">Figure 3</a>. The diagram shows how a shift in the distribution of climatic conditions affects the frequency of extreme temperatures. Panel (a) depicts the increased probability of hot weather and record hot weather as a result of climate change [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-15-01547">51</a>,
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-15-01547">52</a>], and panel (b) overlays a second shift that can occur in urban areas as a result of the UHI effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second shift in temperature distribution will present multiple challenges. The challenge selected for this study was the management of tree canopy in areas targeted for urban infill and higher densities.</p>
</sec>
