<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot5-ijerph-15-01547" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5. What Are the Leverage Points?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most powerful leverage point in Meadow’s list [
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-15-01547">49</a>] is paradigms. While paradigms are difficult to change, they have the potential to influence decision-making across all levels and aspects of the system. The paradigm shift required here is to move from a system dominated by narrow or short-term economic considerations to one that is based on a sustainable development paradigm that takes into account the environmental, social, and economic costs and benefits of tree canopy in urban areas for current and future generations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Goals capture the purpose or function of the system, and are a powerful leverage point because they are an indication of what we value most and can have a significant influence on all aspects of the system [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-15-01547" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-15-01547">31</a>]. While the study highlighted that there were clear goals for urban density targets, these were lacking for tree canopy. Introducing a specific goal or target for tree canopy levels would create a strong leverage point that could serve as an additional indicator of progress towards a more liveable city.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effective goals must be supported by rules such as policies and laws, incentives, constraints, and disincentives. If the goal of the system has been narrowed, the rules will tend to follow suit. The review of past and current policies and the findings of the workshop indicated that current rules do not provide adequate protection of tree canopy levels in Perth. Rules pertaining to tree planting and removal, on both private and public land, are critical. One example highlighted in the workshop was the need for rules to reduce the widespread practice of removing all vegetation, particularly mature trees, during urban development. The physical limitations created by other policies, such as zoning limitations, setback, and height limits and requirements for other infrastructure may severely limit the physical opportunities to incorporate trees into the urban design. If current rules discourage the inclusion of trees in urban design, these rules should be reconsidered. Community tree planting programs can play a significant role in tree management plans, and have the added advantage of increasing community awareness regarding the importance of trees in urban environments. However, these are typically limited to public land, so the influence on the critical space of private land is limited.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Information flows are strong leverage points in changing system behaviour. The study indicated that there are significant gaps and biases in the information flows of the system. In the absence of thorough tree canopy monitoring and reporting, tree canopy levels will continue to be largely overlooked. Improvements in information flows are also needed with respect to the links between tree canopy levels and a range of social, environmental, and economic factors. Responsibility for these factors is dispersed across many sectors, and highlights the need for a whole-of-government approach to manage tree canopy. </p>
</sec>
