<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To capture values of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> which are so high as to indicate that there is no climate in the reference period (within the current harvested area of the crop in question) from which to draw an analogue to the future climate, we calculate a threshold value of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub>, above which the analogue is considered too weak for conclusions regarding attainable yield to be drawn. To calculate 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub>, we randomly draw two sets of 19 individual years from the period 1981 to 2010 and assign one as climate ‘ref' and the other as climate ‘fut', and then calculate 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> as per Equation E1. We thereby calculate for each grid-cell a value of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> for the case when climates in each location are drawn from the same distribution, which we term 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">D</sub>. We then define 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub> as the characteristic maximum value of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">D</sub> (excluding outliers) by calculating its 95th percentile across the current harvested area of each crop. We thus follow the premise that for an analogue to be valid for projecting crop yield, the value of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> for that analogue must be similar to the 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic> calculated between two climates drawn from the same distribution. Taking the mean value of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub> per crop across the 5 GCM climates generates values of 0.7, 0.7 and 1.0 for maize wheat and rice, respectively. For simplicity, we take the most conservative of these, 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub>=0.7, as our baseline, however the projections of attainable yield are extremely robust to this choice (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 19</xref>). This definition of 
 <italic class="italic">SED</italic>
 <sub class="sub">t</sub> closely reflects the calculated gradients in this variable between typically cropped and non-cropped areas (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 1</xref>). We also use these two sets of 19 random years from the same climate distribution to show that the climate analogue method calculates only minimal changes in yield when the climate is unchanged (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Note 4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 20</xref>).
</p>
