<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Modeling with MaxEnt inevitably encounters the problems of over-fitting and threshold selection. The selection of thresholds determines the prediction accuracy of potential distribution areas of species. Usually we need to pay attention to the difference between climate suitability and habitat suitability. In addition to climate, other characteristics such as soil type, matrix composition, slope and watershed are also important factors to affect the habitat suitability of species [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. Due to the inadequate description of species environment requirements, the model may have the problem of being insufficient or over-fitting [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>]. In addition, predicting species distribution needs to take into account their own physiological constraints and competition of ecological communities. Many species are currently geographically distributed to higher altitudes and latitudes, and the rate of movement has even exceeded the previously reported rate [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Our model predicted that the movement of suitable areas for camphor tree to the northwest was also consistent with the climate change rate of the general warming in northern China [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>]. However, the rapid movement of species will inevitably affect the competition of bio-community populations, which may take decades or centuries for the richness and composition of the community to adapt to the current climate [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-03185" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Moreover, changes in the actual distribution of species need to consider many factors, such as the delay of species response to external factors, individual physiological limitations, and driving changes, which may cause species distribution to lag behind climate change. The niche model established in this study emphasized the survival probability of this species under different climatic conditions. Therefore, we estimated that the actual natural migration rate of the boundary range will be lower than the prediction of the niche model.
</p>
